<Article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Article.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Article
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			AM00021
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/AboutThisSite/AM00021
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2012-01-31
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2001-02-07
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			4F601D59-2A5D-9994-ECE38D71BB53586D
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
This health information is provided by Mayo Foundation for Medical Education and Research (&quot;MFMER&quot;). Use of this health information is governed by the terms and conditions of this Agreement. Please read this Agreement carefully before accessing or using this health information. Throughout this Agreement, MFMER is referred to as &quot;we&quot; or &quot;us.&quot; 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				General terms and conditions
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
By accessing or using this health information, you agree to be bound by all of the terms and conditions of this Agreement. This Agreement is intended to be fully effective and binding upon you and us. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We may modify this Agreement at any time, and you agree that such modifications will be effective immediately upon posting of the modified Agreement. You agree to review the Agreement each time you access this health information so that you are aware of any modifications made to this Agreement. By accessing or using this health information, you agree to be bound by all of the terms and conditions of the Agreement at the time of your access or use. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
YOU ACKNOWLEDGE AND AGREE THAT USE OF THIS HEALTH INFORMATION IS AT YOUR OWN RISK AND THAT THIS HEALTH INFORMATION IS PROVIDED ON AN &quot;AS IS&quot; BASIS. YOU UNDERSTAND AND AGREE THAT THIS HEALTH INFORMATION IS INTENDED FOR GENERAL CONSUMER UNDERSTANDING AND EDUCATION ONLY AND IS NOT INTENDED TO BE AND IS NOT A SUBSTITUTE FOR PROFESSIONAL MEDICAL ADVICE. ALWAYS SEEK THE ADVICE OF YOUR PHYSICIAN, NURSE OR OTHER QUALIFIED HEALTH CARE PROVIDER BEFORE YOU UNDERGO ANY TREATMENT OR FOR ANSWERS TO ANY QUESTIONS YOU MAY HAVE REGARDING A MEDICAL CONDITION. NOTHING CONTAINED IN THIS HEALTH INFORMATION IS INTENDED TO BE OR IS TO BE USED FOR MEDICAL DIAGNOSIS OR TREATMENT. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You understand and agree that, except for information, products, services or merchandise clearly identified as being supplied by us, we do not operate, control, supply, endorse, warrant or guarantee any information, products, services or merchandise available on the site that hosts this health information or through the Internet generally in any way. Mayo Clinic, MFMER and MayoClinic.com do not endorse any companies or products. You also understand and agree that we cannot and do not warrant or guarantee this health information will be free of infections or viruses, worms, Trojan horses or other code that contains contaminating or destructive properties. You understand and agree that you are solely responsible for implementing sufficient precautions, procedures and checkpoints to satisfy your own requirements for the accuracy of data input and output, and for maintaining a means external to the Service for the reconstruction of any lost data. We do not assume any responsibility for the loss of any information, data or other materials resulting from your use of the Service. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
YOU UNDERSTAND AND AGREE THAT WE DO NOT MAKE ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, REPRESENTATIONS OR ENDORSEMENTS OF ANY KIND WHATSOEVER (INCLUDING WITHOUT LIMITATION, WARRANTIES OF TITLE OR NONINFRINGEMENT, OR ANY WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE) WITH REGARD TO THE HEALTH INFORMATION OR WITH RESPECT TO ANY INFORMATION, PRODUCT, SERVICE, MERCHANDISE OR OTHER MATERIAL PROVIDED IN THE HEALTH INFORMATION. WE DO NOT WARRANT OR GUARANTEE THE ACCURACY, COMPLETENESS, CORRECTNESS, TIMELINESS OR USEFULNESS OF ANY INFORMATION, PRODUCTS, SERVICES, MERCHANDISE OR OTHER MATERIAL PROVIDED IN OR THROUGH THE HEALTH INFORMATION OR ON THE INTERNET GENERALLY. IN NO EVENT WILL WE BE LIABLE TO YOU OR ANYONE ELSE FOR ANY DECISION MADE OR ACTION TAKEN BY YOU OR ANYONE ELSE IN RELIANCE UPON THE INFORMATION CONTAINED ON OR PROVIDED THROUGH THE SERVICE. YOU UNDERSTAND AND AGREE THAT IN NO EVENT SHALL WE BE LIABLE TO YOU OR ANY OTHER USER OF THE SERVICE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, CONSEQUENTIAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, PUNITIVE, OR ANY OTHER MONETARY OR OTHER DAMAGES, FEES, FINES, PENALTIES, LOSS OF REVENUE OR BUSINESS, OR LIABILITIES ARISING OUT OF OR RELATING IN ANY WAY TO THIS HEALTH INFORMATION. YOU ACKNOWLEDGE AND AGREE THAT YOUR SOLE AND EXCLUSIVE REMEDY FOR DISSATISFACTION WITH THIS HEALTH INFORMATION IS TO STOP USING THE SERVICE. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you are located in any jurisdiction in the world where the common, statutory, regulatory or codified law of such jurisdiction would void this Agreement in whole or in any essential part (the essential parts being at least, but not only, the exclusive jurisdiction and venue and exclusive remedy provisions, the warranty disclaimers, the limitations of liability, and the privacy guidelines and terms of use), or would make accessing this health information illegal, then you are not authorized to use the health information and, if you do so, you do so entirely at your own risk. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You agree to indemnify us and any of our parent or subsidiary companies or organizations, and any of our successors, assigns or licensees, together with any of their respective officers, directors and employees, against any damages, losses, liabilities, judgments, costs or expenses (including reasonable attorneys&apos; fees and costs) arising out of a claim by a third party relating to your use of the health information, or any breach or violation of this Agreement. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You agree that this Agreement is entered into between you and us in the State of Minnesota, United States of America, and is performed within the State of Minnesota and governed by and shall be construed in all respects under the laws of the State of Minnesota, exclusive of its choice of law or conflict of laws provisions. In any claim or action by you directly or indirectly arising under this Agreement or related to the health information, you and we each irrevocably agree to submit to the exclusive personal jurisdiction of the Minnesota State District Court sitting in Olmsted County, Minn., or if such court does not have subject matter jurisdiction, then you and we each irrevocably agree to submit to the exclusive personal jurisdiction of the United States Court for the District of Minnesota, and whichever of those two courts has jurisdiction, you and we each waive any jurisdictional, venue or inconvenient forum objections to such court. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If any of the provisions of this Agreement are held by a court or other tribunal of competent jurisdiction to be not enforceable, then such provisions shall be limited or eliminated to the minimum extent necessary so that this Agreement shall otherwise remain in full force and effect. This Agreement constitutes the entire agreement between you and us relating to the subject matter hereof and supersedes and merges herein any prior promises, agreements or understanding between you and us relating to any of the subject matters of this Agreement. This Agreement may not be modified, in whole or in part, except as described elsewhere in this Agreement. Anything contained on the Service inconsistent with or conflicting with the terms of this Agreement is superseded by the terms of this Agreement. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The marks &quot;Mayo,&quot; &quot;Mayo Clinic,&quot; &quot;MayoClinic.com,&quot; &quot;EmbodyHealth&quot; and the triple-shield Mayo Clinic logo are trademarks of Mayo Foundation for Medical Education and Research. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The health information is copyrighted by us and/or other applicable rights holders. You may download and reprint a single copy of the materials from the Service for your own personal, noncommercial use only, provided you include all applicable notices and disclaimers. Any other use of the materials is strictly prohibited without our prior written permission and the permission of the applicable rights holder(s). 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Terms of use for licensed content
	</Title>
	<Abstract />
	<BenefitSummary />
</Article>
