<Answer xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Answer.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Answer
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			AN01688
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/thin-skin/AN01688
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2011-09-27
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2007-09-26
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1128" Title="80 and over" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1001" Title="Diseases and conditions">
				<Keyword MCVID="1158" Title="Skin hair and nails">
					<Keyword MCVID="1838" Title="Skin">
						<Keyword MCVID="3088" Title="General" />
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			4B1733FC-E7FF-0DBD-1A78EBD1BDF170DD
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				thin skin
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				thinning skin
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				fragile skin
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				weak skin
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Fragile or thin skin that tears easily is a fairly common problem, especially in older adults. Aging, sun exposure and genetics all play a role in thinning skin. Certain medications, such as long-term use of oral or topical corticosteroids, can also weaken skin and the blood vessels in the skin.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thin skin isn&apos;t necessarily a sign of a serious underlying medical condition but should be evaluated by a doctor to determine its cause. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To protect thin skin and prevent tears and cuts:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Wear long-sleeved shirts, long pants and wide-brimmed hats.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Avoid prolonged sun exposure.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;If you must be outside in the sun, use a broad-spectrum sunscreen with a sun protection factor (SPF) of at least 15. Apply sunscreen generously, and reapply every two hours &amp;mdash; or more often if you&apos;re swimming or perspiring.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Keep skin well moisturized and protected by using a quality moisturizing cream, such as Vanicream, Cetaphil or Eucerin.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Talk to your doctor about treating skin with vitamin A (retinol) which may improve the skin&apos;s ability to tolerate injuries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Thin skin? Added protection helps
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Fragile or thin skin is a fairly common problem, especially in older adults.
	</Abstract>
	<Question>
		My mother is 85 years old. Her skin is so thin that if she bumps against something, her skin tears open. Why is this, and what can we do about it?
	</Question>
	<QuestionFirstName>
		No name
	</QuestionFirstName>
	<QuestionState>
		No state given
	</QuestionState>
	<BenefitSummary />
</Answer>
