<Answer xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Answer.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Answer
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			AN01179
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/leg-pain/AN01179
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2011-10-05
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2005-09-02
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="3328" Title="Symptom">
				<Keyword MCVID="3342" Title="Bones joints and muscles">
					<Keyword MCVID="3558" Title="Leg pain" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			E0F12C22-F693-432F-B4E7A075E9231DD8
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				leg pain
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				leg aches
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				leg ache
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				aching legs
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				leg pains
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
New, persistent leg pain certainly warrants a visit to your doctor for evaluation. Leg pain can have many causes, but your description of aching after prolonged standing or sitting suggests a possible buildup of fluid in the leg veins (venous congestion).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Venous congestion occurs when the valves in your leg veins don&apos;t work properly to keep blood moving efficiently from your legs to your heart &amp;mdash; a condition called venous insufficiency. Instead, blood pools in your legs and feet, causing pain and, frequently, swelling. People with venous congestion typically describe the pain as a burning or cramping sensation, mainly in the calf.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Past inflammation of a vein (phlebitis) may damage the valves and lead to venous congestion. Poor function of the valves in the leg veins also contributes to varicose veins &amp;mdash; distended veins visible just beneath the skin. Varicose veins also may lead to venous congestion. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Wearing knee-high support hose may be worth a try to ease discomfort associated with fluid buildup in the legs. Ask your doctor for a recommendation.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Leg pain after prolonged standing or sitting: A concern?
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		New, persistent leg pain or aching may indicate an underlying circulation problem.
	</Abstract>
	<Question>
		Lately, I&apos;ve had a lot of leg pain, especially when sitting at my desk or standing in line at the store. Should I be concerned about this new aching?
	</Question>
	<QuestionFirstName>
		No name
	</QuestionFirstName>
	<QuestionState>
		No state given
	</QuestionState>
	<BenefitSummary />
</Answer>
