<Answer xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Answer.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Answer
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			AN02095
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/bezoars/AN02095
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2012-08-28
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2010-06-30
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1001" Title="Diseases and conditions">
				<Keyword MCVID="1137" Title="Digestive system">
					<Keyword MCVID="1846" Title="Stomach">
						<Keyword MCVID="2980" Title="Gastroparesis" />
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			D110E26D-BFEF-64E9-B8041285454A58A6
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				bezoars
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				phytobezoar
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				trichobezoar
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				pharmacobezoar
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
A bezoar (BE-zor) is a solid mass of indigestible material that accumulates in your digestive tract, sometimes causing a blockage. Bezoars usually form in the stomach, sometimes in the small intestine or, rarely, the large intestine. They can occur in children and adults. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bezoars occur most often in people with certain risk factors, including if you: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Had gastric surgery that results in delayed stomach emptying&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Have decreased stomach size or reduced stomach acid production&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Have diabetes or end-stage kidney disease &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Receive breathing help with mechanical ventilation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One type of bezoar (trichobezoar) may occur in people with psychiatric illness or developmental disabilities. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bezoars are classified according to the material that forms them: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phytobezoars&lt;/strong&gt; are composed of indigestible food fibers, such as cellulose. These fibers occur in fruits and vegetables, including celery, pumpkin, prunes, raisins, leeks, beets, persimmons and sunflower-seed shells. Phytobezoars are the most common type of bezoar.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trichobezoars&lt;/strong&gt; are composed of hair or hair-like fibers, such as carpet or clothing fibers. In severe cases, known as &quot;Rapunzel&apos;s syndrome,&quot; the compacted fibers can fill the stomach with a tail extending into the small intestine. Rapunzel&apos;s syndrome is most common in adolescent girls.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pharmacobezoars&lt;/strong&gt; are composed of medications that don&apos;t properly dissolve in your digestive tract.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bezoars can cause lack of appetite, nausea, vomiting, weight loss and a feeling of fullness after eating only a little food. Bezoars can also cause gastric ulcers, intestinal bleeding and obstruction, leading to tissue death (gangrene) in a portion of the digestive tract. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Small bezoars may pass through the digestive tract on their own or after you take medication to help dissolve the mass. Severe cases, especially large trichobezoars, often require surgery. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you don&apos;t have one of the risk factors for bezoars, you&apos;re not likely to develop them. If you are at risk, reducing your intake of foods with high amounts of indigestible cellulose may reduce your risk. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Bezoars: What foods can cause this digestive problem?
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Bezoars are masses of organic and inorganic matter trapped in the digestive system.
	</Abstract>
	<Question>
		I&apos;ve heard that eating certain foods can cause bezoars. What are bezoars?
	</Question>
	<QuestionFirstName>
		No name
	</QuestionFirstName>
	<QuestionState>
		No state given
	</QuestionState>
	<BenefitSummary />
	<RelatedLinksBox>
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00612" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="B8FD8052-2A5D-9994-E3D7A1ECF01522DF" Title="Gastroparesis" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/gastroparesis/DS00612" />
	</RelatedLinksBox>
</Answer>
