<Answer xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Answer.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Answer
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			AN02112
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/dry-mouth/AN02112
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2013-07-23
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2010-10-30
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1001" Title="Diseases and conditions">
				<Keyword MCVID="1360" Title="Mouth and teeth">
					<Keyword MCVID="1637" Title="Salivary gland">
						<Keyword MCVID="1638" Title="Dry mouth" />
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			DD01E32A-FD29-FA5D-782DA18557763A5C
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				dry mouth
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				dry mouth treatment
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				xerostomia
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				dry mouth relief
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				relief for dry mouth
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				xerostomia
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
The best way to treat dry mouth &amp;mdash; known medically as xerostomia (zeer-o-STOE-me-uh) &amp;mdash; depends on what&apos;s causing it. You can do some things to relieve dry mouth temporarily. But for the best long-term dry mouth remedy, you need to address its cause. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To relieve your dry mouth: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chew sugar-free gum&lt;/strong&gt; or suck on sugar-free hard candies to stimulate the flow of saliva. For some people, xylitol, which is often found in sugar-free gum or sugar-free candies, may cause diarrhea or cramps if consumed in large amounts.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Limit your caffeine intake&lt;/strong&gt; because caffeine can make your mouth drier.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don&apos;t use mouthwashes that contain alcohol&lt;/strong&gt; because they can be drying.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stop all tobacco use&lt;/strong&gt; if you smoke or chew tobacco.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sip water&lt;/strong&gt; regularly.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Try over-the-counter saliva substitutes&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;mdash; look for products containing xylitol, such as Mouth Kote or Oasis Moisturizing Mouth Spray, or ones containing carboxymethylcellulose (kahr-bok-see-meth-ul-SEL-u-lohs) or hydroxyethyl cellulose (hi-drok-see-ETH-ul SEL-u-lohs), such as Biotene Oral Balance.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Try a mouthwash designed for dry mouth&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;mdash; especially one that contains xylitol, such as Biotene Dry Mouth Oral Rinse or ACT Total Care Dry Mouth Rinse, which also offer protection against tooth decay.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid using over-the-counter antihistamines and decongestants&lt;/strong&gt; because they can make your symptoms worse.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breathe through your nose,&lt;/strong&gt; not your mouth.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add moisture to the air at night&lt;/strong&gt; with a room humidifier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Saliva is important to maintain the health of your teeth and mouth. If you frequently have a dry mouth, taking these steps to protect your oral health may also help your condition: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid sugary or acidic foods&lt;/strong&gt; and candies because they increase the risk of tooth decay.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brush with a fluoride toothpaste.&lt;/strong&gt; Ask your dentist if you might benefit from prescription fluoride toothpaste.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use a fluoride rinse&lt;/strong&gt; or brush-on fluoride gel before bedtime.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visit your dentist at least twice yearly&lt;/strong&gt; to detect and treat tooth decay or other dental problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If these steps don&apos;t improve your dry mouth, talk to your doctor or dentist. The cause could be a medication or another condition. Medications are one of the most common causes of dry mouth. Long-term relief from your dry mouth may mean stopping or changing your medication or its dosage, or addressing underlying health issues. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Dry mouth treatment: Tips for controlling dry mouth
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Dry mouth: If you have dry mouth, try these tips for relief.
	</Abstract>
	<Question>
		I frequently have a dry mouth. What can I do to relieve this problem?
	</Question>
	<QuestionFirstName>
		No name
	</QuestionFirstName>
	<QuestionState>
		No state given
	</QuestionState>
	<BenefitSummary />
	<RelatedLinksBox>
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="HA00034" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="50B3D1EF-C44D-46A3-A5E06F9AC4F2A836" Title="Dry mouth" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/dry-mouth/HA00034" />
	</RelatedLinksBox>
</Answer>
