<Answer xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Answer.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Answer
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			AN02124
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/terrible-twos/AN02124
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2013-03-09
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2010-12-16
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1118" Title="Child">
					<Keyword MCVID="1120" Title="02 months to 2 years infant/toddler">
						<Keyword MCVID="3526" Title="16 months to 2 years toddler">
							<Keyword MCVID="3534" Title="2 years" />
						</Keyword>
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1463" Title="Life stage">
				<Keyword MCVID="1533" Title="Children">
					<Keyword MCVID="3747" Title="Infants and toddlers">
						<Keyword MCVID="3751" Title="Toddler health" />
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			FCB14F8F-938E-3AF0-480E988F9A36BC57
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				terrible twos
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
The terrible twos are a normal stage in a toddler&apos;s development characterized by mood changes, temper tantrums and use of the word &quot;no.&quot; The terrible twos typically occur when toddlers begin to struggle between their reliance on adults and their desire for independence. One minute a child might be clinging to mom or dad, and the next he or she is running in the opposite direction. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While the terrible twos can be difficult for parents and caregivers to navigate, keep in mind that 2-year-olds are undergoing major motor, intellectual, social and emotional changes. Their vocabularies are growing, they&apos;re eager to do things on their own, and they&apos;re beginning to discover that they&apos;re expected to follow certain rules. However, most 2-year-olds still aren&apos;t able to move as swiftly as they&apos;d like, clearly communicate their needs or control their feelings. This can lead to frustration and misbehavior &amp;mdash; in other words, the terrible twos. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If your child is in the midst of the terrible twos, expect that you&apos;ll occasionally lose patience with each other. Try to stay calm, however. When your child has a temper tantrum, offer comfort or ignore the behavior. Try to limit your use of the word &quot;no.&quot; Instead, use other forms of discipline, such as redirection or humor. Also, consider avoiding challenging situations &amp;mdash; such as going shopping during your child&apos;s nap time &amp;mdash; and be sure to praise your child for appropriate behavior. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
By accepting the changes your child is going through and showing him or her love and respect, you&apos;ll help your child make it through this difficult stage with confidence. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Terrible twos: Why are 2-year-olds so difficult?
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Find out how to help your toddler navigate the terrible twos.
	</Abstract>
	<Question>
		I&apos;ve heard a lot about the terrible twos. Why are 2-year-olds so difficult?
	</Question>
	<QuestionFirstName />
	<QuestionState />
	<BenefitSummary />
	<RelatedLinksBox>
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY02313" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="439F1D2B-90AA-B7DB-E6A5A343B07DB431" Title="Child development: Know what&apos;s ahead" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/child-development/MY02313" />
	</RelatedLinksBox>
</Answer>
