<SlideShow xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="SlideShow.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			SlideShow
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			AR00027
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/joint-protection/AR00027
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2012-06-12
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2002-11-20
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1001" Title="Diseases and conditions">
				<Keyword MCVID="1133" Title="Bones joints and muscles">
					<Keyword MCVID="1403" Title="Arthritis" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			55609D76-3CDE-46D9-86B8AE68C63EE763
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				joint protection
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				joint pain
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				body mechanics
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				arthritis
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				hand pain
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				hand arthritis
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				finger arthritis
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				rheumatoid arthritis
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				osteoarthritis
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Title>
		Slide show: Joint protection for people with hand arthritis
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Joint protection &amp;mdash; pictures showing joint protection techniques to avoid hand arthritis pain.
	</Abstract>
	<Slides>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				&lt;p&gt;
People with hand arthritis should avoid pinching items between their thumb and forefinger because this puts extra stress on already painful joints. Try adding a short length of foam tubing over the handles of toothbrushes and eating utensils. Certain types of pipe insulation tubing, which can be found at hardware stores, may be useful. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Toothbrushes
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photos showing toothbrushes with and without foam handles.
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				320
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/mcdc22_ergo_toothbrush.gif
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				&lt;p&gt;
Many kitchen tools, such as vegetable peelers, can now be purchased with larger handles. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Large-handled tools
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photo of a vegetable peeler with a large, cushioned handle.
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				320
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/mcdc22_ergo_peeler.jpg
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				&lt;p&gt;
This turning tool features a collection of collapsible metal pins. These pins individually depress so they can mold around objects such as oven knobs and the ends of car or house keys. Using the large handle on the tool helps people avoid the pinching motion required to turn knobs and keys. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Turning tool
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photos of a pin tool engaging a house key.
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				320
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/mcdc22_turn_tool.jpg
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				&lt;p&gt;
Larger barrel pens &amp;mdash; as well as rubbery grips that can be installed over narrow pens and pencils &amp;mdash; can reduce stress on finger and thumb joints. Some pens are designed to be worn on a finger, while others are shaped like a Y so your forefinger can rest on top of the pen. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Pens and pencils
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photo showing a variety of pens designed to reduce stress on finger and thumb joints.
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				320
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/mcdc22_ergo_pens.jpg
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				This type of kitchen knife allows your hand and wrist to stay in a more neutral position, avoiding the pinch grip used with traditional knives. Use an electric food processor to chop large quantities of vegetables.
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Kitchen knife
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photo of a kitchen knife with a handle similar to a saw.
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				320
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/mcdc22_ergo_knife.jpg
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				This type of cutting board may help protect hand joints by reducing the amount of force needed to hold on to food while chopping. The nail pegs and raised ledge help secure food during meal preparation.
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Cutting board
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photo of cutting board with nail pegs.
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				320
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/mcdc22_cutting_board.jpg
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				When you&apos;re faced with a stubborn jar lid or bottle cap, many different types of opening devices can reduce the amount of stress placed on your hand joints. For cans, use an electric can opener to avoid the finger strain of turning a hand-held model.
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Jar openers
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photos of two types of jar-opening devices.
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				320
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/mcdc22_ergo_jars.jpg
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				In normal scissors, your hand must work to open the scissors as well as close them. Spring-loaded scissors open automatically, which reduces joint strain.
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Automatic scissors
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photo of scissors that open automatically.
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				320
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/mcdc22_ergo_scissors.jpg
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				&lt;p&gt;
To protect your finger joints, avoid tightly pinching with your fingers. For example, use a buttonhook to help you grasp and fasten buttons on your clothes. Choose clothes with easy-to-close fasteners, such as zippers, large buttons or hooks. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Buttonhook
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photo of a device that helps button clothes.
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				320
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/mcdc22_buttonhook.jpg
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				Squeezing a doorknob can be hard on finger joints. A lever attachment makes it easier to open the door.
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Doorknob lever
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photo of a lever that attaches to doorknobs.
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				320
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/mcdc22_ergo_doorknob.jpg
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				Avoid suspending the entire weight of a heavy briefcase or purse in your fingers. Use a shoulder strap instead.
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Shoulder straps
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photo of a woman carrying a large purse by its shoulder strap across her body.
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				320
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/mcdc22_heavy_bag.jpg
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				&lt;p&gt;
Use your palms to hold an object when you can, such as when reading a book or magazine. This helps you avoid bending the large knuckles of your hand while keeping your finger joints straight. Or try placing reading materials flat on a table or on a pillow in your lap to avoid grasping the items with your hands. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Holding a book
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Animation showing incorrect and correct ways to hold a book.
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				320
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/mcdc22_holding_book.gif
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				&lt;p&gt;
Use your legs to help you stand up. If necessary, push off on the arms of the chair or a nearby table with your palms &amp;mdash; not your knuckles. Another option is to place your palms on your thighs or knees to push off. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Getting up from a chair
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photos showing ways to rise from a chair that are easier on hand joints.
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				320
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/mcdc22_chair_rise.gif
			</URI>
		</Slide>
	</Slides>
</SlideShow>
