<Article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Article.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Article
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			CA00019
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/chewing-tobacco/CA00019
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2011-10-29
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2001-06-27
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1006" Title="Lifestyle">
				<Keyword MCVID="1255" Title="Quit smoking">
					<Keyword MCVID="4017" Title="Quit-smoking basics" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			BDFA0D03-F8D7-42B2-A8D23038227F0F3A
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				Chewing tobacco
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				spit
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				smokeless
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				smokeless tobacco
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				smokefree tobacco
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				smoke-free tobacco
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				spit tobacco
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				spitting tobacco
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				oral tobacco
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				dip
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				snuff
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				chew
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				chaw
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				oral cancer
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				pinch
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				plug
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				snus
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				leukoplakia
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				dipping
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				tobacco twist
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				tobacco plug
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				spit-free tobacco
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				spitless tobacco
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				dissolvable tobacco
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				ariva
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				stonewall
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				nicotine replacement therapy
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				snuff dipper
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
You can call chewing tobacco by whatever name you want &amp;mdash; smokeless tobacco, spit tobacco, chew, snuff, pinch or dip &amp;mdash; but don&apos;t call it harmless. Whether you use chewing tobacco or other types of smokeless tobacco because you like it or because you think smokeless is safer than cigarettes, be forewarned &amp;mdash; chewing tobacco can cause serious health problems. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Chewing tobacco and other forms of smokeless tobacco
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Chewing tobacco is a common type of smokeless tobacco. Smokeless tobacco products consist of tobacco or a tobacco blend that&apos;s chewed, sucked on or sniffed, rather than smoked. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are many types of smokeless tobacco products around the world. In the United States, the main types of smokeless tobacco are: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Snuff.&lt;/strong&gt; This is finely ground or shredded tobacco leaves. It&apos;s available in dry or moist forms and is packaged in tins or tea bag-like pouches. A pinch of snuff is placed between the lower lip and gum or cheek and gum. Dry forms of snuff can be sniffed into the nose. Using snuff is also called dipping. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chewing tobacco.&lt;/strong&gt; This consists of loose tobacco leaves that are sweetened and packaged in pouches. You put a wad of the tobacco between your cheek and gum and hold it there, sometimes for hours at a time. It&apos;s also called chew and chaw. Usually you spit out the tobacco juices, but if you&apos;re more addicted, you may tend to swallow some of the juices. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Snus.&lt;/strong&gt; Snus (pronounced snoos) is a newer smokeless, spitless tobacco product that originated in Sweden. It comes in a pouch that you stick between your upper lip and gum. You leave it there for about a half-hour without having to spit, then discard it.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dissolvable tobacco.&lt;/strong&gt; These are pieces of compressed powdered tobacco, similar to small hard candies. They dissolve in your mouth, requiring no spitting of tobacco juices. They&apos;re sometimes called tobacco lozenges, but they&apos;re not the same as the nicotine lozenges used to help you quit smoking.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other products.&lt;/strong&gt; In some parts of the country, smokeless tobacco also comes in the form of plugs and twists. Plugs are tobacco compressed into a brick shape, and twists are braided and twisted tobacco. You hold a piece between your cheek and gum, and spit out the tobacco juices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Health risks of chewing tobacco and other forms of smokeless tobacco
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
While the available evidence shows that smokeless tobacco may be less dangerous than cigarettes are, long-term use of chewing tobacco and other smokeless tobacco products can cause serious health problems. That&apos;s because they can contain about 30 cancer-causing substances. Like cigarettes, smokeless tobacco also contains nicotine, which can cause you to become addicted. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&apos;s a look at some of the health problems related to smokeless tobacco: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Addiction.&lt;/strong&gt; Because smokeless tobacco contains nicotine, you can get addicted, just as you can with cigarettes and other tobacco products. Your body may actually absorb as much nicotine from chewing tobacco or snuff as it does from cigarettes. Just as with smoking, withdrawal from smokeless tobacco causes signs and symptoms such as intense cravings, increased appetite, irritability and depressed mood.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cancer.&lt;/strong&gt; Your risk of certain types of cancer increases if you use chewing tobacco or other types of smokeless tobacco. This includes esophageal cancer and various types of oral cancer, including cancers of your mouth, throat, cheek, gums, lips and tongue. You also face increased risks related to pancreatic cancer and kidney cancer. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cavities.&lt;/strong&gt; Chewing tobacco and other forms of smokeless tobacco cause tooth decay. That&apos;s because chewing tobacco contains high amounts of sugar, which contributes to cavities. Chewing tobacco also contains coarse particles that can irritate your gums and scratch away at the enamel on your teeth, making your teeth more vulnerable to cavities. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gum disease.&lt;/strong&gt; The sugar and irritants in chewing tobacco and other forms of smokeless tobacco can cause your gums to pull away from your teeth in the area of your mouth where you place the chew. Over time you can develop gum disease, which can be severe enough to destroy the soft tissue and bone that support your teeth (periodontitis) and lead to tooth loss. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Heart disease.&lt;/strong&gt; Smokeless tobacco increases your heart rate and blood pressure. Some evidence suggests that long-term use of smokeless tobacco increases your risk of dying of certain types of heart disease and stroke. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Precancerous mouth lesions.&lt;/strong&gt; Smokeless tobacco increases your risk of developing small white patches called leukoplakia (loo-koh-PLAY-kee-uh) inside your mouth where the chew is most often placed. These mouth lesions are precancerous &amp;mdash; meaning that the lesions could one day become cancer. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Quitting chewing tobacco and other forms of smokeless tobacco
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
If you use chewing tobacco or other forms of smokeless tobacco, quit. Now that you know the dangers associated with it, you have extra motivation to stop using smokeless tobacco. And if you&apos;re trying to stop using cigarettes, don&apos;t switch to smokeless tobacco instead. While smokeless tobacco may be safer than cigarettes, smokeless tobacco hasn&apos;t been shown to help you stop smoking. In fact, you may end up using both cigarettes and smokeless tobacco. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To stop using any tobacco product, start by talking to your doctor. Or talk to a counselor by calling 1-800-QUIT-NOW (800-784-8669). Your doctor or counselor can guide you in creating a quit plan and choosing nicotine replacement products or medications to help ensure success. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Chewing tobacco: Not a safe alternative to cigarettes
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Chewing tobacco &amp;mdash; Chewing tobacco and other forms of smokeless tobacco pose numerous health risks.
	</Abstract>
	<BenefitSummary>
		Get the facts about chewing tobacco and other forms of smokeless tobacco. They&apos;re more harmful and addictive than you might think.
	</BenefitSummary>
	<RelatedLinksBox>
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="SN00003" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="EFC4004C-25CE-4C77-925237045078807F" Title="Skin care: 5 tips for healthy skin" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/skin-care/SN00003" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="SA00082" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="686E87EE-DBEB-4259-A5906A4CF2A10A02" Title="Massage: Get in touch with its many benefits" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/massage/SA00082" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00024" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="2FEC5C54-5C57-48E2-A445C46DCF50C26C" Title="Cancer prevention: 7 tips to reduce your risk" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer-prevention/CA00024" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CC00023" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="055661AE-8008-40C8-A8526ED085B5CCC1" Title="Secondhand smoke: Avoid dangers in the air" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/secondhand-smoke/CC00023" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01515" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="CED26BBD-E7FF-0DBD-1390ACCE0720404F" Title="Cigar smoking: Safer than cigarette smoking?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cigar-smoking/AN01515" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN00644" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="BA5F698E-310B-499D-B596C3533F2EB8F8" Title="Smoking: Does it cause wrinkles?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/smoking/AN00644" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Video" DocID="MM00778" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="892C86D5-C9C5-C307-16A58B138ACC4EAD" Title="Video: Smoking &amp;mdash; Anatomy of nicotine addiction" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/nicotine-addiction/MM00778" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN02025" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="4D2590EA-0930-6B26-63A5F2E10E6D3BF8" Title="Electronic cigarettes: A safe way to light up?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/electronic-cigarettes/AN02025" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01265" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="3B9B78F5-2A5D-9994-E56E1D483F29CF3C" Title="Hookah smoking: Is it safer than cigarettes?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/hookah/AN01265" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00307" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="E730A942-E51B-4419-950BE71044E9F4AF" Title="Nicotine dependence" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/nicotine-dependence/DS00307" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00025" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="C4A9C39B-7930-4617-AFED8E7692E3139A" Title="Bad breath" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/bad-breath/DS00025" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00038" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="06A75328-0BC3-47E7-A00ADDC9B0E319C4" Title="Lung cancer" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/lung-cancer/DS00038" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY00781" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="5C2B0722-A345-B26A-941F357405C4BA43" Title="Quit-smoking products: Boost your chance of quitting for good" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/quit-smoking-products/MY00781" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="SK00057" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="51BBEF05-E7FF-0DBD-115668D65EC3E3BA" Title="Quitting smoking: 10 ways to resist tobacco cravings" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/nicotine-craving/SK00057" />
	</RelatedLinksBox>
</Article>
