<Article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Article.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Article
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			CM00002
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer-treatment/CM00002
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2012-01-19
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2003-12-15
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1001" Title="Diseases and conditions">
				<Keyword MCVID="1136" Title="Cancer">
					<Keyword MCVID="2082" Title="General" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			B3599E9F-4C7B-4CA3-86132BAA54B5B549
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				cancer treatment
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				oncology and treatment
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				alternative cancer treatments
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				cancer
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				complementary
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				complementary and alternative
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				CAM and cancer
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Many people with cancer are interested in trying anything that may help them, including complementary and alternative cancer treatments. If cancer makes you feel as if you have little control over your health, alternative cancer treatments may offer some feeling of control. But many alternative cancer treatments are unproved and many are even dangerous. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To help you sort out the good from the bad, here are 11 alternative cancer treatments that are generally safe. Plus, there is some evidence that these 11 alternative cancer treatments may provide some benefit. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				How can alternative medicine help people with cancer?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Alternative cancer treatments won&apos;t play any role in curing your cancer, but they may help you cope with signs and symptoms caused by cancer and cancer treatments. Common signs and symptoms such as anxiety, fatigue, nausea and vomiting, pain, difficulty sleeping, and stress may be lessened by alternative treatments. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Use alternative cancer treatments as a supplement to treatments you receive from your doctor &amp;mdash; not as a substitute for medical care. While alternative cancer treatments, such as acupuncture, may reduce nausea or pain, they generally aren&apos;t powerful enough to replace medications from your doctor. Work closely with your doctor to determine the right balance between traditional medicines and alternative cancer treatments. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;mctable&quot;&gt;
&lt;table border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
	&lt;tbody&gt;
		&lt;tr&gt;
			&lt;th width=&quot;40%&quot;&gt;If you&apos;re experiencing&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th width=&quot;60%&quot;&gt;Then consider trying&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;
		&lt;tr&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Anxiety&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Hypnosis, massage, meditation, relaxation techniques&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;
		&lt;tr class=&quot;bodyrow&quot;&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Fatigue&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Exercise, massage, relaxation techniques, yoga&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;
		&lt;tr&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Nausea and vomiting&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Acupuncture, aromatherapy, hypnosis, music therapy&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;
		&lt;tr class=&quot;bodyrow&quot;&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Pain&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Acupuncture, aromatherapy, biofeedback, hypnosis, massage, music therapy&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;
		&lt;tr&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Sleep problems&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Exercise, relaxation techniques, yoga&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;
		&lt;tr class=&quot;bodyrow&quot;&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Stress&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Aromatherapy, exercise, hypnosis, massage, meditation, tai chi, yoga&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Which alternative cancer treatments are worth trying?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
These 11 alternative cancer treatments have shown some promise in helping people with cancer. Talk to your doctor if you&apos;re interested in trying: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Acupuncture.&lt;/strong&gt; During acupuncture treatment, a practitioner inserts tiny needles into your skin at precise points. Studies show acupuncture may be helpful in relieving nausea caused by chemotherapy. Acupuncture may also help relieve certain types of pain in people with cancer. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	Acupuncture is safe if it&apos;s performed by a licensed practitioner using sterile needles. Ask your doctor for names of trusted practitioners. Acupuncture isn&apos;t safe if you&apos;re taking blood thinners or if you have low blood counts, so check with your doctor first. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Aromatherapy.&lt;/strong&gt; Aromatherapy uses fragrant oils to provide a calming sensation. Oils, infused with scents such as lavender, can be applied to your skin during a massage or the oils can be added to bath water. Fragrant oils also can be heated to release their scents into the air. Aromatherapy may be helpful in relieving nausea, pain and stress. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	Aromatherapy can be performed by a practitioner, or you can use aromatherapy on your own. Aromatherapy is safe, though oils applied to your skin can cause allergic reactions. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Biofeedback.&lt;/strong&gt; You use your mind to control various body functions, such as heart rate and blood flow, during biofeedback therapy. A biofeedback therapist uses an electronic device to monitor a specific body function, such as muscle tension or your heart rate. The device uses a beeping sound or a flashing light as cues, for instance, to tell you that your heart rate is slowing down or your muscles are becoming more relaxed. Working with the biofeedback therapist, you learn to control these functions by paying attention to the cues. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	Biofeedback may be helpful in relieving pain in people with cancer. Biofeedback is safe when you work with a certified biofeedback therapist. With practice, you can learn to do biofeedback on your own. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Exercise.&lt;/strong&gt; Exercise may help you manage signs and symptoms during and after cancer treatment. Gentle exercise, such as walking or swimming, may help relieve fatigue and stress and help you sleep better. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	If you haven&apos;t already been exercising regularly, check with your doctor before you begin an exercise program. Start slowly, adding more exercise as you go. Aim to work your way up to at least 30 minutes of exercise most days of the week. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Hypnosis.&lt;/strong&gt; Hypnosis is a deep state of concentration. During a hypnotherapy session, a therapist may hypnotize you by talking in a gentle voice and helping you relax. The therapist will then help you focus on goals, such as controlling your pain and reducing your stress. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	Hypnosis may be helpful for people with cancer who are experiencing anxiety, pain and stress. It may also help prevent anticipatory nausea and vomiting that can occur if chemotherapy has made you sick in the past. When performed by a certified therapist, hypnosis is safe. But tell your therapist if you have a history of mental illness. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Massage therapy.&lt;/strong&gt; During a massage, your practitioner kneads your skin, muscles and tendons in an effort to relieve muscle tension and stress and promote relaxation. Several massage methods exist. Massage can be light and gentle, or it can be deep with more pressure. Studies have found massage can be helpful in relieving pain in people with cancer. It may also help relieve anxiety, fatigue and stress. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	Massage can be safe if you work with a knowledgeable massage therapist. Many cancer centers have massage therapists on staff, or your doctor can refer you to a massage therapist who regularly works with people who have cancer. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	Don&apos;t have a massage if your blood counts are low. Ask the massage therapist to avoid massaging near surgical scars, radiation treatment areas or tumors. If you have cancer in your bones or other bone diseases, such as osteoporosis, ask the massage therapist to use light pressure, rather than deep massage. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Meditation.&lt;/strong&gt; Meditation is a state of deep concentration when you focus your mind on one image, sound or idea, such as a positive thought. When meditating, you might also do deep-breathing or relaxation exercises. Meditation may help people with cancer by relieving anxiety and stress. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	Meditation is generally safe. You can meditate on your own for a few minutes once or twice a day or you can take a class with an instructor. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Music therapy.&lt;/strong&gt; During music therapy sessions, you might listen to music, play instruments, sing songs or write lyrics. A trained music therapist may lead you through activities designed to meet your specific needs, or you may participate in music therapy in a group setting. Music therapy may help relieve pain and control nausea and vomiting. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	Music therapy is safe and doesn&apos;t require any musical talent to participate. Many medical centers have certified music therapists on staff. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Relaxation techniques.&lt;/strong&gt; Relaxation techniques are ways of focusing your attention on calming your mind and relaxing your muscles. Relaxation techniques might include activities such as visualization exercises or progressive muscle relaxation. Relaxation techniques may be helpful in relieving anxiety and fatigue. They may also help people with cancer sleep better. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	Relaxation techniques are safe. Typically a therapist leads you through these exercises and eventually you may be able to do them on your own. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Tai chi.&lt;/strong&gt; Tai chi is a form of exercise that incorporates gentle movements and deep breathing. Tai chi can be led by an instructor, or you can learn tai chi on your own following books or videos. Practicing tai chi may help relieve stress. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	Tai chi is generally safe. The slow movements of tai chi don&apos;t require great physical strength, and the exercises can be easily adapted to your own abilities. Still, talk to your doctor before beginning tai chi. Don&apos;t do any tai chi moves that cause pain. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Yoga.&lt;/strong&gt; Yoga combines stretching exercises with deep breathing. During a yoga session, you position your body in various poses that require bending, twisting and stretching. There are many types of yoga, each with its own variations. Yoga may provide some stress relief for people with cancer. Yoga has also been shown to improve sleep and reduce fatigue. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	Before beginning a yoga class, ask your doctor to recommend an instructor who regularly works with people with health concerns, such as cancer. Avoid yoga poses that cause pain. A good instructor can give you alternative poses that are safe for you. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	You may find some alternative treatments work well together. For instance, deep breathing during a massage may provide further stress relief. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Alternative cancer treatments: 11 options to consider
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Alternative cancer treatments may help you cope with cancer treatment side effects.
	</Abstract>
	<BenefitSummary>
		Alternative cancer treatments can&apos;t cure your cancer, but they may provide some relief from signs and symptoms.
	</BenefitSummary>
	<RelatedLinksBox>
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS01109" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="EAE2DEEA-E7FF-0DBD-1057144038EA6323" Title="Chemo brain" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/chemo-brain/DS01109" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="SlideShow" DocID="MY01725" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="EDC3EC1D-9A14-AB08-31DFB1E3ABE329BB" Title="Slide show: The Mediterranean diet" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/mediterranean-diet/MY01725" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY00323" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="D75DEB67-E7FF-0DBD-1C702656593F0B3F" Title="Brachytherapy" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/brachytherapy/MY00323" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY00105" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="C0133EF8-E7FF-0DBD-169C6332C6D45953" Title="Gene therapy" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/gene-therapy/MY00105" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY00089" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="B5C405F3-E7FF-0DBD-17D02B08AB82FD77" Title="Stem cell transplant" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/stem-cell-transplant/MY00089" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY00088" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="B5C04D78-E7FF-0DBD-1FF66760E140CC1D" Title="Needle biopsy" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/needle-biopsy/MY00088" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01905" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="9DFF414F-E7FF-0DBD-1BCD03C52D197B8E" Title="Cellphones and cancer: What&apos;s the risk?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cell-phones-and-cancer/AN01905" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY00309" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="9AF2EE2C-E7FF-0DBD-1A8FCA94CE9B1305" Title="CT scan" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/ct-scan/MY00309" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY00308" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="9AEF627C-E7FF-0DBD-155D9E86894EFDCD" Title="Ultrasound" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/ultrasound/MY00308" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY00299" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="960B90AD-E7FF-0DBD-126245CC89D3122A" Title="Radiation therapy" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/radiation-therapy/MY00299" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN02061" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="9422D774-DB28-24E4-42201CE2CF20A016" Title="What is compassionate use of experimental drugs?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/compassionate-use/AN02061" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01936" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="90EEBF57-E7FF-0DBD-1FBAF84824FE39B1" Title="Chemotherapy and sex: Is sexual activity OK during treatment?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/chemotherapy-and-sex/AN01936" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN02162" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="87893559-01A2-8CF6-167156AE96DB6FFC" Title="After a flood, are food and medicine safe to use?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/after-a-flood/AN02162" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY01020" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="5E08EF64-FACF-B2BF-FD6B1222673EABD5" Title="Hypnosis" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/hypnosis/MY01020" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN02018" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="55E46151-E885-5896-C20C101CBA801727" Title="Ginger for nausea: Does it work?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/ginger-for-nausea/AN02018" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY01592" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="55797FDC-074D-9B36-20B33F4BB665690D" Title="Proton therapy" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/proton-therapy/MY01592" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN02024" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="144C8942-FC9E-A9FD-0C8694428EDF9B0B" Title="Magic mouthwash: Effective for chemotherapy mouth sores?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/magic-mouthwash/AN02024" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY00238" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="05C8BD86-E7FF-0DBD-150059E403970C30" Title="Positron emission tomography (PET) scan" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/pet-scan/MY00238" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY00233" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="05BE3A9E-E7FF-0DBD-11BF057AFF68529F" Title="SPECT scan" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/spect-scan/MY00233" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY00536" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="001C048C-C6B3-471D-CEDCB0E94EC18648" Title="Chemotherapy" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/chemotherapy/MY00536" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HQ01387" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="F9820A4B-7320-4E1A-98412E8380ADB508" Title="Sleep tips: 7 steps to better sleep" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/sleep/HQ01387" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY01051" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="C54EEF9A-ECA5-FA6C-BEE95E1CE255ECCE" Title="Palliative care: Symptom relief during illness" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/palliative-care/MY01051" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00030" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="C2D1AB8B-565E-4B0B-9C34BEF4FE8ECA63" Title="Chemotherapy nausea and vomiting: Prevention is best defense" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer/CA00030" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY01616" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="C1B3036C-95C2-0633-0DCE16D2A2F0BE5B" Title="Fertility preservation: Understand your options before cancer treatment" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/fertility-preservation/MY01616" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00037" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="A1678D65-8474-4028-85679F53CFE96FD5" Title="Chemotherapy and hair loss: What to expect during treatment" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/hair-loss/CA00037" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY02229" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="97D10F99-96F9-B8ED-A29B93C2B91AE495" Title="Mediterranean diet recipes" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/mediterranean-diet-recipes/MY02229" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="DI00033" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="96C0287B-B8F7-4A9C-824C84551D5E4F6D" Title="Clinical trials: A chance to try new therapies" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/clinical-trials/DI00033" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY02124" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="86149E82-C473-9D9E-F2B37C80473B160B" Title="Mindfulness exercises: How to get started" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/mindfulness-exercises/MY02124" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY02122" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="85845781-9F46-6A0D-BE56D8C4A452879F" Title="Pet therapy: Man&apos;s best friend as healer" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/pet-therapy/MY02122" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00024" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="2FEC5C54-5C57-48E2-A445C46DCF50C26C" Title="Cancer prevention: 7 tips to reduce your risk" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer-prevention/CA00024" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CC00023" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="055661AE-8008-40C8-A8526ED085B5CCC1" Title="Secondhand smoke: Avoid dangers in the air" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/secondhand-smoke/CC00023" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01407" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="D02CD117-E7FF-0DBD-1B172C8988F7AFB1" Title="Chemotherapy side effects: A cause of heart disease?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/chemotherapy-side-effects/AN01407" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01572" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="C68DEC56-E7FF-0DBD-1941747CC18DBFD1" Title="High-dose vitamin C: Can it kill cancer cells?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/alternative-cancer-treatment/AN01572" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN00463" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="C2D4FA32-ED4B-4789-9CB4AED6DF757672" Title="Tumor vs. cyst: What&apos;s the difference?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/tumor/AN00463" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01741" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="B48F4362-E7FF-0DBD-1E1B9FD0D1788369" Title="Curcumin: Can it slow cancer growth?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/curcumin/AN01741" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Video" DocID="MM00638" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="B3684D67-2A5D-9994-E3BD8051DE32E1D8" Title="Video: How cancer spreads" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer/MM00638" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN00654" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="8022D52A-A7C9-4E25-A903FCD7053AB998" Title="Small cell, large cell cancer: What this means" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer/AN00654" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01111" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="6B497AE4-CE04-4860-9C20CAF35CFD35FE" Title="Atypical cells: Are they cancer?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/atypical-cells/AN01111" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="SlideShow" DocID="CA00075" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="491544AC-2A5D-9994-EBE274EA4E6F431B" Title="Slide show: Radiation therapy treatment planning" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/radiation-therapy/CA00075" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Video" DocID="MM00781" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="326F4A39-AAE6-1726-5451D1A058D6D11F" Title="Video: PICC line placement" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/picc-line-placement/MM00781" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00840" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="6A1153F1-E7FF-0DBD-1061638F0F39E31D" Title="Paraneoplastic syndromes of the nervous system" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/paraneoplastic-syndromes/DS00840" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00082" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="D40A35C4-E7FF-0DBD-1DF17BA0656E9D5C" Title="Monoclonal antibody drugs for cancer treatment: How they work" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/monoclonal-antibody/CA00082" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00032" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="CF461BE7-A93A-431C-A5C6BE169724D763" Title="Cancer fatigue: Why it occurs and how to cope" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer-fatigue/CA00032" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HQ01135" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="C596EDA8-DEBC-444F-B01153A818A2C304" Title="Eating during cancer treatment: Tips to make food tastier" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer/HQ01135" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00027" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="B6D4F8E1-4012-435D-899FEE1C9F28DDE1" Title="Cancer treatment decisions: 5 steps to help you decide" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer-treatment/CA00027" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="SA00071" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="B2DAA3D8-7A1F-411A-A37EF20E6550B858" Title="Cancer treatment for women: Possible sexual side effects" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer-treatment/SA00071" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00071" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="AE7710F9-DC59-4055-AE4FFE4DE8279DE3" Title="Cancer survivors: Managing your emotions after cancer treatment" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer-survivor/CA00071" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HO00033" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="9AFAA434-9484-4F2B-A69EFCB322DD1DBE" Title="Cancer treatment myths: Any truth to these common beliefs?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer/HO00033" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00012" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="987C514C-6756-4FF5-8B85CDD6F07F4227" Title="Adjuvant therapy: Treatment to keep cancer from returning" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/adjuvant-therapy/CA00012" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HQ01507" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="8DFF08EE-3CD0-429C-BF5E145C5669616D" Title="Thalidomide: Research advances in cancer and other conditions" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/thalidomide/HQ01507" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HQ00379" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="8DDBC22A-9DEB-49E4-B2DBFDCF6DA2411C" Title="Cancer diagnosis? Advice for dealing with what comes next" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer-diagnosis/HQ00379" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00028" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="8B47B93F-CC17-45BA-800A98CABFB05DD9" Title="Cancer blood tests: Lab tests used in cancer diagnosis" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer-diagnosis/CA00028" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00066" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="7E5CD33E-822C-42B8-B199DEEF17241AA7" Title="Low blood cell counts: Side effect of cancer treatment" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer-treatment/CA00066" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00073" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="5641F40F-D5E8-4D05-8D40E46BE23F8137" Title="Cancer survivors: Late effects of cancer treatment" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer-survivor/CA00073" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00054" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="541725B4-E0E9-4E51-B6F11C30D8E481F0" Title="Mouth sores caused by cancer treatment: How to cope" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/mouth-sores/CA00054" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="SA00070" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="50A88AAB-332D-4808-88247DA44ACE9849" Title="Cancer treatment for men: Possible sexual side effects" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer-treatment/SA00070" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00072" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="4F532516-442A-4E9C-81344F818612FFC0" Title="Cancer survivors: Reconnecting with loved ones after treatment" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer-survivor/CA00072" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00021" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="41AA58E8-49DF-4BD4-A186762D5AA2A009" Title="Cancer pain: Relief is possible" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer-pain/CA00021" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HQ01134" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="3CD37714-A615-4D4A-BA2448B558BD4212" Title="No appetite? How to get nutrition during cancer treatment" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer/HQ01134" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00040" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="2F9D923E-FABA-4607-97D0814475A93176" Title="Diarrhea: Cancer-related causes and how to cope" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/diarrhea/CA00040" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00085" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="27E0CC33-E7FF-0DBD-19A935FF90056FA0" Title="Cancer causes: Popular myths about the causes of cancer" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer-causes/CA00085" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00050" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="20364489-D7FF-47AF-8865618B4A679A74" Title="When cancer returns: How to cope with cancer recurrence" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer/CA00050" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HQ01306" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="1D66B64D-F30C-436E-ABFFEC8971616F07" Title="Cancer diagnosis: 11 tips for coping" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer-diagnosis/HQ01306" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00049" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="1CB388B3-2A33-495C-8A9BBFD0FE28FB03" Title="Cancer survival rate: What it means for your prognosis" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer/CA00049" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00033" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="11596689-42CD-4CD1-9FA79B307C030A01" Title="Cancer surgery: Physically removing cancer" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer-surgery/CA00033" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00053" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="0D7A3614-9863-437D-BFAEFD1407AC82FA" Title="Cancer risk: What the numbers mean" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer/CA00053" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00070" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="0A0DD8B4-F849-4271-A37B87F6CC511AB4" Title="Cancer survivors: Care for your body after treatment" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer-survivor/CA00070" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CA00083" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="0579A73E-E7FF-0DBD-1014915486F5721E" Title="Biopsy: Types of biopsy procedures used to diagnose cancer" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/biopsy/CA00083" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS01076" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="63426615-E7FF-0DBD-1994B85EEA8B6116" Title="Cancer" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cancer/DS01076" />
	</RelatedLinksBox>
</Article>
