<Disease xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Disease.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Disease
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			DS00634
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/lipoma/DS00634
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2012-02-21
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2006-01-11
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1001" Title="Diseases and conditions">
				<Keyword MCVID="1158" Title="Skin hair and nails">
					<Keyword MCVID="2166" Title="Skin tumor">
						<Keyword MCVID="3035" Title="Lipoma" />
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			B5C44775-2A5D-9994-E37A9AA7B86E3635
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				lipoma
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				lipomas
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				lipomata
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				benign skin tumor
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				fatty tumor
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				lumps under skin
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				liposarcoma
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Definition
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
A lipoma is a slow-growing, fatty lump that&apos;s most often situated between your skin and the underlying muscle layer. Often a lipoma is easy to identify because it moves readily with slight finger pressure. It&apos;s doughy to touch and usually not tender. You may have more than one lipoma. Lipomas can occur at any age, but they&apos;re most often detected during middle age. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A lipoma isn&apos;t cancer and is usually harmless. Treatment generally isn&apos;t necessary, but if the lipoma bothers you, is painful or is growing, you may want to have it removed. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
			<PopupMedia>
				<Thumbnail Alt="Image of a lipoma 
" Caption="A lipoma is a fatty tumor located just below the skin. It isn&apos;t cancer and is usually harmless. 
" Height="60" Title="Lipoma" URI="/images/image_popup/thumbs/sn7_lipomathu.jpg" Width="60" />
				<Image Alt="Image of a lipoma 
" Caption="A lipoma is a fatty tumor located just below the skin. It isn&apos;t cancer and is usually harmless. 
" Height="320" Title="Lipoma" URI="/images/image_popup/sn7_lipoma.jpg" Width="320" />
				<HTML>
					A lipoma is a fatty tumor located just below the skin. It isn&apos;t cancer and is usually harmless. 
...
				</HTML>
			</PopupMedia>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Symptoms
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Lipomas are: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Situated&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;just under your skin.&lt;/strong&gt; They commonly occur in the neck, shoulders, back, abdomen, arms and thighs.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Soft and doughy to the touch.&lt;/strong&gt; They also move easily with slight finger pressure.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generally small.&lt;/strong&gt; Lipomas are typically less than 2 inches (5 centimeters) in diameter, but they can grow larger.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sometimes painful.&lt;/strong&gt; Lipomas can be painful if they grow and press on nearby nerves or if they contain many blood vessels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;When to see a doctor&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;A lipoma is rarely a serious medical condition. But if you notice a lump or swelling anywhere on your body, have it checked by your doctor. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
			<PopupMedia>
				<Thumbnail Alt="Image of a lipoma 
" Caption="A lipoma is a fatty tumor located just below the skin. It isn&apos;t cancer and is usually harmless. 
" Height="60" Title="Lipoma" URI="/images/image_popup/thumbs/sn7_lipomathu.jpg" Width="60" />
				<Image Alt="Image of a lipoma 
" Caption="A lipoma is a fatty tumor located just below the skin. It isn&apos;t cancer and is usually harmless. 
" Height="320" Title="Lipoma" URI="/images/image_popup/sn7_lipoma.jpg" Width="320" />
				<HTML>
					A lipoma is a fatty tumor located just below the skin. It isn&apos;t cancer and is usually harmless. 
...
				</HTML>
			</PopupMedia>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Causes
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
The exact cause of lipomas is unknown. Lipomas tend to run in families, so genetic factors likely play a role in their development.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Risk factors
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Several factors may increase your risk of developing a lipoma, including: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Being between 40 and 60 years old.&lt;/strong&gt; Although lipomas can occur at any age, they&apos;re most common in this age group. Lipomas are rare in children.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Having certain other disorders.&lt;/strong&gt; People with other disorders, including adiposis dolorosa, Madelung disease, Cowden syndrome and Gardner&apos;s syndrome, have an increased risk of multiple lipomas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Preparing for your appointment
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
You&apos;re likely to start by seeing your family doctor or a general practitioner. You may then be referred to a doctor who specializes in skin disorders (dermatologist). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&apos;s some information to help you get ready for your appointment and know what to expect from your doctor. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;What you can do&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write down any symptoms you&apos;re experiencing,&lt;/strong&gt; including any that may seem unrelated to the reason for which you scheduled the appointment.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make a list of all medications,&lt;/strong&gt; vitamins or supplements you&apos;re taking.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write down questions to ask&lt;/strong&gt; your doctor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Preparing a list of questions can help you make the most of your time with your doctor. For lipoma, some basic questions to ask your doctor include: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;What caused this growth?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Is it cancer?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Do I need any tests to be sure?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Will this lump always be there?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Can I have it removed?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;What&apos;s involved in having it removed? Are there any risks?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Is it likely to return, or am I likely to get another?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Are there brochures or other resources I can take with me? What websites do you recommend?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Don&apos;t hesitate to ask other questions that occur to you. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;What to expect from your doctor&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;Your doctor is likely to ask you questions, too, including: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;When did you first notice the lump?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Has it grown?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Have you had similar growths in the past?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Is the lump painful?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Have others in your family had similar lumps?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Tests and diagnosis
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
To diagnose a lipoma, your doctor may perform: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A physical exam&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A tissue sample removal (biopsy) for lab examination&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;An ultrasound or other imaging test, such as an MRI or CT scan, if the lipoma is large, has unusual features or appears to be deeper than the fatty tissue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There&apos;s a very small chance that a lump resembling a lipoma may actually be a form of cancer called liposarcoma. Liposarcomas &amp;mdash; cancerous tumors in fatty tissues &amp;mdash; grow rapidly, don&apos;t move under the skin and are usually painful. A biopsy, MRI or CT scan is typically done if your doctor suspects liposarcoma.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Treatments and drugs
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
No treatment is usually necessary for a lipoma. However, if the lipoma is in a location that bothers you, is painful or is growing, your doctor might recommend that it be removed. Lipoma treatments include:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Surgical removal.&lt;/strong&gt; Most lipomas are removed surgically by cutting them out. Recurrences after removal are uncommon.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steroid injections.&lt;/strong&gt; This treatment shrinks the lipoma but usually doesn&apos;t completely eliminate the tumor.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Liposuction.&lt;/strong&gt; This treatment uses a needle and a large syringe to remove the fatty lump.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Lipoma
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Lipoma &amp;mdash; Comprehensive overview covers symptoms, causes, treatment of this usually harmless fatty tumor.
	</Abstract>
	<BenefitSummary />
</Disease>
