<Disease xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Disease.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Disease
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			DS00842
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/dust-mites/DS00842
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2010-11-05
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2006-11-08
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1118" Title="Child">
					<Keyword MCVID="1122" Title="06 to 12 years elementary/preteen" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1118" Title="Child">
					<Keyword MCVID="1123" Title="13 to 18 years teen" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1001" Title="Diseases and conditions">
				<Keyword MCVID="1746" Title="Immune system">
					<Keyword MCVID="1747" Title="Allergy">
						<Keyword MCVID="3571" Title="Environmental allergy">
							<Keyword MCVID="2220" Title="Dust mite allergy" />
						</Keyword>
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			6ABB9250-E7FF-0DBD-150E349EBF322EDC
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				dust allergy
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				dust mite allergy
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Definition
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Dust mite allergy is an allergic reaction to tiny bugs that commonly live in house dust. Signs of dust mite allergy include those common to hay fever, such as sneezing and runny nose. Many people with dust mite allergy also experience signs of asthma, such as wheezing and difficulty breathing. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Dust mites, relatives of the spider, are too small to see without a microscope. Dust mites eat skin cells shed by people, and they thrive in warm, humid environments. In most homes, bedding, upholstered furniture and carpeting provide an ideal environment for dust mites. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Steps to reduce the number of dust mites in your home can often control dust mite allergy. Medications or other treatments may be necessary to relieve symptoms and manage asthma. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Symptoms
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Dust mite allergy symptoms caused by inflammation of nasal passages include: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Sneezing&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Runny nose&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Itchy, red or watery eyes&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Nasal congestion&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Itchy nose, roof of mouth or throat&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Postnasal drip&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Cough&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Facial pressure and pain&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Frequent awakening&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Swollen, blue-colored skin under your eyes&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;In a child, frequent upward rubbing of the nose&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If your dust mite allergy contributes to asthma, you may also experience: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Difficulty breathing&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Chest tightness or pain&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;An audible whistling or wheezing sound when exhaling&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Trouble sleeping caused by shortness of breath, coughing or wheezing&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Bouts of coughing or wheezing that are worsened by a respiratory virus such as a cold or the flu&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A dust mite allergy can range from mild to severe. A mild case of dust mite allergy may cause an occasional runny nose, watery eyes and sneezing. In severe cases, the condition may be ongoing, or chronic, resulting in persistent sneezing, cough, congestion, facial pressure or severe asthma attack. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;When to see a doctor&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Some signs and symptoms of dust mite allergy, such as a runny nose or sneezing, are similar to those of the common cold. Sometimes it&apos;s difficult to know whether you have a cold or an allergy. If symptoms persist for more than one week, you might have an allergy. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If your signs and symptoms are severe &amp;mdash; such as severe nasal congestion, difficulty sleeping or wheezing &amp;mdash; call your doctor. Seek emergency care if wheezing or shortness of breath rapidly worsens or if you are short of breath with minimal activity. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Causes
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Dust mites eat skin cells people shed, and rather than drinking water, they absorb water from humidity in the atmosphere. They thrive in temperatures around 70 F (21 C) and a relative humidity around 70 percent. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
House dust is easily trapped in the fibers of bed linens, furniture cushions and carpeting. These materials also hold moisture well. Consequently, bedrooms are ideal habitats for dust mites. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Dust also contains the feces and decaying bodies of dust mites, and it&apos;s the proteins present in this dust mite &quot;debris&quot; that&apos;s the culprit in dust mite allergy. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;What causes the allergic reaction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Allergies occur when your immune system reacts to a foreign substance such as pollen, pet dander or dust mites. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Your immune system produces proteins known as antibodies. Some of these antibodies protect you from unwanted invaders that could make you sick or cause an infection. When you have allergies, your immune system makes antibodies that identify your particular allergen as something harmful, even though it isn&apos;t. When you inhale the allergen or come into contact with it, your immune system responds and produces an inflammatory response in your nasal passages or lungs. Prolonged or regular exposure to the allergen can cause the ongoing (chronic) inflammation associated with asthma. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
			<PopupMedia>
				<Thumbnail Alt="Image showing dust mite 
" Caption="The common dust mite is shown magnified approximately 2,000 times in this image. A protein present in the feces and decaying bodies of dust mites is the source of dust mite allergy. 
" Height="60" Title="Dust mite" URI="/images/image_popup/thumbs/r7_dustmitethu.jpg" Width="60" />
				<Image Alt="Image showing dust mite 
" Caption="The common dust mite is shown magnified approximately 2,000 times in this image. A protein present in the feces and decaying bodies of dust mites is the source of dust mite allergy. 
" Height="400" Title="Dust mite" URI="/images/image_popup/r7_dustmite.jpg" Width="400" />
				<HTML>
					The common dust mite is shown magnified approximately 2,000 times in this image. A protein present in the feces and decaying bodies of dust mites is the source of dust mite allergy. 
...
				</HTML>
			</PopupMedia>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Risk factors
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
The following factors increase your risk of developing a dust mite allergy: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Family history.&lt;/strong&gt; You&apos;re more likely to develop a sensitivity to dust mites if allergies run in your family.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exposure.&lt;/strong&gt; Being exposed to high levels of dust mites, especially early in life, increases your risk.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Age.&lt;/strong&gt; You&apos;re more likely to develop dust mite allergy during childhood or early adulthood.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Complications
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Sinus infections&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Ongoing (chronic) inflammation of tissues in the nasal passages caused by dust mite allergy can obstruct your sinuses, the hollow cavities connected to your nasal passages. These obstructions may make you more likely to develop infections of the sinuses (sinusitis). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Asthma&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
People with asthma and dust mite allergy often have difficulty managing asthma symptoms. They may be at risk of asthma attacks that require immediate medical treatment or emergency care. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Preparing for your appointment
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
If you&apos;re experiencing runny nose, sneezing, wheezing, shortness of breath or other symptoms that may be related to an allergy, you&apos;ll probably start by seeing your family doctor or general practitioner. Because appointments can be brief, and because there&apos;s often a lot of ground to cover, it&apos;s a good idea to prepare for your appointment. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;What you can do&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write down any symptoms you&apos;re experiencing,&lt;/strong&gt; including any that may seem unrelated to allergy-like symptoms.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write down your family&apos;s history&lt;/strong&gt; of allergy and asthma, including specific types of allergies if you know them.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make a list of all medications,&lt;/strong&gt; as well as any vitamins or supplements that you&apos;re taking.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask if you should stop any medications,&lt;/strong&gt; for example, antihistamines that would affect the results of an allergy skin test.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Preparing a list of questions will help you make the most of your time together. For symptoms that may be related to dust mite allergy, some basic questions to ask your doctor include: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;What is the most likely cause of my signs and symptoms?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Are there any other possible causes?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Will I need any allergy tests?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Should I see an allergy specialist?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;What is the best treatment?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Is there a generic alternative to the medicine you&apos;re prescribing me?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;What changes can I make at home to reduce my exposure to dust mites?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Of the changes you&apos;ve described, which are the most likely to help?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;If the first round of drug treatments and environmental changes we&apos;ve discussed don&apos;t help, what will we try next?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Are there any brochures or other printed material that I can take home with me? What websites do you recommend visiting?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In addition to the questions that you&apos;ve prepared to ask your doctor, don&apos;t hesitate to ask questions during your appointment at any time that you don&apos;t understand something. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;What to expect from your doctor&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Your doctor is likely to ask you a number of questions. Being ready to answer them may reserve time to go over any points you want to spend more time on. Your doctor may ask: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;When did you first begin experiencing symptoms?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Are symptoms worse at certain times of day?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Are the symptoms worse in the bedroom or other rooms of the house?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Do you have pets, and do they go in the bedrooms?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;What kind of self-care techniques have you used, and have they helped?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;What, if anything, appears to worsen your symptoms?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Is there dampness or water damage in the home or workplace?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Do you have an air conditioner in the home?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Issues for people with asthma&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you already have been diagnosed with asthma and are having difficulty managing the disease, your doctor may talk to you about the possibility of allergies. Although allergies are a major contributing factor to asthma, the influence of allergy on asthma severity isn&apos;t always obvious. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The impact of a pollen allergy may be noticeable because the allergy is seasonal. For example, you may have more difficulty managing your asthma for a short time during the summer. Dust mite allergy, on the other hand, is due to something to which you&apos;re constantly exposed to some degree. Therefore, you may not recognize it as a factor complicating your asthma when, in fact, it may be a primary cause. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;What you can do in the meantime&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
If you suspect that you may have a dust mite allergy, take steps to reduce house dust, particularly in your bedroom. Keep your bedroom clean, remove dust-collecting clutter and wash bedding in hot water that is at least 130 F (54.4 C). 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Tests and diagnosis
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Your doctor may suspect dust mite allergy based on symptoms, an examination of your nose and your answers to his or her questions. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
He or she may use a lighted, instrument to look at the condition of the lining of your nose. If you have an allergy to something airborne, the lining of the nasal passage will be swollen and may appear pale or bluish. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Your doctor may suspect a dust mite allergy, based on your comments. For example, if your symptoms are worse when you go to bed or while cleaning &amp;mdash; when dust mite allergens would be temporarily airborne &amp;mdash; you may have dust mite allergy. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you have a pet &amp;mdash; another common source of allergies &amp;mdash; it may be more difficult to determine the cause of the allergy, particularly if your pet sleeps in your bedroom. The source of your allergy may be clearer after you take steps to reduce levels of the possible allergens from your home. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Allergy skin test&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Your doctor may suggest an allergy skin test to determine what you&apos;re allergic to. You may be referred to an allergy specialist (allergist) for this test. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In this test, tiny drops of purified allergen extracts &amp;mdash; including an extract for dust mites &amp;mdash; are pricked onto your skin&apos;s surface. This is usually carried out on the forearm, but it may be done on the upper back. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The drops are left on your skin for 15 minutes before your doctor or nurse observes your skin for signs of allergic reactions. If you&apos;re allergic to dust mites, you&apos;ll develop a red, itchy bump where the dust mite extract was pricked onto your skin. The most common side effects of these skin tests are itching and redness. These side effects usually go away within 30 minutes. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Blood test&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In some cases, a skin test can&apos;t be performed because of the presence of a skin condition or because of interactions with certain medications. As an alternative, your doctor may order a blood test that that screens your blood for specific allergy-causing antibodies to various common allergens, including dust mites. This test may also indicate how sensitive you are to an allergen. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Treatments and drugs
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
The first treatment for controlling dust mite allergy is avoiding dust mites as much as possible. When you minimize your exposure to dust mites, you should expect to have allergic reactions that are less often or less severe. However, it&apos;s impossible to completely eliminate dust mites from your environment. You may also need medications to control symptoms. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Allergy medications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Your doctor may direct you to take one of the following medications to improve nasal allergy symptoms: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Antihistamines&lt;/strong&gt; reduce the production of an immune system chemical that is active in an allergic reaction. These drugs relieve itching, sneezing and runny nose. Prescription antihistamine tablets include fexofenadine (Allegra) and desloratadine (Clarinex). Azelastine (Astelin, Astepro) and olopatadine (Patanase) are prescription antihistamines taken as a nasal spray. Over-the-counter antihistamine tablets (Claritin, Zyrtec, others), as well as antihistamine syrups for children, also are available.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Corticosteroids&lt;/strong&gt; delivered as a nasal spray can reduce inflammation and control symptoms of hay fever. These drugs include fluticasone (Flonase), mometasone furoate (Nasonex), triamcinolone (Nasacort) and ciclesonide (Omnaris). Nasal corticosteroids provide a low dose of the drug and have a much lower risk of side effects compared with oral corticosteroids.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Decongestants&lt;/strong&gt; can help shrink swollen tissues in your nasal passages and make it easier to breathe through your nose. Some over-the-counter allergy tablets combine an antihistamine with a decongestant. Oral decongestants can increase blood pressure and shouldn&apos;t be taken if you have severe high blood pressure or cardiovascular disease. In men with an enlarged prostate, the drug can worsen the condition. Talk to your doctor about whether you can safely take a decongestant.
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
	Over-the-counter decongestants taken as a nasal spray may briefly reduce allergy symptoms. If you use a decongestant spray for more than three days in a row, it can contribute to congestion.
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cromolyn sodium&lt;/strong&gt; prevents the release of an immune system chemical and may reduce symptoms. You need to use this over-the-counter nasal spray several times a day, and it&apos;s most effective when used before signs and symptoms develop. Cromolyn sodium doesn&apos;t have serious side effects.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Leukotriene modifiers&lt;/strong&gt; block the action of certain immune system chemicals. Your doctor may prescribe this prescription tablet, montelukast (Singulair). Possible side effects include headache. Less common side effects include abdominal pain, cough, dental pain and dizziness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Other therapies&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Immunotherapy,&lt;/strong&gt; a series of allergy shots, can &quot;train&quot; your immune system not to be sensitive to an allergen. One to two weekly shots expose you to very small doses of the allergen, in this case, the dust mite protein that causes an allergic reaction. The dose is gradually increased, usually during a three- to six-month period. Maintenance shots are needed every two to four weeks for three to five years. Immunotherapy is usually used when other simple treatments don&apos;t work well.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nasal lavage&lt;/strong&gt; is the use of a saltwater (saline) rinse for your nasal passages. Your doctor may suggest a saline rinse to help lessen congestion, sneezing and postnasal drip. You can purchase over-the-counter saline sprays or nasal lavage kits with devices, such as squeeze bottles, to administer a rinse. You can make your own solution with 1/8 teaspoon (5 milliliters) of table salt in 8 ounces (237 milliliters) of distilled or purified water. Mix the ingredients together and store the solution at room temperature, and remix another batch after a week. Lavage your nose daily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Lifestyle and home remedies
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Avoiding exposure to dust mites is the best strategy for controlling dust mite allergy. While you can&apos;t completely eliminate dust mites from your home, you can significantly reduce their number. Use these suggestions: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use allergen-proof bed covers.&lt;/strong&gt; Cover your mattress and pillows in dust-proof or allergen-blocking covers. These covers, made of tightly woven fabric, prevent dust mites from colonizing or escaping from the mattress or pillows. Encase box springs in allergen-proof covers.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wash bedding weekly.&lt;/strong&gt; Wash all sheets, blankets, pillowcases and bedcovers in hot water that is at least 130 F (54.4 C) to kill dust mites and remove allergens. If bedding can&apos;t be washed hot, put the items in the drier for at least 20 minutes at a temperature above 130 F (54.4 C) to kill the mites. Then wash and dry the bedding to remove allergens. Freezing nonwashable items for 24 hours also can kill dust mites, but this won&apos;t remove the allergens.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep humidity low.&lt;/strong&gt; Maintain a relative humidity between 30 and 50 percent in your home. A dehumidifier or air conditioner can help keep humidity low, and a hygrometer (available at hardware stores) can measure humidity levels.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Choose bedding wisely.&lt;/strong&gt; Avoid bedcovers that trap dust easily and are difficult to clean frequently.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buy washable stuffed toys.&lt;/strong&gt; Wash them often in hot water and dry thoroughly. Also, keep stuffed toys off beds.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remove dust.&lt;/strong&gt; Use a damp or oiled mop or rag rather than dry materials to clean up dust. This prevents dust from becoming airborne and resettling.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vacuum regularly.&lt;/strong&gt; Vacuuming carpeting and upholstered furniture removes surface dust &amp;mdash; but vacuuming isn&apos;t effective at removing most dust mites and dust mite allergens. Use a vacuum cleaner with a double-layered microfilter bag or a high-efficiency particulate air (HEPA) filter to help decrease house-dust emissions from the cleaner. If your allergies are severe, leave the area being vacuumed while someone else does the dirty work. Stay out of the vacuumed room for 20 minutes after vacuuming.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cut clutter.&lt;/strong&gt; If it collects dust, it also collects dust mites. Remove knickknacks, tabletop ornaments, books, magazines and newspapers from your bedroom.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remove carpeting and other dust mite habitats.&lt;/strong&gt; Carpeting provides a comfortable habitat for dust mites. This is especially true if carpeting is over concrete, which holds moisture easily and provides a humid environment for mites. If possible, replace wall-to-wall bedroom carpeting with tile, wood, linoleum or vinyl flooring. Consider replacing other dust-collecting furnishings in bedrooms, such upholstered furniture, nonwashable curtains and horizontal blinds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Air purifiers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Air purifiers collect airborne dust in your home and can help with controlling dust if you also maintain vigorous cleaning practices. But purifiers won&apos;t remove dust mites because the mites are too heavy to remain airborne long enough to be filtered through an air purifier. Some dust mites may be airborne right after cleaning, but they quickly settle again onto surfaces. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Dust mite allergy
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Dust mite allergy &amp;mdash; Comprehensive overview covers symptoms and treatment of allergy to dust mites.
	</Abstract>
	<BenefitSummary />
	<RelatedLinksBox>
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01241" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="B0F40A94-2A5D-9994-E46A807D9C5DB928" Title="Nasal spray addiction: Is it real?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/nasal-spray-addiction/AN01241" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY01158" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="32EF9C94-F392-CBE1-BE5F35260FE0602B" Title="Allergy shots" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/allergy-shots/MY01158" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HQ00076" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="DF9C6CB0-CEE5-40D6-AFF0B81BF0BC3673" Title="Humidifiers: Air moisture eases skin, breathing symptoms" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/humidifiers/HQ00076" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="AA00037" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="BBD5759D-4334-4DD4-9EC29CAA95A45281" Title="Allergy medications: Know your options" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/allergy-medications/AA00037" />
	</RelatedLinksBox>
</Disease>
