<Disease xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Disease.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Disease
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			DS00097
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/hepatitis-c/DS00097
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2013-08-13
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2000-10-02
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1001" Title="Diseases and conditions">
				<Keyword MCVID="1137" Title="Digestive system">
					<Keyword MCVID="1841" Title="Liver">
						<Keyword MCVID="1858" Title="Hepatitis">
							<Keyword MCVID="2427" Title="Hepatitis C" />
						</Keyword>
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			7235BE2E-BEC1-40BE-971C851E75A0FDC5
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				hepatitis C
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				hepatitis
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				hepatitis C symptoms
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				liver
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				liver disease
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				jaundice
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				hepatitus
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				hepatitus C
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				hep C
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				hepititis C
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				HCV
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Definition
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Hepatitis C is an infection caused by a virus that attacks the liver and leads to inflammation. Most people infected with the hepatitis C virus (HCV) have no symptoms. In fact, most people don&apos;t know they have the hepatitis C infection until liver damage shows up, decades later, during routine medical tests. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hepatitis C is one of several hepatitis viruses and is generally considered to be among the most serious of these viruses. Hepatitis C is passed through contact with contaminated blood &amp;mdash; most commonly through needles shared during illegal drug use. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
			<PopupMedia>
				<Thumbnail Alt="Illustration showing the liver, located above the stomach
" Caption="The liver is your largest internal organ. About the size of a football, it&apos;s located mainly in the upper right portion of your abdomen, beneath the diaphragm and above your stomach.
" Height="60" Title="The liver" URI="/images/image_popup/thumbs/r7_liverthu.jpg" Width="60" />
				<Image Alt="Illustration showing the liver, located above the stomach
" Caption="The liver is your largest internal organ. About the size of a football, it&apos;s located mainly in the upper right portion of your abdomen, beneath the diaphragm and above your stomach.
" Height="682" Title="The liver" URI="/images/image_popup/r7_liver.jpg" Width="400" />
				<HTML>
					The liver is your largest internal organ. About the size of a football, it&apos;s located mainly in the upper right portion of your abdomen, beneath the diaphragm and above your stomach.
...
				</HTML>
			</PopupMedia>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Symptoms
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Hepatitis C infection usually produces no signs or symptoms during its earliest stages. When signs and symptoms do occur, they may include: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Fatigue&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Fever&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Nausea or poor appetite&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Muscle and joint pains&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Yellowing of the skin and whites of the eyes (jaundice)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;When to see a doctor&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Make an appointment with your doctor if you have any signs and symptoms that worry you. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Causes
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Hepatitis C infection is caused by the hepatitis C virus (HCV). HCV is spread when you come in contact with blood contaminated with the virus. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
			<PopupMedia>
				<Thumbnail Alt="Illustration showing the liver, located above the stomach
" Caption="The liver is your largest internal organ. About the size of a football, it&apos;s located mainly in the upper right portion of your abdomen, beneath the diaphragm and above your stomach.
" Height="60" Title="The liver" URI="/images/image_popup/thumbs/r7_liverthu.jpg" Width="60" />
				<Image Alt="Illustration showing the liver, located above the stomach
" Caption="The liver is your largest internal organ. About the size of a football, it&apos;s located mainly in the upper right portion of your abdomen, beneath the diaphragm and above your stomach.
" Height="682" Title="The liver" URI="/images/image_popup/r7_liver.jpg" Width="400" />
				<HTML>
					The liver is your largest internal organ. About the size of a football, it&apos;s located mainly in the upper right portion of your abdomen, beneath the diaphragm and above your stomach.
...
				</HTML>
			</PopupMedia>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Risk factors
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Your risk of hepatitis C infection is increased if you: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Are a health care worker who has been exposed to infected blood, such as may happen if an infected needle pierces your skin&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Have ever injected illicit drugs&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Have HIV&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Received a piercing or tattoo in an unclean environment using unsterile equipment&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Received a blood transfusion or organ transplant before 1992&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Received clotting factor concentrates before 1987&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Received hemodialysis treatments for a long period of time&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Were born to a woman with a hepatitis C infection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Complications
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Hepatitis C infection that continues over many years can cause significant complications, such as: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scarring of the liver tissue (cirrhosis).&lt;/strong&gt; After 20 to 30 years of hepatitis C infection, cirrhosis may occur. Scarring in your liver makes it difficult for your liver to function.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Liver cancer.&lt;/strong&gt; A small number of people with hepatitis C infection may develop liver cancer.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Liver failure.&lt;/strong&gt; A liver that is severely damaged by hepatitis C may be unable to function adequately.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
			<PopupMedia>
				<Thumbnail Alt="Illustrations of a normal liver and liver cirrhosis 
" Caption="A normal liver (left) shows no signs of scarring. In cirrhosis (right), scar tissue replaces normal liver tissue. 
" Height="60" Title="Normal liver vs. liver cirrhosis" URI="/images/image_popup/thumbs/r7_normcirrhosisthu.jpg" Width="60" />
				<Image Alt="Illustrations of a normal liver and liver cirrhosis 
" Caption="A normal liver (left) shows no signs of scarring. In cirrhosis (right), scar tissue replaces normal liver tissue. 
" Height="195" Title="Normal liver vs. liver cirrhosis" URI="/images/image_popup/r7_normcirrhosis.jpg" Width="400" />
				<HTML>
					A normal liver (left) shows no signs of scarring. In cirrhosis (right), scar tissue replaces normal liver tissue. 
...
				</HTML>
			</PopupMedia>
			<PopupMedia>
				<Thumbnail Alt="Illustration of liver cancer 
" Caption="Liver cancer begins in the cells of the liver. The most common form of liver cancer begins in cells called hepatocytes and is called hepatocellular carcinoma. 
" Height="60" Title="Liver cancer" URI="/images/image_popup/thumbs/mcdc7_liver_cancerthu.jpg" Width="60" />
				<Image Alt="Illustration of liver cancer 
" Caption="Liver cancer begins in the cells of the liver. The most common form of liver cancer begins in cells called hepatocytes and is called hepatocellular carcinoma. 
" Height="320" Title="Liver cancer" URI="/images/image_popup/mcdc7_liver_cancer.jpg" Width="400" />
				<HTML>
					Liver cancer begins in the cells of the liver. The most common form of liver cancer begins in cells called hepatocytes and is called hepatocellular carcinoma. 
...
				</HTML>
			</PopupMedia>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Preparing for your appointment
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Who to see&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
If you think you may have a risk of hepatitis C, see your family doctor or a general practitioner. Once you&apos;ve been diagnosed with hepatitis C infection, your doctor may recommend you see a specialist. Specialists who see people with hepatitis C infection include: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Doctors who specialize in infectious diseases&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Doctors who specialize in liver diseases (hepatologists)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;How to prepare&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Because appointments can be brief and because there&apos;s often a lot of ground to cover, it&apos;s a good idea to be well prepared. To prepare, try to: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be aware of any pre-appointment restrictions.&lt;/strong&gt; At the time you make the appointment, be sure to ask if there&apos;s anything you need to do in advance, such as restrict your diet.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write down any symptoms you&apos;re experiencing,&lt;/strong&gt; including any that may seem unrelated to the reason for which you scheduled the appointment.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write down key personal information,&lt;/strong&gt; including any major stresses or recent life changes.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make a list of all medications,&lt;/strong&gt; vitamins or supplements you&apos;re taking.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consider taking a family member or friend along.&lt;/strong&gt; Sometimes it can be difficult to remember all the information provided during an appointment. Someone who accompanies you may remember something that you missed or forgot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Questions to ask&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Time with your doctor may be limited, so preparing a list of questions will help you make the most of your time together. List your questions from most important to least important, in case time runs out. For hepatitis C infection, some basic questions to ask your doctor include: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;How much hepatitis C virus do I have in my body?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Should I be tested for other causes of liver disease, such as hepatitis B?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Has the hepatitis C virus damaged my liver?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Do I need treatment for hepatitis C infection?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;What are my treatment options?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;What are the benefits of each treatment option?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;What are the potential risks of each treatment option?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Is there one treatment you think is best for me?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;I have other medical conditions. How will these affect my hepatitis C treatment?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Should my family be tested for hepatitis C?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Is it possible for me to spread hepatitis C to others?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;How can I protect the people around me from hepatitis C?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Should I see a specialist? What will that cost, and will my insurance cover it?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Are there brochures or other material that I can take with me? What websites do you recommend?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;What will determine whether I should plan for a follow-up visit?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Is it safe for me to drink alcohol?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;What medications should I avoid?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In addition to the questions that you&apos;ve prepared to ask your doctor, don&apos;t hesitate to ask questions that occur to you during your appointment. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;What to expect from your doctor&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Your doctor is likely to ask you a number of questions. Being ready to answer them may allow more time later to cover points you want to address. Your doctor may ask: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;When did you first begin experiencing symptoms?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Have your symptoms been continuous or occasional?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;How severe are your symptoms?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;What, if anything, seems to improve your symptoms?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;What, if anything, appears to worsen your symptoms?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Have you ever had a blood transfusion or an organ transplant? If so, when?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Have you ever used self-injected drugs not prescribed by your doctor?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Have you ever been diagnosed with hepatitis or jaundice?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Does anyone in your family have hepatitis C?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Is there a history of liver disease in your family?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Tests and diagnosis
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Screening for hepatitis C&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Testing for hepatitis C infection in people who have a high risk of coming in contact with the virus may help doctors begin treatment or recommend lifestyle changes that may slow liver damage. This is recommended because hepatitis C infection often begins damaging the liver before it causes signs and symptoms. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
People who may want to talk to their doctors about screening for hepatitis C infection include: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Anyone who has ever injected illicit drugs&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Anyone with unexplained, unusual liver function test results&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Babies born to mothers with hepatitis C&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Health care and emergency workers who have been exposed to blood or accidental needle sticks&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;People with hemophilia who were treated with clotting factors before 1987&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;People who have ever undergone long-term hemodialysis treatments&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;People who received blood transfusions or organ transplants before 1992&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Sexual partners of anyone diagnosed with hepatitis C infection&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;People with HIV infection&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Anyone born from 1945 to 1965&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Blood tests to diagnose hepatitis C&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Blood tests may help to: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Determine whether you have the hepatitis C virus&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Measure the quantity of the hepatitis C virus in your blood (viral load)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Evaluate the genetic makeup of the virus (genotyping), which helps determine your treatment options&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Testing samples of liver tissue to determine severity of liver damage&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Your doctor may also recommend a procedure to remove a small sample of liver tissue for laboratory testing. A liver biopsy can help determine the severity of the disease and guide treatment decisions. During a liver biopsy, your doctor inserts a thin needle through your skin and into your liver to remove the tissue sample. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
			<PopupMedia>
				<Thumbnail Alt="Illustration of a liver biopsy 
" Caption="A liver biopsy is a procedure to remove a small sample of liver tissue for laboratory testing. A liver biopsy is commonly performed by inserting a thin needle through your skin and into your liver.
" Height="60" Title="Liver biopsy" URI="/images/image_popup/thumbs/mcdc7_liver_biopsythu.jpg" Width="60" />
				<Image Alt="Illustration of a liver biopsy 
" Caption="A liver biopsy is a procedure to remove a small sample of liver tissue for laboratory testing. A liver biopsy is commonly performed by inserting a thin needle through your skin and into your liver.
" Height="373" Title="Liver biopsy" URI="/images/image_popup/mcdc7_liver_biopsy.jpg" Width="400" />
				<HTML>
					A liver biopsy is a procedure to remove a small sample of liver tissue for laboratory testing. A liver biopsy is commonly performed by inserting a thin needle through your skin and into your liver....
				</HTML>
			</PopupMedia>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Treatments and drugs
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Treatment isn&apos;t always necessary&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
A diagnosis of hepatitis C infection doesn&apos;t necessarily mean you need treatment. If your doctor recommends no treatment, you&apos;ll undergo follow-up blood tests to monitor for liver problems. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Antiviral medications&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Hepatitis C infection is treated with antiviral medications intended to clear the virus from your body. Your doctor may recommend a combination of medications taken over several weeks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Throughout treatment your doctor will monitor your response to medications.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Antiviral medications can cause depression and flu-like signs and symptoms, such as fatigue, fever and headache. Some side effects can be serious enough that treatment must be delayed or stopped in certain cases. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Liver transplant&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
If your liver has been severely damaged, a liver transplant may be an option. During a liver transplant, the surgeon removes your damaged liver and replaces it with a healthy liver. Most transplanted livers come from deceased donors, though a small number come from living donors who donate a portion of their livers. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For people with hepatitis C infection, a liver transplant is not a cure. Treatment with antiviral medications usually continues after a liver transplant, since hepatitis C infection is likely to recur in the new liver. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Vaccinations to protect against other forms of viral hepatitis&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Your doctor will likely recommend that you receive vaccines against the hepatitis A and B viruses. These are separate viruses that also can cause liver damage and complicate treatment of hepatitis C. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
			<PopupMedia>
				<Thumbnail Alt="Illustration showing a living-donor liver transplant
" Caption="A small percentage of liver donations come from a living donor, such as a friend or family member. During a living-donor liver transplant, one portion of the donor&apos;s liver is removed and transplanted in your body. The livers begin regenerating new cells almost immediately.
" Height="60" Title="Living liver transplant" URI="/images/image_popup/thumbs/d7_livinglivertransplantthu.jpg" Width="60" />
				<Image Alt="Illustration showing a living-donor liver transplant
" Caption="A small percentage of liver donations come from a living donor, such as a friend or family member. During a living-donor liver transplant, one portion of the donor&apos;s liver is removed and transplanted in your body. The livers begin regenerating new cells almost immediately.
" Height="230" Title="Living liver transplant" URI="/images/image_popup/d7_living_liver_transplant.jpg" Width="400" />
				<HTML>
					A small percentage of liver donations come from a living donor, such as a friend or family member. During a living-donor liver transplant, one portion of the donor&apos;s liver is removed and transplanted ...
				</HTML>
			</PopupMedia>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Lifestyle and home remedies
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
If you receive a diagnosis of hepatitis C, your doctor will likely recommend certain lifestyle changes. These measures will help keep you healthy longer and protect the health of others as well: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stop drinking alcohol.&lt;/strong&gt; Alcohol speeds the progression of liver disease.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid medications that may cause liver damage.&lt;/strong&gt; Review your medications with your doctor, including the over-the-counter medications you take. Your doctor may recommend avoiding certain medications.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Help prevent others from coming in contact with your blood.&lt;/strong&gt; Cover any wounds you have and don&apos;t share razors or toothbrushes. Don&apos;t donate blood, body organs or semen, and advise health care workers that you have the virus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Alternative medicine
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
No complementary or alternative medicine treatments have proved helpful in preventing or treating hepatitis C infection. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One herb that continues to attract attention for its touted liver-health properties is milk thistle. Proponents of milk thistle recommend the herb to treat jaundice and other liver disorders. People take milk thistle as a capsule, extract or infusion. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A clinical trial by the National Center for Complementary and Alternative Medicine found milk thistle was no better than a placebo at lowering liver enzyme levels in people with hepatitis C. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&apos;re interested in trying milk thistle, discuss the benefits and risks with your doctor. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Prevention
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Protect yourself from hepatitis C infection by taking the following precautions: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stop using illicit drugs.&lt;/strong&gt; If you use illicit drugs, seek help.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be cautious about body piercing and tattooing.&lt;/strong&gt; If you choose to undergo piercing or tattooing, look for a reputable shop. Ask questions beforehand about how the equipment is cleaned. Make sure the employees use sterile needles. If employees won&apos;t answer your questions, look for another shop.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practice safer sex if you choose to have sex.&lt;/strong&gt; Don&apos;t engage in unprotected sex with multiple partners or with any partner whose health status is uncertain. Sexual transmission between monogamous couples may occur, but the risk is low.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Hepatitis C
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Hepatitis C &amp;mdash; Comprehensive overview covers symptoms, treatment of infection with the hepatitis C virus.
	</Abstract>
	<BenefitSummary />
	<RelatedLinksBox>
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY00949" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="BF094DD4-EB8C-F3AC-12068A1EC5AE889B" Title="Liver biopsy" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/liver-biopsy/MY00949" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY00094" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="B729B58C-E7FF-0DBD-12F16E2756745D18" Title="Bilirubin test" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/bilirubin/MY00094" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY00093" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="B727321E-E7FF-0DBD-1CADFEB8D4A46579" Title="Liver function tests" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/liver-function-tests/MY00093" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN00758" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="F7370FBF-65CF-4A67-89AD8C9FAAAEF7B9" Title="Hepatitis C: What happens in end-stage liver disease?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/hepatitis-c/AN00758" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN00701" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="4B441C27-43B2-4498-81579FE52DC2A001" Title="Hepatitis C: How common is sexual transmission?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/hepatitis-c/AN00701" />
	</RelatedLinksBox>
</Disease>
