<FirstAid xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="FirstAid.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			FirstAid
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			FA00016
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/first-aid-sprain/FA00016
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2012-03-20
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			1999-12-21
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1004" Title="Content Packages">
				<Keyword MCVID="3155" Title="First aid">
					<Keyword MCVID="3164" Title="Traumatic injuries" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="3327" Title="First aid">
				<Keyword MCVID="3670" Title="Bones joints and muscles">
					<Keyword MCVID="3902" Title="Sprain" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			3B8D4BC4-D392-4BE6-B365F04D565A7261
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				sprain
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				sprains
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				strain
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				muscle
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				joint
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				ligament
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Your ligaments are tough, elastic-like bands that connect bone to bone and hold your joints in place. A sprain is an injury to a ligament caused by tearing of the fibers of the ligament. The ligament can have a partial tear, or it can be completely torn apart. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of all sprains, ankle and knee sprains occur most often. Sprained ligaments swell rapidly and are painful. Generally, the greater the pain and swelling, the more severe the injury is. For most minor sprains, you probably can treat the injury yourself.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Follow the instructions for R.I.C.E.&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rest&lt;/strong&gt; the injured limb. Your doctor may recommend not putting any weight on the injured area for 48 hours. But don&apos;t avoid all activity. Even with an ankle sprain, you can usually still exercise other muscles to minimize deconditioning. For example, you can use an exercise bicycle with arm exercise handles, working both your arms and the uninjured leg while resting the injured ankle on another part of the bike. That way you still get three-limb exercise to keep up your cardiovascular conditioning.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ice&lt;/strong&gt; the area. Use a cold pack, a slush bath or a compression sleeve filled with cold water to help limit swelling after an injury. Try to ice the area as soon as possible after the injury and continue to ice it for 15 to 20 minutes, four to eight times a day, for the first 48 hours or until swelling improves. If you use ice, be careful not to use it too long, as this could cause tissue damage.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compress&lt;/strong&gt; the area with an elastic wrap or bandage. Compressive wraps or sleeves made from elastic or neoprene are best.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elevate&lt;/strong&gt; the injured limb above your heart whenever possible to help prevent or limit swelling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After two days, gently begin using the injured area. You should feel a gradual, progressive improvement. Over-the-counter pain relievers, such as ibuprofen (Advil, Motrin, others) and acetaminophen (Tylenol, others), may be helpful to manage pain during the healing process. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
See your doctor if your sprain isn&apos;t improving after two or three days. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Get emergency medical assistance if:&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;You&apos;re unable to bear weight on the injured leg, the joint feels unstable or numb, or you can&apos;t use the joint. This may mean the ligament was completely torn. On the way to the doctor, apply a cold pack.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;You develop redness or red streaks that spread out from the injured area. This means you may have an infection.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;You have re-injured an area that has been injured a number of times in the past.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;You have a severe sprain. Inadequate or delayed treatment may contribute to long-term joint instability or chronic pain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Sprain
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		How to administer first aid for a sprain.
	</Abstract>
	<MobileBody>
		&lt;p&gt;
Sprains are the result of stretching or tearing a ligament or ligaments &amp;mdash; the tissue that connects your bones. Ankle and knee sprains occur most often. Sprained ligaments swell rapidly and are painful. Generally, the greater the pain and the more unstable the joint feels, the more severe the injury is. For most minor sprains, you can probably treat the injury yourself.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Follow the instructions for R.I.C.E. &lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rest&lt;/strong&gt; the injured limb. But don&apos;t avoid all activity.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ice&lt;/strong&gt; the area. Try to apply ice as soon as possible after the injury and continue to apply it for 10 to 15 minutes four times a day for 48 hours.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compress&lt;/strong&gt; the area with an elastic wrap or bandage.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elevate&lt;/strong&gt; the injured limb whenever possible to help prevent or limit swelling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After two days, gently begin using the injured area. You should feel a gradual, progressive improvement. Pain relievers, such as ibuprofen (Advil, Motrin, others) and acetaminophen (Tylenol, others), may be helpful. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
See your doctor if your sprain doesn&apos;t improve after two or three days. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Get emergency medical assistance if:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;You&apos;re unable to bear weight on the injured leg, the joint feels unstable or you can&apos;t use the joint. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;You have a fever higher than 100 F (37.8 C), and the area is red and hot. You may have an infection. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;You have a severe sprain. Inadequate or delayed treatment may cause long-term joint instability or chronic pain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
	</MobileBody>
	<BenefitSummary />
</FirstAid>
