<FirstAid xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="FirstAid.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			FirstAid
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			FA00050
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/first-aid-heart-attack/FA00050
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2012-02-03
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			1999-08-25
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1004" Title="Content Packages">
				<Keyword MCVID="3155" Title="First aid">
					<Keyword MCVID="3161" Title="Major medical emergencies" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="3327" Title="First aid">
				<Keyword MCVID="3903" Title="Cardiovascular system">
					<Keyword MCVID="3906" Title="Heart attack" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			CFC8A2A8-B211-482E-BFEED59D7FAAD6C9
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				heart attack
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				myocardial infarction
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Someone having a heart attack may experience any or all of the following: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Uncomfortable pressure, fullness or squeezing pain in the center of the chest&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Prolonged pain in the upper abdomen&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Discomfort or pain spreading beyond the chest to the shoulders, neck, jaw, teeth, or one or both arms&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Shortness of breath&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Lightheadedness, dizziness, fainting&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Sweating&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Nausea&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A heart attack generally causes chest pain for more than 15 minutes, but it can also have no symptoms at all. Many people who experience a heart attack have warning signs hours, days or weeks in advance. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;If you or someone else may be having a heart attack&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Call 911 or your local emergency medical assistance number.&lt;/strong&gt; Don&apos;t tough out the symptoms of a heart attack for more than five minutes. If you don&apos;t have access to emergency medical services, have a neighbor or a friend drive you to the nearest hospital. Drive yourself only as a last resort, if there are absolutely no other options, and realize that it places you and others at risk when you drive under these circumstances.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chew and swallow an aspirin,&lt;/strong&gt; unless you&apos;re allergic to aspirin or have been told by your doctor never to take aspirin. But seek emergency help first, such as calling 911.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take nitroglycerin,&lt;/strong&gt; if prescribed. If you think you&apos;re having a heart attack and your doctor has previously prescribed nitroglycerin for you, take it as directed. Do not take anyone else&apos;s nitroglycerin, because that could put you in more danger.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Begin CPR if the person is unconscious.&lt;/strong&gt; If you&apos;re with a person who might be having a heart attack and he or she is unconscious, tell the 911 dispatcher or another emergency medical specialist. You may be advised to begin cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR). If you haven&apos;t received CPR training, doctors recommend skipping mouth-to-mouth rescue breathing and performing only chest compressions (about 100 per minute). The dispatcher can instruct you in the proper procedures until help arrives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Heart attack
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		How to recognize, get help for and provide first aid for a heart attack.
	</Abstract>
	<MobileBody>
		&lt;p&gt;
Someone having a heart attack may have any, none or all of these signs and symptoms: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Uncomfortable pressure, fullness or squeezing pain in the center of the chest&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Prolonged pain in the upper abdomen&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Discomfort or pain spreading beyond the chest to the shoulders, neck, jaw, teeth, or one or both arms&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Shortness of breath&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Lightheadedness, dizziness, fainting&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Sweating&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Nausea&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A heart attack generally causes chest pain for longer than 15 minutes, but it can also have no symptoms at all. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;If you or someone else may be having a heart attack &lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Call 911 or your local emergency number.&lt;/strong&gt; Don&apos;t tough out the symptoms of a heart attack for more than five minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chew and swallow an aspirin,&lt;/strong&gt; unless you&apos;re allergic to aspirin or have been told by your doctor never to take aspirin. But seek emergency help first, such as by calling 911.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take nitroglycerin,&lt;/strong&gt; if prescribed.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Begin CPR.&lt;/strong&gt; If you&apos;re with a person who might be having a heart attack and he or she is unconscious, tell the 911 dispatcher or another emergency medical specialist. You may be advised to begin cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR). If you haven&apos;t received CPR training, doctors recommend skipping mouth-to-mouth rescue breathing and performing only chest compressions (about 100 per minute). The dispatcher can instruct you in the proper procedures until help arrives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
	</MobileBody>
	<BenefitSummary />
</FirstAid>
