<FirstAid xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="FirstAid.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			FirstAid
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			FA00010
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/first-aid-spinal-injury/FA00010
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2012-03-16
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			1999-12-21
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1004" Title="Content Packages">
				<Keyword MCVID="3155" Title="First aid">
					<Keyword MCVID="3164" Title="Traumatic injuries" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="3327" Title="First aid">
				<Keyword MCVID="3670" Title="Bones joints and muscles">
					<Keyword MCVID="3901" Title="Spinal injury" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			C36EB300-7A74-436B-9E40EEDB44D5B9DD
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				spinal injury
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				spinal cord injury
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				spine
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				spinal cord
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				neck
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				back
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
If you suspect a back or neck (spinal) injury, do not move the affected person. Permanent paralysis and other serious complications can result. Assume a person has a spinal injury if: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;There&apos;s evidence of a head injury with an ongoing change in the person&apos;s level of consciousness&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The person complains of severe pain in his or her neck or back&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The person won&apos;t move his or her neck&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;An injury has exerted substantial force on the back or head&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The person complains of weakness, numbness or paralysis or lacks control of his or her limbs, bladder or bowels&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The neck or back is twisted or positioned oddly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you suspect someone has a spinal injury: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Call 911 or emergency medical help.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Keep the person still. Place heavy towels on both sides of the neck or hold the head and neck to prevent movement.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Provide as much first aid as possible without moving the person&apos;s head or neck. If the person shows no signs of circulation (breathing, coughing or movement), begin CPR, but do not tilt the head back to open the airway. Use your fingers to gently grasp the jaw and lift it forward. If the person has no pulse, begin chest compressions.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;If the person is wearing a helmet, don&apos;t remove it.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;If you absolutely must roll the person because he or she is vomiting, choking on blood or in danger of further injury, you need at least one other person. With one of you at the head and another along the side of the injured person, work together to keep the person&apos;s head, neck and back aligned while rolling the person onto one side.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Spinal injury
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		How to administer first aid for a spinal injury.
	</Abstract>
	<MobileBody>
		&lt;p&gt;
If you suspect a back or neck (spinal) injury, do not move the affected person. Permanent paralysis and other serious complications can result. Assume a person has a spinal injury if: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;There&apos;s evidence of a head injury with an ongoing change in the person&apos;s level of consciousness &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The person complains of severe neck or back pain &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The person won&apos;t move his or her neck&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;An injury has exerted substantial force on the back or head &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The person complains of weakness, numbness or paralysis or lacks control of limbs, bladder or bowels &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The neck or back is twisted or positioned oddly &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you suspect someone has a spinal injury:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Call 911 or emergency medical help &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Keep the person still and in much the same position in which he or she was found. Place heavy towels on both sides of the neck or hold the head and neck to prevent movement.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Provide as much first aid as possible without moving the head or neck. If the person shows no signs of circulation (breathing, coughing or movement), begin CPR, but don&apos;t tilt the head back to open the airway. Use your fingers to gently grasp the jaw and lift it forward. If the person has no pulse, begin chest compressions.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;If you absolutely must roll the person because he or she is vomiting, choking on blood or in danger of further injury, use at least two people. Work together to keep the person&apos;s head, neck and back aligned while rolling the person onto one side.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
	</MobileBody>
	<BenefitSummary />
</FirstAid>
