<SlideShow xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="SlideShow.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			SlideShow
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			FL00103
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/baby-baths/FL00103
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2013-02-27
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2005-07-15
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1118" Title="Child">
					<Keyword MCVID="1119" Title="00 birth to 01 month newborn" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1463" Title="Life stage">
				<Keyword MCVID="1533" Title="Children">
					<Keyword MCVID="3747" Title="Infants and toddlers">
						<Keyword MCVID="3749" Title="Newborn health" />
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			B9FF1FA6-4F9B-4247-9BEAFA6F9D7955C2
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				infant
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				newborn
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				baby
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				bathing
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				baby baths
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				bath
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				baby bath
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Title>
		Slide show: Baby baths
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Baby baths can be tricky. Find out how to safely clean your baby.
	</Abstract>
	<Slides>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				&lt;p&gt;
Baby baths can be fun for parents and babies alike. Sometimes bathing a slippery, squirming baby can be difficult, however &amp;mdash; especially if your baby&apos;s not too keen on the idea. Before you plunge into baby baths, make sure you&apos;re comfortable with the basics. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				It&apos;s bath time!
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photo of baby wrapped in a towel
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				227
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/fl22_babyintowel.jpg
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				&lt;p&gt;
You might consider giving your newborn a sponge bath, at least until the umbilical cord stump falls off. To give your baby a sponge bath, lay your baby on his or her back on a soft towel or pad. Wet a washcloth, wring out excess water and wipe your baby&apos;s face. There&apos;s usually no need to use soap. Use a clean cotton ball or cloth to wipe each eyelid, from the inside to the outside corner. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Consider sponge baths
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photo of parent washing baby&apos;s forehead
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				227
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/fl22_babyforehead.jpg
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				&lt;p&gt;
When you&apos;re ready to clean the rest of your baby&apos;s body, stick with plain water. If your baby is smelly or dirty, use a mild moisturizing soap. Pay special attention to creases under the arms, behind the ears, around the neck and in the diaper area. Also wash between your baby&apos;s fingers and toes. To keep your baby warm, expose only the parts you&apos;re washing. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Getting into the creases
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photo of parent washing behind baby&apos;s ear
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				227
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/fl22_washingear.jpg
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				&lt;p&gt;
Your baby&apos;s hair might not need to be washed during every bath. If it seems dirty, gently massage a drop of mild baby shampoo into your baby&apos;s scalp. Rinse the shampoo with a damp washcloth, cupping one hand across your baby&apos;s forehead to keep suds out of his or her eyes. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Washing baby&apos;s hair
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photo of parent washing baby&apos;s hair
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				227
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/fl22_shampoo.jpg
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				&lt;p&gt;
When you&apos;re ready to give your baby a tub bath &amp;mdash; whether you do so right from the start or you try sponge baths first &amp;mdash; you&apos;ll have plenty of choices. You can use a free-standing plastic tub specifically designed for newborns, a plain plastic basin or a small inflatable tub that fits inside the bathtub. Lined with a towel or rubber mat, the kitchen or bathroom sink might be another option. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Remember, though, safety is the most important consideration &amp;mdash; not necessarily the type of tub. Gather your supplies and a cup of rinsing water ahead of time so that you can keep one hand on the baby at all times. Never leave your baby alone in the water. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Breaking out the tub
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photo of baby tub and supplies
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				227
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/fl22_supplies.jpg
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				&lt;p&gt;
To prevent scalding, set the thermostat on your water heater to below 120 F (49 C). Always check the temperature with your hand before bathing your baby. Be sure the room is comfortably warm, too. A wet baby may be easily chilled. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The ideal amount of water for a baby bath is debatable. A common recommendation is 2 to 3 inches (5 to 8 centimeters) of warm water. To keep your baby warm, pour warm water over his or her body throughout the bath. Some research suggests that using slightly more water &amp;mdash; enough to cover a baby&apos;s shoulders &amp;mdash; can be calming and help reduce heat loss. With any amount of water, be sure to hold your baby securely. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Checking the water temperature
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photo of hand testing water temperature
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				227
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/fl22_handtestingwater.jpg
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				&lt;p&gt;
A secure hold will help your baby feel comfortable &amp;mdash; and stay safe &amp;mdash; in the tub. Use one of your hands to support your baby&apos;s head and the other to hold and guide your baby&apos;s body into the water, feet first. Support your baby&apos;s head and torso with your arm and hand. Wrap your arm under your baby&apos;s back, grasping your baby firmly under the armpit. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Use a secure hold
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photo of parent washing under baby&apos;s arm
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				252
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/fl22_washingarm.jpg
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				&lt;p&gt;
When you clean your baby&apos;s back and buttocks, lean him or her forward on your arm. Continue to grasp your baby under the armpit. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Washing baby&apos;s back
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photo of parent washing baby&apos;s back
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				227
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/fl22_washingback.jpg
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				&lt;p&gt;
Pay special attention to creases under the arms, behind the ears, around the neck and in the diaper area. Also wash between your baby&apos;s fingers and toes. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Remember the creases
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photo of parent washing baby&apos;s toes
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				230
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/fl22_washingtoes.jpg
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				&lt;p&gt;
When your baby moves beyond a washcloth for rinsing hair, you might want to try a football hold under the faucet. Support your baby&apos;s back with your arm, keeping a firm hold on your baby&apos;s head while you rinse. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				Rinsing baby&apos;s hair
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photo of parent rinsing baby&apos;s hair
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				227
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/fl22_rinsinghair.jpg
			</URI>
		</Slide>
		<Slide>
			<Caption>
				&lt;p&gt;
If your baby cries in the tub, stay calm. Clean what you can and then wrap your baby snugly in a towel. You might want to wait a few days and then try again. In the meantime, use sponge baths to clean the parts that really need attention &amp;mdash; your baby&apos;s face, neck and diaper area. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</Caption>
			<Title>
				When baby cries
			</Title>
			<ImageAltText>
				Photo of baby crying in the tub
			</ImageAltText>
			<Height>
				189
			</Height>
			<Width>
				320
			</Width>
			<URI>
				/images/slideshow/fl22_cryingintub.jpg
			</URI>
		</Slide>
	</Slides>
</SlideShow>
