<Article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Article.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Article
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			HI00027
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/high-blood-pressure/HI00027
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2012-07-19
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2003-02-28
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1001" Title="Diseases and conditions">
				<Keyword MCVID="1145" Title="Cardiovascular system">
					<Keyword MCVID="1147" Title="High blood pressure" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			A4B126D1-26BB-4A5C-8F616E89C237E24A
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				high blood pressure
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				hypertension
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				prevention
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				blood pressure
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				primary hypertension
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				essential hypertension
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				salt
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				sodium
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				DASH
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				DASH diet
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
If you&apos;ve been diagnosed with high blood pressure (a systolic pressure &amp;mdash; the top number &amp;mdash; of 140 or above or a diastolic pressure &amp;mdash; the bottom number &amp;mdash; of 90 or above), you might be worried about taking medication to bring your numbers down. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Lifestyle plays an important role in treating your high blood pressure. If you successfully control your blood pressure with a healthy lifestyle, you may avoid, delay or reduce the need for medication. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here are 10 lifestyle changes you can make to lower your blood pressure and keep it down. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				1. Lose extra pounds and watch your waistline
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Blood pressure often increases as weight increases. Losing just 10 pounds (4.5 kilograms) can help reduce your blood pressure. In general, the more weight you lose, the lower your blood pressure. Losing weight also makes any blood pressure medications you&apos;re taking more effective. You and your doctor can determine your target weight and the best way to achieve it. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Besides shedding pounds, you should also keep an eye on your waistline. Carrying too much weight around your waist can put you at greater risk of high blood pressure. In general: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Men are at risk if their waist measurement is greater than 40 inches (102 centimeters, or cm).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Women are at risk if their waist measurement is greater than 35 inches (89 cm).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Asian men are at risk if their waist measurement is greater than 36 inches (91 cm).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Asian women are at risk if their waist measurement is greater than 32 inches (81 cm).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				2. Exercise regularly
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Regular physical activity &amp;mdash; at least 30 to 60 minutes most days of the week &amp;mdash; can lower your blood pressure by 4 to 9 millimeters of mercury (mm Hg). And it doesn&apos;t take long to see a difference. If you haven&apos;t been active, increasing your exercise level can lower your blood pressure within just a few weeks. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you have prehypertension &amp;mdash; systolic pressure between 120 and 139 or diastolic pressure between 80 and 89 &amp;mdash; exercise can help you avoid developing full-blown hypertension. If you already have hypertension, regular physical activity can bring your blood pressure down to safer levels. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Talk to your doctor about developing an exercise program. Your doctor can help determine whether you need any exercise restrictions. Even moderate activity for 10 minutes at a time, such as walking and light strength training, can help. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But avoid being a &quot;weekend warrior.&quot; Trying to squeeze all your exercise in on the weekends to make up for weekday inactivity isn&apos;t a good strategy. Those sudden bursts of activity could actually be risky. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				3. Eat a healthy diet
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Eating a diet that is rich in whole grains, fruits, vegetables and low-fat dairy products and skimps on saturated fat and cholesterol can lower your blood pressure by up to 14 mm Hg. This eating plan is known as the Dietary Approaches to Stop Hypertension (DASH) diet. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It isn&apos;t easy to change your eating habits, but with these tips, you can adopt a healthy diet: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep a food diary.&lt;/strong&gt; Writing down what you eat, even for just a week, can shed surprising light on your true eating habits. Monitor what you eat, how much, when and why.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consider boosting potassium.&lt;/strong&gt; Potassium can lessen the effects of sodium on blood pressure. The best source of potassium is food, such as fruits and vegetables, rather than supplements. Talk to your doctor about the potassium level that&apos;s best for you.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be a smart shopper.&lt;/strong&gt; Make a shopping list before heading to the supermarket to avoid picking up junk food. Read food labels when you shop and stick to your healthy-eating plan when you&apos;re dining out, too.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cut yourself some slack.&lt;/strong&gt; Although the DASH diet is a lifelong eating guide, it doesn&apos;t mean you have to cut out all of the foods you love. It&apos;s OK to treat yourself occasionally to foods you wouldn&apos;t find on a DASH diet menu, such as a candy bar or mashed potatoes with gravy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				4. Reduce sodium in your diet
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Even a small reduction in the sodium in your diet can reduce blood pressure by 2 to 8 mm Hg. The recommendations for reducing sodium are: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Limit sodium to 2,300 milligrams (mg) a day or less.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A lower sodium level &amp;mdash; 1,500 mg a day or less &amp;mdash; is appropriate for people 51 years of age or older, and individuals of any age who are African-American or who have high blood pressure, diabetes or chronic kidney disease.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To decrease sodium in your diet, consider these tips: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Track how much salt is in your diet.&lt;/strong&gt; Keep a food diary to estimate how much sodium is in what you eat and drink each day.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read food labels.&lt;/strong&gt; If possible, choose low-sodium alternatives of the foods and beverages you normally buy.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eat fewer processed foods.&lt;/strong&gt; Potato chips, frozen dinners, bacon and processed lunch meats are high in sodium.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don&apos;t add salt.&lt;/strong&gt; Just 1 level teaspoon of salt has 2,300 mg of sodium. Use herbs or spices, rather than salt, to add more flavor to your foods.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ease into it.&lt;/strong&gt; If you don&apos;t feel like you can drastically reduce the sodium in your diet suddenly, cut back gradually. Your palate will adjust over time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				5. Limit the amount of alcohol you drink
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Alcohol can be both good and bad for your health. In small amounts, it can potentially lower your blood pressure by 2 to 4 mm Hg. But that protective effect is lost if you drink too much alcohol &amp;mdash; generally more than one drink a day for women and men older than age 65, or more than two a day for men age 65 and younger. Also, if you don&apos;t normally drink alcohol, you shouldn&apos;t start drinking as a way to lower your blood pressure. There&apos;s more potential harm than benefit to drinking alcohol. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you drink more than moderate amounts of it, alcohol can actually raise blood pressure by several points. It can also reduce the effectiveness of high blood pressure medications. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Track your drinking patterns.&lt;/strong&gt; Along with your food diary, keep an alcohol diary to track your true drinking patterns. One drink equals 12 ounces (355 milliliters, or mL) of beer, 5 ounces of wine (148 mL) or 1.5 ounces of 80-proof liquor (45 mL). If you&apos;re drinking more than the suggested amounts, cut back.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consider tapering off.&lt;/strong&gt; If you&apos;re a heavy drinker, suddenly eliminating all alcohol can actually trigger severe high blood pressure for several days. So when you stop drinking, do it with the supervision of your doctor or taper off slowly, over one to two weeks.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don&apos;t binge.&lt;/strong&gt; Binge drinking &amp;mdash; having four or more drinks in a row &amp;mdash; can cause large and sudden increases in blood pressure, in addition to other health problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				6. Avoid tobacco products and secondhand smoke
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
On top of all the other dangers of smoking, the nicotine in tobacco products can raise your blood pressure by 10 mm Hg or more for up to an hour after you smoke. Smoking throughout the day means your blood pressure may remain constantly high. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You should also avoid secondhand smoke. Inhaling smoke from others also puts you at risk of health problems, including high blood pressure and heart disease. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				7. Cut back on caffeine
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
The role caffeine plays in blood pressure is still debatable. Drinking caffeinated beverages can temporarily cause a spike in your blood pressure, but it&apos;s unclear whether the effect is temporary or long lasting. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To see if caffeine raises your blood pressure, check your pressure within 30 minutes of drinking a cup of coffee or another caffeinated beverage you regularly drink. If your blood pressure increases by five to 10 points, you may be sensitive to the blood pressure raising effects of caffeine. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				8. Reduce your stress
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Stress or anxiety can temporarily increase blood pressure. Take some time to think about what causes you to feel stressed, such as work, family, finances or illness. Once you know what&apos;s causing your stress, consider how you can eliminate or reduce stress. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you can&apos;t eliminate all of your stressors, you can at least cope with them in a healthier way. Take breaks for deep-breathing exercises. Get a massage or take up yoga or meditation. If self-help doesn&apos;t work, seek out a professional for counseling. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				9. Monitor your blood pressure at home and make regular doctor&apos;s appointments
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
If you have high blood pressure, you may need to monitor your blood pressure at home. Learning to self-monitor your blood pressure with an upper arm monitor can help motivate you. Talk to your doctor about home monitoring before getting started. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Regular visits to your doctor are also likely to become a part of your normal routine. These visits will help keep tabs on your blood pressure. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have a primary care doctor.&lt;/strong&gt; People who don&apos;t have a primary care doctor find it harder to control their blood pressure. If you can, visit the same health care facility or professional for all of your health care needs.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visit your doctor regularly.&lt;/strong&gt; If your blood pressure isn&apos;t well controlled, or if you have other medical problems, you might need to visit your doctor every month to review your treatment and make adjustments. If your blood pressure is under control, you might need to visit your doctor only every six to 12 months, depending on other conditions you might have.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				10. Get support from family and friends
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Supportive family and friends can help improve your health. They may encourage you to take care of yourself, drive you to the doctor&apos;s office or embark on an exercise program with you to keep your blood pressure low. Talk to your family and friends about the dangers of high blood pressure. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you find you need support beyond your family and friends, consider joining a support group. This may put you in touch with people who can give you an emotional or morale boost and who can offer practical tips to cope with your condition. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		10 ways to control high blood pressure without medication
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		You can lower your blood pressure without medication. Try these 10 lifestyle changes.
	</Abstract>
	<BenefitSummary>
		By making these 10 lifestyle changes, you can lower your blood pressure and reduce your risk of heart disease.
	</BenefitSummary>
	<RelatedLinksBox>
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00788" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="D37E3592-E7FF-0DBD-137E686E8DA4F36A" Title="Prehypertension" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/prehypertension/DS00788" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS01114" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="42823E43-E7FF-0DBD-118600FF8103E891" Title="Secondary hypertension" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/secondary-hypertension/DS01114" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY00143" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="DF97963B-E7FF-0DBD-11424887D8C55C79" Title="Microalbumin test" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/microalbumin/MY00143" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Video" DocID="MM00636" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="DC99F092-6EAA-4CDC-88A1F80D923861AE" Title="Video: Heart and circulatory system &amp;mdash; How they work" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/circulatory-system/MM00636" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Table" DocID="HI00048" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="BF9EC580-06B1-40EC-B4FD27D51F856FBB" Title="DASH diet: Guide to recommended servings" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/dash-diet/HI00048" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY01180" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="8FA1E447-9FAA-8A0D-C4932F5017C91661" Title="Blood pressure test" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/blood-pressure-test/MY01180" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN02162" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="87893559-01A2-8CF6-167156AE96DB6FFC" Title="After a flood, are food and medicine safe to use?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/after-a-flood/AN02162" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN02060" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="74319CCA-A39A-D5B6-0F4AF737780B30B1" Title="Healthy chocolate: Dream or reality?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/healthy-chocolate/AN02060" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="SlideShow" DocID="MY01702" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="7334523E-D11B-512B-FD7E52C9D2319327" Title="Slide show: 5 main dish vegetable recipes" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/vegetable-recipes/MY01702" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN00317" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="4F93C99A-DDC4-4CC7-882F71F66A0DD4E4" Title="Water softeners: How much sodium do they add?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/sodium/AN00317" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN02066" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="1F592789-EAB0-EB7E-CC07A47C78BCE0AF" Title="Polypill: Does it treat heart disease?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/polypill/AN02066" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN02154" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="0DB75F75-EC64-9E6B-D5831E36A41606E6" Title="Do infrared saunas have any health benefits?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/infrared-sauna/AN02154" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN02163" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="02C4202F-9CA4-40A5-82E7C63FD990CC88" Title="Diuretics and gout: What&apos;s the connection?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/diuretics-and-gout/AN02163" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HI00047" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="FE95D456-5ADE-4E86-8A957584F1FC49A4" Title="DASH diet: Healthy eating to lower your blood pressure" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/dash-diet/HI00047" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HQ01387" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="F9820A4B-7320-4E1A-98412E8380ADB508" Title="Sleep tips: 7 steps to better sleep" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/sleep/HQ01387" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HI00046" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="AD93AF8B-6E0E-4BD5-87D575C0F1F79DC8" Title="Sample menus for the DASH eating plan" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/dash-diet/HI00046" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY01874" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="8CFB62FE-E33C-7457-779E0B9DE4B51EC3" Title="Herbal supplements may not mix with heart medicines" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/herbal-supplements/MY01874" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HI00020" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="70354217-6336-473A-9009C1A4226569A2" Title="DASH diet: Tips for shopping and cooking" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/dash-diet/HI00020" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="WO00098" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="42D602A0-DB4A-49D5-8C5241231FF58FEC" Title="Birth control pill FAQ: Benefits, risks and choices" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/birth-control-pill/WO00098" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY02523" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="3BA1D951-96EA-1423-7EA1E4AB155CF29C" Title="How much sleep do you really need?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/sleep-custom-site/MY02523" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY02522" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="3B9EBCAC-0B17-E216-16450C0FA665AFFE" Title="Sleep deprivation: Know the risks" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/sleep-custom-site/MY02522" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HI00021" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="2CEE92F2-74A2-468C-8DC51ED91D249468" Title="DASH diet: Tips for dining out" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/dash-diet/HI00021" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01409" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="EA3ADB22-E7FF-0DBD-15BFFADA0E76F71B" Title="Beta blockers: Do they cause weight gain?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/beta-blockers/AN01409" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01805" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="E642627E-E7FF-0DBD-127101A5D18D71A5" Title="Blood pressure medications: Can they raise my triglycerides?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/blood-pressure-medications/AN01805" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Video" DocID="MM00785" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="E4AF5952-E281-9FDB-A49D030ABA3ADA63" Title="Video: How to measure blood pressure using an automatic monitor" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/how-to-measure-blood-pressure/MM00785" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Video" DocID="MM00784" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="E4AC6F86-E982-CDFA-7000379CDB6D02C5" Title="Video: How to measure blood pressure using a manual monitor" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/how-to-measure-blood-pressure/MM00784" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Video" DocID="MM00783" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="E4A91387-DA91-1FD3-6FA25DF674886A49" Title="Video: What is blood pressure?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/what-is-blood-pressure/MM00783" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN00391" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="E3340A96-EE3F-459C-ADCF5542FB8031D2" Title="Blood pressure: Does it have a daily pattern?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/blood-pressure/AN00391" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01224" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="E2C8DF16-2A5D-9994-EE1CD5A39AE77278" Title="Beta blockers: How do they affect exercise?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/beta-blockers/AN01224" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01523" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="CED59AD9-E7FF-0DBD-189A34D534017ACC" Title="Resperate: Can it help reduce blood pressure?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/resperate/AN01523" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN00357" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="C22A32DF-E88A-4A19-ACF061ACA161F96A" Title="Blood pressure: Can it be higher in one arm?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/blood-pressure/AN00357" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01871" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="B957C014-E7FF-0DBD-15B79F240E5F9EC4" Title="Calcium supplements: Do they interfere with blood pressure drugs?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/calcium-supplements/AN01871" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01086" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="9CD2F26A-4D26-4A8F-A56633C979B71EC0" Title="Anxiety: A cause of high blood pressure?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/anxiety/AN01086" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Table" DocID="HI00043" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="9A5682D3-EA4F-4B75-9AD9B2FA46746B6C" Title="Blood pressure chart: What your reading means" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/blood-pressure/HI00043" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01113" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="99858DDA-4298-4DC2-83B13F42E9CCB7D5" Title="Isolated systolic hypertension: A health concern?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/hypertension/AN01113" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN00637" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="7BEA90EA-45BD-4052-B3CA28CDED7CCD0E" Title="Weightlifting: Bad for your blood pressure?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/weightlifting/AN00637" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN00626" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="6C95FDF4-3201-4DA8-865B9C4E129DE8D6" Title="Hypertensive crisis: What are the symptoms?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/hypertensive-crisis/AN00626" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN00792" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="6488C9E0-4259-425B-975EDA39F3378760" Title="Caffeine: How does it affect blood pressure?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/blood-pressure/AN00792" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01786" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="59D4C6A4-E7FF-0DBD-17D7F3407E1DB63D" Title="Blood pressure: Is it affected by cold weather?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/blood-pressure/AN01786" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01463" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="52A7F294-E7FF-0DBD-188D6FB40F00387D" Title="Menopause and high blood pressure: What&apos;s the connection?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/menopause-and-high-blood-pressure/AN01463" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN00352" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="4E053CF6-9A01-4F1E-88EF4EFB7844213D" Title="Diuretics: A cause of low potassium?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/blood-pressure/AN00352" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01344" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="48D55B0C-2A5D-9994-E2070E8DBEE5BAC0" Title="Sleep deprivation: A cause of high blood pressure?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/sleep-deprivation/AN01344" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01605" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="482CD8BB-E7FF-0DBD-187477B75BF4D2C3" Title="L-arginine: Does it lower blood pressure?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/l-arginine/AN01605" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01927" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="4749301C-E7FF-0DBD-1C750E4DE8E2856B" Title="High blood pressure and cold remedies: Which are safe?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/high-blood-pressure/AN01927" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN00925" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="46A20906-5691-4B4F-BF4B99510FDE9DC7" Title="Blood pressure readings: Why higher at home?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/blood-pressure/AN00925" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01926" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="43031CCA-E7FF-0DBD-1E620A538B1217A7" Title="Blood pressure cuff: Does size matter?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/blood-pressure-cuff/AN01926" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01496" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="30A83E05-E7FF-0DBD-1A10CF3D8AFDC8D3" Title="Blood pressure medication: Still necessary if I lose weight?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/blood-pressure-medication/AN01496" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN00968" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="20C60920-4142-4A35-99621C105DDACB6C" Title="Pulse pressure: An indicator of heart health?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/pulse-pressure/AN00968" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN02075" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="1F34C088-C0FA-8D35-216AD8B2A7293F30" Title="Can whole-grain foods lower blood pressure?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/whole-grain-foods/AN02075" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN02014" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="18414840-0787-01C2-EDA51F2BFC00878C" Title="White-coat hypertension: When blood pressure rises at the doctor&apos;s office" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/white-coat-hypertension/AN02014" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01839" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="10D4EF3C-E7FF-0DBD-1FB6834D9B1CB13E" Title="Wrist blood pressure monitors: Are they accurate?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/wrist-blood-pressure-monitors/AN01839" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN00567" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="10CD97B6-69B4-4765-AAC24EA41546EB0D" Title="Free blood pressure machines: Are they accurate?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/blood-pressure/AN00567" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN00318" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="0D0864BA-4B41-4A21-9E4E20422944FF2E" Title="Alcohol: Does it affect blood pressure?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/blood-pressure/AN00318" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00017" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="FE3FE459-7D1E-405F-95E9339CD2E974B8" Title="Thoracic aortic aneurysm" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/aortic-aneurysm/DS00017" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS01194" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="A79FE318-0945-8020-C0195BB597B9EC18" Title="Abdominal aortic aneurysm" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/abdominal-aortic-aneurysm/DS01194" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS01196" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="876FB7D4-F866-4917-1B55AD849EC7E466" Title="Membranous nephropathy" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/membranous-nephropathy/DS01196" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00314" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="6DA0F41C-F55D-430B-A0B267A41E791B57" Title="Obesity" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/obesity/DS00314" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00582" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="27C87FA4-C560-4F97-B5B680BD5D09F585" Title="Brain aneurysm" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/brain-aneurysm/DS00582" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS01129" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="18047987-0FF0-30B7-30826F629576DC5D" Title="Enlarged heart" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/enlarged-heart/DS01129" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00396" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="0487CA33-EE6D-4E87-93CB56C658CA5FB5" Title="Hyperparathyroidism" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/hyperparathyroidism/DS00396" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS01209" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="00181BF2-A05D-C7CA-9AC2C61BC10CCFFA" Title="Spontaneous coronary artery dissection" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/spontaneous-coronary-artery-dissection/DS01209" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HI00057" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="E8A46831-F3A5-4B73-9D4D158B904FA5F7" Title="Vasodilators" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/high-blood-pressure-medication/HI00057" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HI00030" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="E7492D61-D3D0-4624-9EBDA3A85E08B557" Title="Diuretics" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/diuretics/HI00030" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HI00016" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="D84ACA1C-2A12-4A75-900208367D504614" Title="Get the most out of home blood pressure monitoring" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/high-blood-pressure/HI00016" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HI00061" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="CB1CED06-E45C-41E1-B860780817DE5EEE" Title="Calcium channel blockers" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/calcium-channel-blockers/HI00061" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HI00060" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="C0E0B21D-8943-4415-99B10B646B4EE634" Title="Angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/ace-inhibitors/HI00060" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HI00028" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="82388918-C8B7-4322-87CE9FCD15FD393F" Title="Choosing blood pressure medications" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/high-blood-pressure-medication/HI00028" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HI00062" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="6DF4F95D-E7FF-0DBD-1306F218EC685233" Title="High blood pressure dangers: Hypertension&apos;s effects on your body" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/high-blood-pressure/HI00062" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HI00024" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="45DF4744-A2FE-4E0A-AE71D442093FDC2F" Title="Exercise: A drug-free approach to lowering high blood pressure" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/high-blood-pressure/HI00024" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HI00054" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="3AF3E6F5-A43E-43DE-9E5E1707B87E8A58" Title="Angiotensin II receptor blockers" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/angiotensin-II-receptor-blockers/HI00054" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HI00059" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="1D095753-6FDD-4079-AF6DA015DA2BD68F" Title="Beta blockers" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/beta-blockers/HI00059" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HI00056" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="1B1D19FB-94E0-4340-BAA6FA799836AF08" Title="Central-acting agents" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/high-blood-pressure-medication/HI00056" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HI00055" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="13E80AE3-3DFF-4989-B3A6E6049BE5988D" Title="Alpha blockers" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/alpha-blockers/HI00055" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HI00091" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="13476B30-E7FF-0DBD-18FF920E1D5480C7" Title="High blood pressure and sex: Overcome the challenges" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/high-blood-pressure-and-sex/HI00091" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HI00092" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="13281AD6-E7FF-0DBD-106BB14106AB2F8C" Title="Stress and high blood pressure: What&apos;s the connection?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/stress-and-high-blood-pressure/HI00092" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00100" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="D2F240ED-803D-4E1A-A692B907BFCFDD6D" Title="High blood pressure (hypertension)" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/high-blood-pressure/DS00100" />
	</RelatedLinksBox>
</Article>
