<Answer xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Answer.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Answer
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			HO00172
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/male-yeast-infection/HO00172
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2012-09-18
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			1997-10-03
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1129" Title="Gender">
				<Keyword MCVID="1130" Title="Men" />
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1001" Title="Diseases and conditions">
				<Keyword MCVID="1148" Title="Infectious disease">
					<Keyword MCVID="1584" Title="Fungal">
						<Keyword MCVID="2639" Title="Yeast infection" />
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			0BC07341-0549-49A0-B7FD77092D080A54
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				male yeast infection
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				yeast infection
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				penile yeast infection
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				penis yeast infection
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Though yeast infections are more common in women, anyone can get one. It&apos;s possible for a man to get a genital yeast infection if he has unprotected sexual intercourse with a partner who has a genital yeast infection. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
However, if your girlfriend has a yeast infection, it doesn&apos;t mean you&apos;ll get one too. Sexual transmission of yeast infections is uncommon. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Prolonged antibiotic use increases your risk of a yeast infection, and men and women with diabetes or impaired immune systems, such as those with HIV, are more susceptible to yeast infections. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Signs and symptoms of a male yeast infection include a reddish rash, itching or burning at the tip of the penis. Most male yeast infections are easily treated with over-the-counter antifungal treatments, such as Monistat (yes, men can use it too). Apply the medication directly to the affected skin twice daily for a week. If the rash doesn&apos;t go away, or if it recurs frequently, consult your doctor. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you and your partner both have symptoms of genital yeast infection, it&apos;s important that you both be treated. Otherwise, you may keep reinfecting each other. Also, it&apos;s generally recommended that you refrain from sexual contact until all signs and symptoms of the infection are gone. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Male yeast infection: Can I get it from my girlfriend?
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Learn about causes and signs and symptoms of male yeast infection.
	</Abstract>
	<Question>
		Can I get a genital yeast infection from my girlfriend? I thought only women got yeast infections.
	</Question>
	<QuestionFirstName>
		John
	</QuestionFirstName>
	<QuestionState>
		No state given
	</QuestionState>
	<BenefitSummary />
</Answer>
