<Article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Article.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Article
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			HQ00076
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/humidifiers/HQ00076
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2010-09-25
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2000-04-15
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1001" Title="Diseases and conditions">
				<Keyword MCVID="1148" Title="Infectious disease">
					<Keyword MCVID="3186" Title="Cold and flu">
						<Keyword MCVID="1593" Title="Common cold" />
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			DF9C6CB0-CEE5-40D6-AFF0B81BF0BC3673
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				humidifiers
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				dry skin
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				dry air
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				asthma
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				portable humidifier
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				house humidifier
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				room humidifier
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				skin
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				home humidifier
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				air humidifier
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				general humidifier
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				console humidifier
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				central humidifier
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				clean humidifier
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Dry sinuses, bloody noses and cracked lips &amp;mdash; humidifiers can help soothe these familiar problems caused by dry indoor air. Humidifiers can also help ease symptoms of a cold or another respiratory condition. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But be cautious &amp;mdash; while humidifiers can be useful, they can actually make you sick if they aren&apos;t maintained properly or if humidity levels stay too high. If you do use humidifiers, play it safe: Monitor humidity levels and keep your humidifier clean &amp;mdash; dirty humidifiers can breed mold or bacteria that can make you sick. If you have allergies or asthma, talk to your doctor before using a humidifier. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				What are humidifiers?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Humidifiers are devices that emit water vapor or steam to increase moisture levels in the air (humidity). There are several types: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Central humidifiers&lt;/strong&gt; are built into home heating and air conditioning systems and are designed to humidify the whole house.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ultrasonic humidifiers&lt;/strong&gt; produce a cool mist with ultrasonic vibration. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impeller humidifiers&lt;/strong&gt; produce a cool mist with a rotating disk.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evaporators&lt;/strong&gt; use a fan to blow air through a wet wick, filter or belt.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steam vaporizers&lt;/strong&gt; use electricity to create steam that cools before leaving the machine. Avoid this type of humidifier if you have children; hot water inside this type of humidifier may cause burns if it&apos;s spilled.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Ideal humidity levels
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Humidity is the amount of water vapor in the air. The amount of humidity varies depending on the season, weather and where you live. Generally, humidity levels are higher in the summer and lower during winter months. Ideally, humidity in your home should be between 30 and 50 percent. Humidity that&apos;s too low or too high can cause problems. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Low humidity&lt;/strong&gt; can cause dry skin, irritate your nasal passages and throat, and make your eyes itchy.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High humidity&lt;/strong&gt; can make your home feel stuffy and can cause condensation on walls, floors and other surfaces that triggers the growth of harmful bacteria, dust mites and molds. These allergens can cause respiratory problems and trigger allergy and asthma flare-ups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				How to measure humidity
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
The best way to test humidity levels in your house is with a hygrometer. This device, which looks like a thermometer, measures the amount of moisture in the air. Hygrometers can be purchased at hardware stores and department stores. When buying a humidifier, consider purchasing one with a built-in hygrometer (humidistat) that maintains humidity within a healthy range. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Humidifiers, asthma and allergies
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
If you or your child has asthma or allergies, talk to your doctor before you start using a humidifier. Increased humidity may ease breathing in children and adults who have asthma or allergies, especially during a respiratory infection such as a cold. But dirty mist, or increased growth of allergens caused by high humidity, can trigger or worsen asthma and allergy symptoms. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				When the air&apos;s too damp: Dehumidifiers and air conditioners
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Just as air that&apos;s dry can be a problem, so can air that&apos;s too moist. When humidity gets too high &amp;mdash; common during summer months &amp;mdash; it&apos;s a good idea to take steps to reduce indoor moisture. There are two ways to reduce humidity: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use an air conditioner.&lt;/strong&gt; Central or window-mounted air conditioning units dry the air, keeping indoor humidity at a comfortable and healthy level.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use a dehumidifier.&lt;/strong&gt; These devices collect excess moisture from the air, lowering humidity levels. Dehumidifiers work like air conditioners, without the &quot;cooling&quot; effect. They&apos;re often used to help dry out damp basements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Keep it clean: Dirty humidifiers and health problems
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Dirty reservoirs and filters in humidifiers can quickly breed bacteria and mold. Dirty humidifiers can be especially problematic for people with asthma and allergies, but even in healthy people humidifiers have the potential to trigger flu-like symptoms or even lung infections when the contaminated mist or steam is released into the air. Steam vaporizers or evaporators may be less likely to release airborne allergens than may cool-mist humidifiers. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Tips for keeping your humidifier clean
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
To keep humidifiers free of harmful mold, fungi and bacteria, follow the guidelines recommended by the manufacturer. These tips for portable humidifiers also can help: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use distilled or demineralized water.&lt;/strong&gt; Tap water contains minerals that can create deposits inside your humidifier that promote bacterial growth. And, when released into the air, these minerals often appear as white dust on your furniture. You may also breathe in some minerals that are dispersed into the air. Distilled or demineralized water contains has a much lower mineral content compared with tap water. In addition, use demineralization cartridges or filters if recommended by the manufacturer.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Change humidifier water often.&lt;/strong&gt; Don&apos;t allow film or deposits to develop inside your humidifiers. Empty the tanks, dry the inside surfaces and refill with clean water every day if possible.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clean humidifiers every three days.&lt;/strong&gt; Unplug the humidifier before you clean it. Remove any mineral deposits or film from the tank or other parts of the humidifier with a 3 percent hydrogen peroxide solution, which is available at pharmacies. Some manufacturers recommend using chlorine bleach or other disinfectants.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always rinse the tank after cleaning&lt;/strong&gt; to keep harmful chemicals from becoming airborne &amp;mdash; and then inhaled.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Change humidifier filters regularly.&lt;/strong&gt; If the humidifier has a filter, change it at least as often as the manufacturer recommends &amp;mdash; and more often if it&apos;s dirty.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep the area around humidifiers dry.&lt;/strong&gt; If the area around a humidifier becomes damp or wet &amp;mdash; including windows, carpeting, drapes or tablecloths &amp;mdash; turn the humidifier down or reduce how frequently you use it.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prep humidifiers for storage.&lt;/strong&gt; Drain and clean humidifiers before storing them. And then clean them again when you take them out of storage for use. Throw away all used cartridges, cassettes or filters.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow instructions for central humidifiers.&lt;/strong&gt; If you have a humidifier built into your central heating and cooling system, read the instruction manual or ask your heating and cooling specialist about proper maintenance.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consider replacing old humidifiers.&lt;/strong&gt; Over time, humidifiers can build up deposits that are difficult or impossible to remove and encourage growth of bacteria.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Humidifiers: Air moisture eases skin, breathing symptoms
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Humidifiers: What they can do for you and how to maintain them.
	</Abstract>
	<BenefitSummary>
		Humidifiers can ease problems caused by dry air. But they need regular maintenance. Here are tips to ensure your humidifier doesn&apos;t become a household health hazard.
	</BenefitSummary>
	<RelatedLinksBox>
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01097" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="F7DE5864-56EF-48A0-B67BCE81FEF47855" Title="Exercise and illness: Work out with a cold?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/exercise/AN01097" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN02160" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="3E154DC1-FC23-ED49-364492869F954F20" Title="Do the benefits of vitamin C include improved mood?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/benefits-vitamin-c/AN02160" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01238" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="35958F8C-2A5D-9994-E6DBF7EFD2A7FF7D" Title="Flu germs: How long can they live outside the body?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/infectious-disease/AN01238" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HQ00407" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="8113ABC9-2782-41C3-99A825A54DCDD6B1" Title="Hand-washing: Do&apos;s and don&apos;ts" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/hand-washing/HQ00407" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01755" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="FCC83C08-E7FF-0DBD-16839B0D2043FFCB" Title="Neti pot: Can it clear your nose?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/neti-pot/AN01755" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01879" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="ED283AA7-E7FF-0DBD-153DE0C4079002D2" Title="Neti pot solution: Can I make my own?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/neti-pot-solution/AN01879" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01982" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="ECED1265-FF13-A459-4C2B047E9709A0C6" Title="Echinacea: Is it effective for the common cold?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/echinacea/AN01982" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01799" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="E57C0C3C-E7FF-0DBD-13BA07E16C070DAE" Title="Honey: An effective cough remedy?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/honey/AN01799" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01455" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="D61F8B02-E7FF-0DBD-1D4A1209DBE7C777" Title="Cold symptoms: Does drinking milk increase phlegm?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/phlegm/AN01455" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01740" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="B48EA41E-E7FF-0DBD-16AB3D080DA6A304" Title="Plugged ears: What is the remedy?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/plugged-ears/AN01740" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN02148" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="7E87EACC-9889-8129-B34CF9FF468A6443" Title="Zinc for colds: The final word?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/zinc-for-colds/AN02148" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01551" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="5AC4578D-E7FF-0DBD-165C47E6A5914B0B" Title="Vicks VapoRub: An effective nasal decongestant?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/nasal-decongestant/AN01551" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01229" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="206620A6-2A5D-9994-E831783A747E7FD0" Title="Cold or allergy: Which is it?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/common-cold/AN01229" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00031" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="FFA2CF6E-5489-4E06-A01B9DFB1B4E2351" Title="Bronchitis" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/bronchitis/DS00031" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00526" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="D696BD57-F78D-4F57-824FC3F836303920" Title="Sore throat" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/sore-throat/DS00526" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="ID00036" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="8821B915-2A5D-9994-EC57A408AADC554B" Title="Cold remedies: What works, what doesn&apos;t, what can&apos;t hurt" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cold-remedies/ID00036" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00056" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="7857D5F5-3E9F-4289-918B67FA9D0E63E2" Title="Common cold" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/common-cold/DS00056" />
	</RelatedLinksBox>
</Article>
