<FirstAid xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="FirstAid.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			FirstAid
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			HQ00105
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/first-aid-nosebleeds/HQ00105
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2011-12-20
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2000-04-15
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1004" Title="Content Packages">
				<Keyword MCVID="3155" Title="First aid">
					<Keyword MCVID="3159" Title="Head and facial problems" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="3327" Title="First aid">
				<Keyword MCVID="3910" Title="Ears nose and throat">
					<Keyword MCVID="3916" Title="Nosebleeds" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			D389F1D6-12FD-4FF5-935DFA126CA43B92
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				nosebleeds
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				nosebleed
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				nose bleed
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				bloody nose
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				nose bleeds
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				epistaxis
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Nosebleeds are common. Most often they are a nuisance and not a true medical problem. But they can be both. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;To take care of a nosebleed&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sit upright and lean forward.&lt;/strong&gt; By remaining upright, you reduce blood pressure in the veins of your nose. This discourages further bleeding. Sitting forward will help you avoid swallowing blood, which can irritate your stomach.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pinch your nose.&lt;/strong&gt; Use your thumb and index finger to pinch your nostrils shut. Breathe through your mouth. Continue to pinch for five to 10 minutes. Pinching sends pressure to the bleeding point on the nasal septum and often stops the flow of blood.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To prevent re-bleeding,&lt;/strong&gt; don&apos;t pick or blow your nose and don&apos;t bend down for several hours after the bleeding episode. During this time remember to keep your head higher than the level of your heart.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If re-bleeding occurs,&lt;/strong&gt; blow out forcefully to clear your nose of blood clots and spray both sides of your nose with a decongestant nasal spray containing oxymetazoline (Afrin, Mucinex Moisture Smart, others). Pinch your nose again as described above and call your doctor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Seek medical care immediately if&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The bleeding lasts for more than 20 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The nosebleed follows an accident, a fall or an injury to your head, including a punch in the face that may have broken your nose&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Contact your doctor if&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You experience frequent nosebleeds.&lt;/strong&gt; You may need a blood vessel cauterized. Cautery is a technique in which the blood vessel is burned with electric current, silver nitrate or a laser. Your doctor may pack your nose with special gauze or an inflatable latex balloon to put pressure on the blood vessel and stop the bleeding.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You&apos;re experiencing nasal bleeding and are taking blood thinners,&lt;/strong&gt; such as aspirin or warfarin (Coumadin). Your doctor may advise adjusting your medication dosage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Using supplemental oxygen administered with a nasal tube (cannula) may increase your risk of nosebleeds. Apply a water-based lubricant to your nostrils and increase the humidity in your home to help relieve nasal bleeding. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Nosebleeds
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		How to administer first aid for nosebleeds.
	</Abstract>
	<MobileBody>
		&lt;p&gt;
Some nosebleeds are a nuisance and not a true medical problem. Others are difficult to stop and require a specialist&apos;s help. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;To take care of a nosebleed&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sit upright and lean forward.&lt;/strong&gt; This reduces blood pressure in the veins of your nose and discourages further bleeding.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pinch your nose.&lt;/strong&gt; Use your thumb and index finger to pinch your nostrils shut, and breathe through your mouth. Continue pinching for five to 10 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To prevent re-bleeding,&lt;/strong&gt; don&apos;t pick or blow your nose and don&apos;t bend down for several hours. During this time, remember to keep your head higher than the level of your heart.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If re-bleeding occurs,&lt;/strong&gt; blow out forcefully to clear your nose of blood clots and spray both sides of your nose with a decongestant nasal spray containing oxymetazoline (Afrin, Mucinex Moisture Smart, others). Pinch your nose again and call your doctor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Seek medical care immediately if&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The bleeding lasts more than 20 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The nosebleed follows an accident, a fall or an injury to your head&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Contact your doctor if&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;You have frequent nosebleeds. You may need to have a blood vessel cauterized. In cautery, the blood vessel is burned with electric current, silver nitrate or a laser.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;You&apos;re taking blood thinners, such as aspirin or warfarin (Coumadin). Your doctor may adjust your medication dosage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
	</MobileBody>
	<BenefitSummary />
</FirstAid>
