<Article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Article.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Article
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			HQ01396
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/healthy-diet/HQ01396
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2012-05-25
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			1999-01-01
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1006" Title="Lifestyle">
				<Keyword MCVID="1259" Title="Weight loss">
					<Keyword MCVID="1260" Title="Mayo Clinic diet" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			818C3AED-AA47-490A-9D4922BBC74DFD68
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				meal planning
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				snack
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				healthy snacks
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				healthy diet
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				healthy diets
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				snacking
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				healthy food
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				health food
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				snack foods
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				snack food
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				weight loss
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				fat
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				overweight
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				weight loss management
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				weightloss
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				healthy weight
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				weight and loss
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				lose weight
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				losing weight
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				loosing weight
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				weight
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				weight management
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				healthy weight
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				weight control
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				weightloss
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				weight maintenance
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				weight maintainance
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Your stomach is growling, but lunch is hours away. You could indulge yourself with a snack, but you think it&apos;s best to grit your teeth and wait for lunch. Not so, if weight loss is your goal. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Although you may feel guilty about snacking, snacks aren&apos;t necessarily bad. In fact, well-planned weight-loss diets, such as the Mayo Clinic Diet, allow for snacks to help manage hunger and reduce bingeing. Eating a healthy snack of a piece of fruit or some raw veggies can tame your hunger without ruining your appetite for your next meal. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The key to incorporating snacks into your weight-loss plan is to keep moderation and balance in mind.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Choose healthy snacks
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Select foods that satisfy your hunger, supply your body with energy and provide important nutrients. Opt for snacks of 100 calories or less to stay within your daily calorie goal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So what are some smart choices? Here are several suggestions for 100-calorie snacks:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;1 cup sliced bananas and fresh raspberries (or any fruit)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;2 cups of baby carrots&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;3 1/2 cups air-popped popcorn&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;5 Melba toast crackers, rye or pumpernickel&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons of peanuts&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;2 domino-sized slices of low-fat colby or cheddar cheese&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Know which foods to reach for
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
You can eat more of foods with high water or fiber content and few calories, such as carrots, grapes and air-popped popcorn, for your 100 calories. Choose snacks from these food groups: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fruits and vegetables.&lt;/strong&gt; Eating fruits and vegetables provides a feeling of fullness and only a small number of calories. Fruits and vegetables also provide vitamins, minerals, fiber and other nutrients.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Whole grains.&lt;/strong&gt; Whole-grain snacks are rich in fiber and complex carbohydrates, which give you energy with staying power. Look for items such as low-fat whole-grain crackers, whole-grain pretzels and whole-grain crispbreads.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nuts and seeds.&lt;/strong&gt; Nuts and seeds provide protein, so you will feel fuller longer. They are high in fat, but it&apos;s mostly monounsaturated, a healthy kind of fat. Nuts and seeds are high in calories, however, so don&apos;t eat them in large quantities.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Low-fat dairy products.&lt;/strong&gt; Cheese, yogurt and other dairy products are good sources of calcium and protein, plus many other vitamins and minerals. Choose the low-fat versions. Some yogurts have extra added sugar, so look for plain, low-calorie or &quot;light&quot; varieties.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Plan ahead to make better choices
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
With planning and a little preparation, you can have healthy foods on hand so that you&apos;re ready when temptation strikes:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Prepare and pack healthy meals at home for children and/or adults to eat at school or work.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Have healthy snacks available at home and bring nutrient-dense snacks to eat when on the go.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Before attending parties, eat a small, healthy snack at home. Then at the party take small portions and focus on healthy options.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				When a snack fills in for a meal
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
With today&apos;s busy world, healthy meals often lose out to busy schedules. A grab-and-go snack could be the difference between some nourishment and none at all. Try these ideas for healthy snacks that minimize calories and maximize whole grains, fruits and vegetables. They&apos;re all around 200 calories. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Toast one-half of a whole-wheat English muffin. Top with one slice Canadian bacon, a tomato slice and one slice low-fat American cheese. Microwave until the cheese melts.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Spread 1 tablespoon part-skim ricotta cheese over one-half of a small cinnamon-raisin bagel. Sprinkle with cinnamon if desired and top with a thinly sliced apple.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Layer a 6-inch soft corn or flour tortilla with 2 tablespoons shredded low-fat cheddar or Monterey Jack cheese. Microwave until the cheese melts. Slice into bite-sized pie shapes. Dip into some salsa if desired.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Heed your hunger pangs, but forget the guilt. And remember it&apos;s easier to choose good-for-you snacks if your refrigerator and shelves are stocked with healthy options.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Snacks: How they fit into your weight-loss plan
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Snacks don&apos;t have to be a guilty pleasure. &amp;nbsp;Discover creative and healthy ways to satisfy your hunger without sabotaging your weight-loss plan.
	</Abstract>
	<BenefitSummary>
		Well-planned, healthy snacks can complement your weight-loss plan. Here are creative and healthy ways to satisfy your hunger.
	</BenefitSummary>
	<RelatedLinksBox>
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01619" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="7CD3EB4E-E7FF-0DBD-1A0CA768270F5259" Title="Weight loss: Better to cut calories or exercise more?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/weight-loss/AN01619" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="SA00103" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="5084A5CE-ADF0-4A3B-A3D52E4DF3B91F3E" Title="Mayo Clinic Healthy Weight Pyramid: A sample menu" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/healthy-weight-pyramid/SA00103" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="SlideShow" DocID="NU00267" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="1F7E8CF3-0B32-4AF2-878A4F3AEF496B58" Title="Slide show: Guide to portion control for weight loss" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/portion-control/NU00267" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="SelfAssessment" DocID="NU00595" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="17643287-E9FA-48AC-A5366CF2F3CF81A8" Title="Mayo Clinic Healthy Weight Pyramid tool" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/weight-loss/NU00595" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MH00025" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="B691B8CF-806D-486B-90325657443BE215" Title="Weight loss: Gain control of emotional eating" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/weight-loss/MH00025" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY01646" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="51DBC886-9143-CCD9-FFAF5CE70F799264" Title="The Mayo Clinic Diet: A weight-loss program for life" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/mayo-clinic-diet/MY01646" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="NU00195" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="16871D19-D8E9-474D-895DE36CEA41A539" Title="Energy density and weight loss: Feel full on fewer calories" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/weight-loss/NU00195" />
	</RelatedLinksBox>
</Article>
