<Article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Article.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Article
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			MC00057
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/senior-sex/MC00057
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2011-07-16
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2007-06-28
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1127" Title="65 to 80 older" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1128" Title="80 and over" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1129" Title="Gender">
				<Keyword MCVID="1130" Title="Men" />
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1006" Title="Lifestyle">
				<Keyword MCVID="4781" Title="Sexual health">
					<Keyword MCVID="4784" Title="Sex and aging" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			8B59A03B-E7FF-0DBD-1E846353AAA31315
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				sex
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				senior sex
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				older man sex
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				sex tips
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				sex aging
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				sex problems
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				sex older male
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Senior sex isn&apos;t the same as it was in your 20s &amp;mdash; but it can still be satisfying. Contrary to common myths about sexuality and older adults, sexual interest is not just for the young. Many seniors continue to enjoy their sexuality into their 80s and beyond. A healthy sex life is not only fulfilling, but it&apos;s also good for other aspects of your life, including your physical health and self-esteem. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Senior sex: What changes as men get older?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
As men age, testosterone levels decline and changes in sexual function are common. These physiological changes can include:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A need for more stimulation to achieve and maintain an erection and orgasm&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Shorter orgasms&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Less forceful ejaculation and less semen ejaculated&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Longer time needed to achieve another erection after ejaculation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You may feel some anxiety about these changes, but remember they don&apos;t have to end your enjoyment of sex. Adapting to your changing body can help you maintain a healthy and satisfying sex life. For example, you may need to adjust your sexual routine to include more stimulation to become aroused.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Senior sex and health problems
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Your health also can have a big impact on your sex life and sexual performance. If you or your partner is in poor health or has a chronic health condition, such as heart disease or arthritis, sex and intimacy become more challenging. Certain surgeries and many medications, such as blood pressure medications, antihistamines, antidepressants and acid-blocking drugs, can affect sexual function.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But don&apos;t give up. You and your partner can experiment with ways to adapt to your limitations. For example, if you&apos;re worried about having sex after a heart attack, talk with your doctor about your concerns. If arthritis pain is a problem, try different sexual positions or try using heat to alleviate joint pain before or after sexual activity. Stay positive and focus on ways of being sexual and intimate that work for you and your partner.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Senior sex and emotional issues
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
At any age, emotional issues can affect your sexuality. Many older couples report greater satisfaction with their sex life because they have fewer distractions, more time and privacy, and no worries about pregnancy. On the other hand, some older adults feel stressed by health problems, financial concerns and other lifestyle changes. Depression can decrease your desire for and interest in sex. If you feel you might be depressed, talk to your doctor or a counselor.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Senior sex tips
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Sex may not be the same for you or your partner as it was when you both were younger. But sex and intimacy can continue to be a rewarding part of your life. Here are some tips for maintaining a healthy and enjoyable sex life:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Talk with your partner.&lt;/strong&gt; It may be difficult to talk about sex if you grew up viewing it as a taboo subject. But openly talking with your partner about your needs, desires and concerns can help you both enjoy sex and intimacy more.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visit your doctor.&lt;/strong&gt; Your doctor can help you manage chronic conditions and medications that affect your sex life. If you have trouble maintaining an erection or reaching orgasm, ask your doctor about medications or other treatments for these problems.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expand your definition of sex.&lt;/strong&gt; Intercourse is only one way to have fulfilling sex. Touching, kissing and other intimate sexual contact can be just as rewarding for both you and your partner. Realize that as you age, it&apos;s normal for you and your partner to have different sexual abilities and needs. Be open to finding new ways to enjoy sexual contact and intimacy.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adapt your routine.&lt;/strong&gt; Simple changes can improve your sex life. Change the time of day when you have sex to a time when you have the most energy. Try the morning &amp;mdash; when you&apos;re refreshed from a good night&apos;s sleep &amp;mdash; rather than at the end of a long day. Because it might take longer for you or your partner to become aroused, take more time to set the stage for romance. Try a new sexual position or explore other new ways of connecting romantically and sexually.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don&apos;t give up on romance.&lt;/strong&gt; If you&apos;ve lost your partner, it can be difficult to imagine starting another relationship &amp;mdash; but socializing is well worth the effort for many single seniors. No one outgrows the need for emotional closeness and intimacy. If you start an intimate relationship with a new partner, be sure to practice safe sex. Many older adults are unaware that they are still at risk of sexually transmitted diseases, such as AIDS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And a final piece of advice for maintaining a healthy sex life: Take good care of yourself. Eat healthy, stay active, don&apos;t drink too much alcohol, and don&apos;t smoke or use illegal drugs. And be sure to see your doctor regularly, especially if you have any chronic health conditions or take prescription medications.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Senior sex: Tips for older men
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Senior sex &amp;mdash; Tips for the aging man.
	</Abstract>
	<BenefitSummary>
		What you can do to maintain a healthy and enjoyable sex life as you grow older.
	</BenefitSummary>
	<RelatedLinksBox>
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01390" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="40513DDC-E7FF-0DBD-13FF3BBDFF94A5A0" Title="Testosterone therapy in women: Does it boost sex drive?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/testosterone-therapy/AN01390" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01431" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="AD8BD53B-E7FF-0DBD-11FEF7FFCA6E7B86" Title="Loss of sex drive in men: Natural with aging?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/loss-of-sex-drive/AN01431" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HA00035" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="98CEE3DF-5ADF-4979-B969A6F1268D21B9" Title="Sexual health and aging: Keep the passion alive" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/sexual-health/HA00035" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MC00030" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="671310EE-FD49-43AB-80A5A9AEB5AD7EDD" Title="Testosterone therapy: Key to male vitality?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/testosterone-therapy/MC00030" />
	</RelatedLinksBox>
</Article>
