<Article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Article.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Article
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			MH00054
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/suicide/MH00054
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2012-06-15
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2004-04-15
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1001" Title="Diseases and conditions">
				<Keyword MCVID="1153" Title="Mental health">
					<Keyword MCVID="2445" Title="Suicidal behavior" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			EF9C2BFA-C7CB-416C-A6B9EAE12EF2E00E
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				suicide
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				suicidal
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				suicide ideation
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				suicidal ideation
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				considering suicide
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				suicidality
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				suicide thoughts
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				thoughts of suicide
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				contemplating suicide
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				suicide hotline
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				suicide hot line
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				crisis line
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				attempted suicide
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				depression
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				hopelessness
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				anxiety
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				substance abuse
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				suicide warning signs
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				suicide survivors
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				suicide prevention
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				self-mutilation
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				self mutilation
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				self injury
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				cutting
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
When life doesn&apos;t seem worth living anymore, it may seem that the only way to find relief is through suicide. When you&apos;re feeling this way, it may be hard to believe, but you do have other options.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Take a step back and separate your emotions from your actions for the moment. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Recognize that depression and hopelessness can distort your perceptions and reduce your ability to make good decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Realize that suicidal feelings are the result of treatable problems.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Act as if there are other options instead of suicide, even if you may not see them right now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It may not be easy, and you might not feel better overnight. Eventually, though, the sense of hopelessness &amp;mdash; and thoughts of suicide &amp;mdash; will lift. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Get immediate help
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
If you think you may hurt yourself or attempt suicide, get help right away by taking one of these actions:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Call your mental health specialist.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Call 911 or your local emergency number.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Call a suicide hotline number &amp;mdash; in the United States, call the National Suicide Prevention Lifeline at 800-273-TALK (800-273-8255) to reach a trained counselor. Use that same number and press 1 to reach the Veterans Crisis Line.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Reach out to a close friend or loved one. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Seek help from your doctor or other health care provider.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Contact a minister, spiritual leader or someone else in your faith community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Learn coping strategies
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Don&apos;t try to manage suicidal thoughts or behavior on your own. You need professional help and support to overcome the problems linked to suicidal thinking. Your doctor or mental health provider can help you identify coping strategies tailored to your specific situation. Consider discussing coping strategies with people who know you well, such as family members or trusted friends. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You may be advised to do things you don&apos;t feel like doing, such as talking with friends when you&apos;d rather stay in your bedroom all day. It will get easier to do such things as they become habits. If you&apos;re already in treatment, go to all of your appointments and take medications as directed. Do your best to stick with your treatment plan, even when you&apos;re feeling hopeless. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Make a plan for life
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Create a written plan of action or a &quot;safety plan&quot; with your mental health provider that you can refer to when you&apos;re considering suicide or are in a crisis. Learn to spot your warning signs early, so you can put your plan into action.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Your plan is a checklist of activities or actions you promise to do so you can stay safe when you have thoughts of suicide, such as: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Contact your doctor, therapist or crisis center to help you cope with suicidal thoughts&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Call a supportive family member or friend who can help you cope with your suicidal thoughts&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Try specific healthy and enjoyable activities when negative thoughts start to intrude&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Review why your life is valuable and the reasons to live&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even if the immediate crisis passes with your self-care strategies, see a doctor or mental health provider. This will help you get appropriate treatment for suicidal thoughts and feelings so that you don&apos;t have to continually operate in a crisis mode.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a foundation for your plan, take these steps: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stick with your treatment plan.&lt;/strong&gt; Commit to taking your medication as prescribed and attending all treatment sessions and appointments&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep a list of contact names and numbers readily available.&lt;/strong&gt; Include your doctors, therapists and crisis centers that can help you cope with suicidal thoughts. Include friends or loved ones who agree to be available as part of your safety plan.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remove potential means of committing suicide.&lt;/strong&gt; This may include ridding your home of guns, razors or other objects you may consider using to hurt or kill yourself. If possible, give your medications to someone who can safeguard them for you and help you take them as prescribed.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Schedule daily activities for yourself, including physical activity.&lt;/strong&gt; Activities that brought you small pleasure in the past can make a difference &amp;mdash; such as listening to music, watching a funny movie, knitting or visiting a museum. Or try something different. Because physical activity and exercise may reduce depression symptoms, consider walking, jogging, swimming, gardening or taking up another activity.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get together with others.&lt;/strong&gt; Establish your support network by reaching out to friends, family and people who care about you and are there when you need them. Make an effort to be social, even if you don&apos;t feel like it, to prevent isolation.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Join a support group.&lt;/strong&gt; Joining a support group can help you cope with suicidal thinking and recognize that there are many options in your life other than suicide.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid drug and alcohol use.&lt;/strong&gt; Rather than numb painful feelings, alcohol and drugs can increase suicidal thoughts and the likelihood of harming yourself by making you more impulsive and more likely to act on your self-destructive feelings.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid risky websites on the Internet.&lt;/strong&gt; Stay away from websites that may encourage suicide as a way to solve your problems.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write about your thoughts and feelings.&lt;/strong&gt; Consider writing about the things in your life that you value and appreciate, no matter how small they may seem at the time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Look beyond thoughts of suicide
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
The hopelessness you feel as you consider suicide may be the side effect of a difficult situation or an illness that can be treated. This emotion can be so overpowering that it clouds your judgment and leads you to believe that taking your own life is the best, or only, option. Recognize that these feelings are temporary and that with appropriate treatment you can learn how to help yourself feel better about life again. Asking others for support can help you see that you have other options and give you hope about the future.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
By getting proper treatment and using effective coping strategies, you can learn to manage or eliminate suicidal thoughts and develop a more satisfying life.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Are you thinking about suicide? How to stay safe and find treatment
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Suicide isn&apos;t a solution. Create a plan to keep yourself safe.
	</Abstract>
	<BenefitSummary>
		Hopelessness may lead you to think about suicide. Learn how to stay safe, get through a crisis and find treatment.
	</BenefitSummary>
	<RelatedLinksBox>
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00175" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="F61D92BD-C12C-4C1E-98CE1DDC09196EA2" Title="Depression (major depression)" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/depression/DS00175" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MH00058" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="2789058A-4F26-4607-81369F33504F80BD" Title="Suicide: What to do when someone is suicidal" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/suicide/MH00058" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS01062" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="C22F27E8-E7FF-0DBD-18D04660F2EA2EBE" Title="Suicide and suicidal thoughts" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/suicide/DS01062" />
	</RelatedLinksBox>
</Article>
