<Article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Article.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Article
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			MH00131
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/forgiveness/MH00131
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2011-11-23
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2007-11-21
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1463" Title="Life stage">
				<Keyword MCVID="3524" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="3820" Title="Adult health and wellness">
						<Keyword MCVID="3825" Title="Healthy relationships" />
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			CD324595-E7FF-0DBD-18645326231FC21C
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				forgiveness
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				forgive
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				forgiving
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				absolution
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				betrayal
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				what is forgiveness
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				apology
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				apologize
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Nearly everyone has been hurt by the actions or words of another. Perhaps your mother criticized your parenting skills, your colleague sabotaged a project or your partner had an affair. These wounds can leave you with lasting feelings of anger, bitterness or even vengeance &amp;mdash; but if you don&apos;t practice forgiveness, you might be the one who pays most dearly. By embracing forgiveness, you can also embrace peace, hope, gratitude and joy. Consider how forgiveness can lead you down the path of physical, emotional and spiritual well-being. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				What is forgiveness?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Generally, forgiveness is a decision to let go of resentment and thoughts of revenge. The act that hurt or offended you might always remain a part of your life, but forgiveness can lessen its grip on you and help you focus on other, positive parts of your life. Forgiveness can even lead to feelings of understanding, empathy and compassion for the one who hurt you. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Forgiveness doesn&apos;t mean that you deny the other person&apos;s responsibility for hurting you, and it doesn&apos;t minimize or justify the wrong. You can forgive the person without excusing the act. Forgiveness brings a kind of peace that helps you go on with life. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				What are the benefits of forgiving someone?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Letting go of grudges and bitterness can make way for compassion, kindness and peace. Forgiveness can lead to: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Healthier relationships &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Greater spiritual and psychological well-being &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Less anxiety, stress and hostility &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Lower blood pressure &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Fewer symptoms of depression &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Lower risk of alcohol and substance abuse &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Why is it so easy to hold a grudge?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
When you&apos;re hurt by someone you love and trust, you might become angry, sad or confused. If you dwell on hurtful events or situations, grudges filled with resentment, vengeance and hostility can take root. If you allow negative feelings to crowd out positive feelings, you might find yourself swallowed up by your own bitterness or sense of injustice. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				What are the effects of holding a grudge?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
If you&apos;re unforgiving, you might pay the price repeatedly by bringing anger and bitterness into every relationship and new experience. Your life might become so wrapped up in the wrong that you can&apos;t enjoy the present. You might become depressed or anxious. You might feel that your life lacks meaning or purpose, or that you&apos;re at odds with your spiritual beliefs. You might lose valuable and enriching connectedness with others. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				How do I reach a state of forgiveness?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Forgiveness is a commitment to a process of change. To begin, you might: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Consider the value of forgiveness and its importance in your life at a given time&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Reflect on the facts of the situation, how you&apos;ve reacted, and how this combination has affected your life, health and well-being&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;When you&apos;re ready, actively choose to forgive the person who&apos;s offended you&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Move away from your role as victim and release the control and power the offending person and situation have had in your life&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As you let go of grudges, you&apos;ll no longer define your life by how you&apos;ve been hurt. You might even find compassion and understanding. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				What happens if I can&apos;t forgive someone?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Forgiveness can be challenging, especially if the person who&apos;s hurt you doesn&apos;t admit wrong or doesn&apos;t speak of his or her sorrow. If you find yourself stuck, consider the situation from the other person&apos;s point of view. Ask yourself why he or she would behave in such a way. Perhaps you would have reacted similarly if you faced the same situation. In addition, consider broadening your view of the world. Expect occasional imperfections from the people in your life. You might want to reflect on times you&apos;ve hurt others and on those who&apos;ve forgiven you. It can also be helpful to write in a journal, pray or use guided meditation &amp;mdash; or talk with a person you&apos;ve found to be wise and compassionate, such as a spiritual leader, a mental health provider, or an impartial loved one or friend. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Does forgiveness guarantee reconciliation?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
If the hurtful event involved someone whose relationship you otherwise value, forgiveness can lead to reconciliation. This isn&apos;t always the case, however. Reconciliation might be impossible if the offender has died or is unwilling to communicate with you. In other cases, reconciliation might not be appropriate. Still, forgiveness is possible &amp;mdash; even if reconciliation isn&apos;t. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				What if I have to interact with the person who hurt me but I don&apos;t want to?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
If you haven&apos;t reached a state of forgiveness, being near the person who hurt you might be tense and stressful. To handle these situations, remember that you can choose to attend or avoid specific functions and gatherings. Respect yourself and do what seems best. If you choose to attend, don&apos;t be surprised by a certain amount of awkwardness and perhaps even more intense feelings. Do your best to keep an open heart and mind. You might find that the experience helps you to move forward with forgiveness. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				What if the person I&apos;m forgiving doesn&apos;t change?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Getting another person to change his or her actions, behavior or words isn&apos;t the point of forgiveness. Think of forgiveness more about how it can change your life &amp;mdash; by bringing you peace, happiness, and emotional and spiritual healing. Forgiveness can take away the power the other person continues to wield in your life. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				What if I&apos;m the one who needs forgiveness?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
The first step is to honestly assess and acknowledge the wrongs you&apos;ve done and how those wrongs have affected others. At the same time, avoid judging yourself too harshly. You&apos;re human, and you&apos;ll make mistakes. If you&apos;re truly sorry for something you&apos;ve said or done, consider admitting it to those you&apos;ve harmed. Speak of your sincere sorrow or regret, and specifically ask for forgiveness &amp;mdash; without making excuses. Remember, however, you can&apos;t force someone to forgive you. Others need to move to forgiveness in their own time. Whatever the outcome, commit to treating others with compassion, empathy and respect. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Forgiveness: Letting go of grudges and bitterness
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Forgiveness and letting go can lead you down the path of healing and peace.
	</Abstract>
	<BenefitSummary>
		When someone you care about hurts you, you can hold on to anger, resentment and thoughts of revenge &amp;mdash; or embrace forgiveness and move forward.
	</BenefitSummary>
	<RelatedLinksBox>
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY00814" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="E0F45336-B87B-5407-FEA8BFFF3FEB95AD" Title="Family therapy" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/family-therapy/MY00814" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY00951" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="C479531F-936D-18DB-D681C2945E9973F7" Title="Premarital counseling" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/premarital-counseling/MY00951" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY01349" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="411B1F8A-9EF7-00F1-228FEBB642AED83F" Title="Sex therapy" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/sex-therapy/MY01349" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY00839" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="38DD38C5-FADE-C5DE-7226C80CA8806A15" Title="Marriage counseling" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/marriage-counseling/MY00839" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MH00110" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="FBC677B4-2A5D-9994-E75D5B11F4FFE139" Title="Infidelity: Mending your marriage after an affair" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/infidelity/MH00110" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="WO00044" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="FABEA7A3-032F-482F-88FB4CAA0769DC15" Title="Domestic violence against women: Recognize patterns, seek help" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/domestic-violence/WO00044" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY00557" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="43254CED-001C-3D8E-ED3C5D1AB41B8E11" Title="Domestic violence against men: Know the signs" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/domestic-violence-against-men/MY00557" />
	</RelatedLinksBox>
</Article>
