<Article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Article.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Article
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			MH00036
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/grief/MH00036
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2012-11-17
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2002-09-04
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1463" Title="Life stage">
				<Keyword MCVID="3524" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1579" Title="End of life">
						<Keyword MCVID="1581" Title="Grief" />
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			4DBCF89B-EE72-487B-AB396FAC59E1847F
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				grief
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				death
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				loss
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				grief and loss
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				dealing with grief
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				grief recovery
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				complicated grief
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				grief symptoms
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				bereavement
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				ptsd
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				post-traumatic stress disorder
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				dying
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				depression
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				mental health
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				anniversary reactions
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
When a loved one dies, you might be faced with grief over your loss again and again &amp;mdash; sometimes even years later. Feelings of grief might return on the anniversary of your loved one&apos;s death, birthday or other special days throughout the year. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
These feelings, sometimes called an anniversary reaction, aren&apos;t necessarily a setback in the grieving process. They&apos;re a reflection that your loved one&apos;s life was important to you. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To continue on the path toward healing, know what to expect &amp;mdash; and how to cope with reminders of your loss. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Reminders can be anywhere
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Certain reminders of your loved one might be inevitable, especially on holidays, birthdays, anniversaries and other special days that follow your loved one&apos;s death. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Reminders aren&apos;t just tied to the calendar, though. They can be tied to sights, sounds and smells &amp;mdash; and they can ambush you. You might suddenly be flooded with emotions when you drive by the restaurant your partner loved or when you hear your child&apos;s favorite song. Even memorial celebrations for others can trigger the pain of your own loss. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				What to expect when grief returns
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Anniversary reactions can last for days at a time or &amp;mdash; in more extreme cases &amp;mdash; much longer. During an anniversary reaction you might experience: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Sadness&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Loneliness&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Anger&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Anxiety&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Trouble sleeping&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Fatigue&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Pain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Anniversary reactions can also evoke powerful memories of the feelings and events surrounding your loved one&apos;s death. For example, you might remember in great detail where you were and what you were doing when your loved one died. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Tips to cope with reawakened grief
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Even years after a loss, you might continue to feel sadness when you&apos;re confronted with reminders of your loved one&apos;s death. As you continue healing, take steps to cope with reminders of your loss. For example: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be prepared.&lt;/strong&gt; Anniversary reactions are normal. Knowing that you&apos;re likely to experience anniversary reactions can help you understand them and even turn them into opportunities for healing.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Plan a distraction.&lt;/strong&gt; Schedule a gathering or a visit with friends or loved ones during times when you&apos;re likely to feel alone or be reminded of your loved one&apos;s death.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reminisce about your relationship.&lt;/strong&gt; Focus on the good things about your relationship with your loved one and the time you had together, rather than the loss. Write a letter to your loved one or a note about some of your good memories. You can add to this note anytime.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start a new tradition.&lt;/strong&gt; Make a donation to a charitable organization in your loved one&apos;s name on birthdays or holidays, or plant a tree in honor of your loved one.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connect with others.&lt;/strong&gt; Draw friends and loved ones close to you, including people who were special to your loved one. Find someone who&apos;ll encourage you to talk about your loss. Stay connected to your usual support systems, such as spiritual leaders and social groups. Consider joining a bereavement support group.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow yourself to feel a range of emotions.&lt;/strong&gt; It&apos;s OK to be sad and feel a sense of loss, but also allow yourself to experience joy and happiness. As you celebrate special times, you might find yourself both laughing and crying.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				When grief becomes overly intense
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
There&apos;s no time limit for grief, and anniversary reactions can leave you reeling. Still, the intensity of grief tends to lessen with time. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If your grief gets worse over time instead of better or interferes with your ability to function in daily life, consult a grief counselor or other mental health provider. Unresolved or complicated grief can lead to depression and other mental health problems. With professional help, however, you can re-establish a sense of control and direction in your life &amp;mdash; and return to the path toward healing. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Grief: Coping with reminders after a loss
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Grief &amp;mdash; After a loved one dies, reminders can reignite grief. Here&apos;s help continuing to heal.
	</Abstract>
	<BenefitSummary>
		Grief doesn&apos;t magically end at a certain point after a loved one&apos;s death. Reminders often bring back the pain of loss. Here&apos;s help coping &amp;mdash; and healing.
	</BenefitSummary>
	<RelatedLinksBox>
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY00194" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="6A932FE2-E7FF-0DBD-15A1B22BF9201628" Title="Cognitive behavioral therapy" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cognitive-behavioral-therapy/MY00194" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY00186" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="470A84D0-E7FF-0DBD-14CBD2F07ED3D45E" Title="Psychotherapy" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/psychotherapy/MY00186" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="PR00098" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="DE7A40B9-5056-4DB3-A41F7BA528851BBF" Title="Pregnancy loss: How to cope" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/pregnancy-loss/PR00098" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01649" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="540BF73C-E7FF-0DBD-1646790B2AD42B83" Title="Grieving process: Is crying required?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/grieving-process/AN01649" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS01023" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="3BA7BEF0-E7FF-0DBD-1D9EBEBA8524182D" Title="Complicated grief" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/complicated-grief/DS01023" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY02337" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="B3B298AB-D50E-91B3-61078FD26905C7DC" Title="Dealing with grief: Confronting painful emotions" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/grief/MY02337" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MH00107" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="A142418F-2A5D-9994-E9456F59CF180F6B" Title="Infant death: Grief and the path to remembrance" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/infant-death/MH00107" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MH00048" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="35568B71-C153-4323-93968861D7F9F657" Title="Suicide grief: Healing after a loved one&apos;s suicide" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/suicide/MH00048" />
	</RelatedLinksBox>
</Article>
