<Video xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Video.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Video
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			MM00586
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/carpal-tunnel-syndrome-treatments/MM00586
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2012-08-02
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2004-08-26
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1001" Title="Diseases and conditions">
				<Keyword MCVID="1134" Title="Nervous system">
					<Keyword MCVID="2333" Title="Peripheral nerve">
						<Keyword MCVID="4278" Title="Pinched nerve">
							<Keyword MCVID="2334" Title="Carpal tunnel syndrome" />
						</Keyword>
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			0E08A0B1-7228-485C-BC5B78908FB352C6
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword />
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash />
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="" />
	</Meta>
	<Title>
		Carpal tunnel symptoms &amp;mdash; nonsurgical treatment
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Nonsurgical treatments can help improve carpal tunnel syndrome, a Mayo Clinic surgeon explains.
	</Abstract>
	<Stream>
		<VideoFile>
			/video/streams/mm00586_mbr.wmv
		</VideoFile>
		<Format>
			WMV
		</Format>
	</Stream>
	<Transcript>
		&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Peter Amadio, M.D., a Mayo Clinic hand surgeon&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The most important nonsurgical treatment is looking at the activities that you&apos;re doing and making sure you&apos;re not doing any of these awkward activities with the wrist bent, strong pinching, strong gripping, that might predispose or aggravate people to have carpal tunnel syndrome. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After the activity modifications, it&apos;s important for people to remember to take frequent rest breaks, perhaps five minutes every hour, to do something a little bit different with their hands, to give their hands a chance to get some more circulation back into their hands as they&apos;re doing activities throughout the day, and to vary your activities as much as you can throughout the day. So activity modification is very important. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After that, splinting is very helpful, especially at night. Many people wake up in the middle of the night with their hands numb and tingling. It&apos;s a very common symptom of carpal tunnel syndrome. That symptom can often times be controlled by wearing a brace on your wrist at night. Wearing a brace during the day usually just makes you do things differently and may actually aggravate the symptoms of carpal tunnel syndrome because you&apos;re doing things in a more awkward fashion. But at night, splinting can be very helpful. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other time that splinting is useful is when you&apos;re driving a car or something like that where you&apos;re doing prolonged gripping, and again, the splint helps to hold your wrist in a straighter position that can be helpful. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The third nonsurgical treatment that is particularly effective is a cortisone injection into the wrist. We don&apos;t know exactly how it works, but it does seem to provide at least temporary relief in almost everybody with carpal tunnel syndrome, and in about a third of people, it can provide quite long-lasting relief. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, activity modifications, splinting at night and cortisone injections are the main nonoperative treatments that help. Vitamins, anti-inflammatory medications, fluid pills, things of those natures, don&apos;t appear to be as effective. 
&lt;/p&gt;
	</Transcript>
	<Thumbnail alt="" height="60" uri="/images/video/thumbnail/mm00586_licensingthumb.jpg" width="60" />
</Video>
