<Video xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Video.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Video
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			MM00768
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/turkey-chili/MM00768
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2013-06-26
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2008-11-19
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1006" Title="Lifestyle">
				<Keyword MCVID="1094" Title="Nutrition and healthy eating">
					<Keyword MCVID="1248" Title="Healthy cooking" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			439C4065-E7FF-0DBD-1FB694FE9BEB03B7
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword />
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash />
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="" />
	</Meta>
	<Title>
		Hearty turkey chili
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Hearty turkey chili &amp;mdash; See how to prepare this healthy recipe.
	</Abstract>
	<Stream>
		<VideoFile>
			/video/streams/mm00768_mbr.wmv
		</VideoFile>
		<Format>
			WMV
		</Format>
	</Stream>
	<Transcript>
		&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Richard Johnson:&lt;/strong&gt; Have you ever wondered what to do with leftover turkey, besides make sandwiches? Well, today we&apos;re going to make some hearty turkey chili, and this is a recipe that&apos;s going to help us enjoy simple food. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&apos;ve got some zucchini. We&apos;re just going to pop that in the oven real quick. And we have some that&apos;s been in there for about 10 minutes. So you can see, it&apos;s got some nice color, and that&apos;s what we&apos;re looking for. The other thing we&apos;re going to do is we&apos;re going to caramelize, or brown, our other ingredients as well. And to do that we have a nice, heavy pot that we&apos;ve heated. And now we&apos;re going to add a little bit of oil &amp;mdash; it doesn&apos;t take much &amp;mdash; and we&apos;re going to saute our onions. And then as they start to brown, we can start adding our other ingredients. We don&apos;t want to add our ingredients too quickly because they&apos;re going to steam instead of brown, and we&apos;re not going to get that good flavor. Now we&apos;ve also got some nice, colorful peppers. That&apos;s going to give us some great flavor. And we&apos;ve got some chopped, fresh garlic. We don&apos;t want to add it too quickly into the process, because it can brown too much and then turn our dish bitter. So, we want to be careful about that. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now would be a good time for us to add our turkey. And I always like to add my seasonings before I add any of my wet ingredients. And the reason I do that is because it brings out more of the flavor from those. So what we have is some chili powder, and I like to put a little cumin in my chili, so we&apos;ve go that working pretty good. We can add some tomatoes &amp;mdash; we&apos;re just using canned tomatoes &amp;mdash; and some beans. That&apos;s looking pretty hearty already, isn&apos;t it? Let all those things get to know each other really well. A little vegetable broth, and just a touch of brown sugar for some sweetness. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once you&apos;ve got everybody together, you want to let it simmer and intensify just a little bit and then we can add our zucchini. Now by adding zucchini to this dish, we&apos;re getting more vegetables into the mix, which is always a good thing, and our portions will be lower in calories and fat because we&apos;re adding vegetables. Cover it up and let that simmer for about 15 minutes. And what we end up with is a beautiful, fast, flavorful, hearty turkey chili that&apos;s high in fiber, lots of vegetables. What a terrific way to enjoy simple food. 
&lt;/p&gt;
	</Transcript>
	<Thumbnail alt="" height="60" uri="/images/video/thumbnail/mm00768.jpg" width="60" />
</Video>
