<Video xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Video.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Video
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			MM00723
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/lunge/MM00723
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2012-12-01
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2008-02-28
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1006" Title="Lifestyle">
				<Keyword MCVID="1090" Title="Fitness">
					<Keyword MCVID="1198" Title="Strength training">
						<Keyword MCVID="3307" Title="Body weight exercises" />
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			3FC83969-E7FF-0DBD-1007BAB62F5210AF
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword />
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash />
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="" />
	</Meta>
	<Title>
		Lunge exercise
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		The lunge is an exercise that targets the leg muscles. See how it&apos;s done.
	</Abstract>
	<Stream>
		<VideoFile>
			/video/streams/mm00723_mbr.wmv
		</VideoFile>
		<Format>
			WMV
		</Format>
	</Stream>
	<Transcript>
		&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Laskowski:&lt;/strong&gt; The lunge is a body resistance exercise that works the leg muscles. Specifically, the lunge targets the quadriceps and the hamstring muscles in the thigh, the gluteal muscles in the buttock, and to a lesser extent, the lower leg muscles. The lunge is a great conditioning exercise for many sports, especially those that involve lunging movements, such as tennis, basketball or soccer. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Nicole Krupa:&lt;/strong&gt; To do a stationary lunge, start by standing up comfortably. Step ahead with one foot and lean forward until your knee reaches a 90-degree angle and your rear knee is parallel to the ground. Then return to the starting position. You&apos;ll feel some tension in your legs. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When you&apos;re doing lunges, keep your back in a neutral position, but don&apos;t flatten the curve of your lower back, and don&apos;t arch your back in the other direction. Make sure that your knee doesn&apos;t go beyond your toes and that your knee stays centered over your foot. Don&apos;t let your knee roll inward or outward. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you can&apos;t lower your knee to a 90-degree angle, simply go as low as you can. Do as many repetitions as you can, depending on your fitness level. Stop when you&apos;re fatigued or your form begins to suffer. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For a variety, try a traveling lunge. Simply step ahead with the opposite foot rather than return to the starting position. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Remember, for best results, keep your back in a neutral position and let your knee follow your foot on the way down. Keep your movements smooth and controlled. 
&lt;/p&gt;
	</Transcript>
	<Thumbnail alt="" height="60" uri="/images/video/thumbnail/mm00723.jpg" width="60" />
</Video>
