<Video xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Video.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Video
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			MM00769
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/apple-berry-cobbler/MM00769
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2013-06-26
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2008-11-19
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1006" Title="Lifestyle">
				<Keyword MCVID="1094" Title="Nutrition and healthy eating">
					<Keyword MCVID="1248" Title="Healthy cooking" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			439F91D8-E7FF-0DBD-1C9EF1246D99CD15
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword />
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash />
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="" />
	</Meta>
	<Title>
		Apple berry cobbler
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Apple berry cobbler &amp;mdash; See how to prepare this healthy recipe.
	</Abstract>
	<Stream>
		<VideoFile>
			/video/streams/mm00769_mbr.wmv
		</VideoFile>
		<Format>
			WMV
		</Format>
	</Stream>
	<Transcript>
		&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Richard Johnson:&lt;/strong&gt; Have you ever found yourself in need of a low-fat, low-sodium, healthy dessert that you can put together in a short amount of time? Well, apple berry cobbler should fit the bill. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today, we are using raspberries and blueberries and apples. Now I also added some turbinado sugar, which is a good choice. Some people find that they&apos;re able to use less of it because it has some more interesting flavors. And we&apos;re also going to use some fresh cinnamon. And I like to grate my cinnamon as close to the time as I&apos;m going to eat it as possible because it tastes so much better. The flavors are much more intense, and I retain some of those essential oils from the cinnamon. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, we&apos;re also going to use some fresh lemon zest. And we&apos;re just going to squeeze the juice from half of our lemon right into our mix. I&apos;ll make sure that my sugar is starting to dissolve. And then we&apos;re going to add a little bit of cornstarch, and what the cornstarch is going to do is bind up some of the liquid and actually form a sauce as our cobbler bakes. We do want to make sure that the cornstarch is completely dissolved by the liquid, so we don&apos;t get any clumps. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Alright, now the next part of this recipe is our batter, and our batter starts out with some egg whites. And we&apos;re just going to want to break those up a little bit. We don&apos;t have to whip this too much. It doesn&apos;t need to be frothing like a meringue, and that&apos;s actually plenty right there. So we&apos;re just going to add some soy milk, some salt, some vanilla and a little bit more turbinado sugar for sweetness. Mix that all up really well; add a little whole-wheat pastry flour. It substitutes just about one for one in most recipes for all-purpose flour, adds some interesting flavor and it&apos;s better for us. Make sure we don&apos;t have any lumps. And our next step is to fill our ramekins with some of the batter. So we&apos;re just going to quickly put some of our fruit into the ramekins. I thought it might be fun to make some individual ones; that&apos;s why we&apos;re using the ramekins, but you can use the same recipe and make a larger one. I&apos;m just going to pour a little bit of the batter over the top. It doesn&apos;t have to cover the whole thing. You just want a little bit of accent on there, and you want some of those berries to peek through, so you get some nice color. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now we&apos;re going to go into a 350-degree oven for about 30 minutes. And we&apos;re just going to pop these in there really quickly. What we end up with is a beautiful apple berry cobbler. Healthy, low-fat, low-sodium &amp;mdash; a great way for us to enjoy simple food. 
&lt;/p&gt;
	</Transcript>
	<Thumbnail alt="" height="60" uri="/images/video/thumbnail/mm00769.jpg" width="60" />
</Video>
