<Video xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Video.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Video
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			MM00762
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/caesar-salad/MM00762
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2013-06-26
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2008-05-23
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1006" Title="Lifestyle">
				<Keyword MCVID="1094" Title="Nutrition and healthy eating">
					<Keyword MCVID="1248" Title="Healthy cooking" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			BAA1F46D-E7FF-0DBD-1AE91C6522CA36E3
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword />
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash />
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="" />
	</Meta>
	<Title>
		Caesar salad with grilled chicken
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Caesar salad with grilled chicken &amp;mdash; See how to prepare this healthy recipe.
	</Abstract>
	<Stream>
		<VideoFile>
			/video/streams/mm00762_mbr.wmv
		</VideoFile>
		<Format>
			WMV
		</Format>
	</Stream>
	<Transcript>
		&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Richard Johnson:&lt;/strong&gt; Caesar salad, one of the most popular dishes in the country. We&apos;re going to make our version with some grilled chicken. We&apos;ve started out with some boneless, skinless chicken breasts. We put it in some marinade of Italian dressing in a plastic bag because that helps to coat it a little better, for about 30 minutes. We&apos;ve got a nice hot grill. Sear these really well; you&apos;ll get some nice flavors and color. Now, because I&apos;ve been handling some raw chicken, I&apos;m going to make sure I wash my hands before I do anything else. Now while my chicken is cooking, I&apos;m going to go ahead and prepare my lettuce and get my dressing ready. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now to prepare my lettuce, I just want to cut the end off, and then I like to chop it up, just kind of roughly, leaving my pieces fairly large. I&apos;m going to rinse this in some cold water, and while that&apos;s happening, I&apos;m going to make my dressing. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&apos;ve got some fat-free mayonnaise, and I&apos;m going to add that to my bowl along with a little bit of extra-virgin olive oil. The mayonnaise here is going to carry the flavor of the olive oil really well. We&apos;ve got some red wine vinegar, some Worcestershire sauce, lemon juice. And because this is going to be a little thick, we&apos;re going to put a little bit of water in it as well, just to thin it down a little bit. We&apos;ll whip that up with our fork. We&apos;re going to use some fresh garlic. Fresh garlic is one of my favorite ingredients, and it&apos;s really easy to work with. Just smack it with the back of the knife and it peels really easily. And then we&apos;re going to use about half of this. If you want to use more garlic, go for it. I like a lot of garlic. I like to keep mine fairly coarse in this particular recipe because I like those little pockets of flavor &amp;mdash; little explosions of fresh garlic. Finish off with a little black pepper. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, our chicken is done, and the way I know that is because I used a thermometer to check it. And what I&apos;m looking for &amp;mdash; I want to make sure that it&apos;s over 165 degrees for at least 15 seconds in order for it to be safe. So we&apos;re going to want to let that rest for at least 5 minutes before we cut it, to keep it nice and moist. While we&apos;re letting that rest, let&apos;s go ahead and finish our salad. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&apos;ve got our dressing, got a nice clean romaine that we washed and drained really well. We&apos;re going to give that a couple of quick tosses. Instead of serving your dressing on the side, you really should toss it. It&apos;s going to coat the leaves more evenly. You&apos;re going to get a lot more flavor out of it and be a lot more happy. Add our croutons, give it a couple more tosses, and we&apos;re ready for cheese. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is Parmigiano-Reggiano cheese, and it&apos;s one of my favorite ingredients to use. And half an ounce really doesn&apos;t look like too much. I grated this using a regular box grater on the finest grating, and you can see about how much it has here. We&apos;re going to do a little bit better than that. By using a finer grater and grating it the very last minute, we&apos;re going to get the most flavor out of our cheese possible, so we&apos;re going to be happy with a lot less. We&apos;ll slice a little of our chicken breasts, fan that over the top, a little sprinkle of cheese, and we have a chicken Caesar salad that we&apos;re really going to enjoy. 
&lt;/p&gt;
	</Transcript>
	<Thumbnail alt="" height="60" uri="/images/video/thumbnail/mm00762.jpg" width="60" />
</Video>
