<Video xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Video.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Video
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			MM00766
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/pork-tenderloin/MM00766
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2013-06-26
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2008-10-03
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1006" Title="Lifestyle">
				<Keyword MCVID="1094" Title="Nutrition and healthy eating">
					<Keyword MCVID="1248" Title="Healthy cooking" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			A1F60308-E7FF-0DBD-1186B88F6746D7DC
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword />
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash />
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="" />
	</Meta>
	<Title>
		Jamaican barbecued pork tenderloin
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Jamaican barbecued pork tenderloin &amp;mdash; See how to prepare this healthy recipe.
	</Abstract>
	<Stream>
		<VideoFile>
			/video/streams/mm00766_mbr.wmv
		</VideoFile>
		<Format>
			WMV
		</Format>
	</Stream>
	<Transcript>
		&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Richard Johnson:&lt;/strong&gt; Jamaican barbecued pork tenderloin is a wonderful choice when we&apos;re talking about what to grill. Now, pork tenderloin is fairly lean compared to some other cuts of pork, but it does have a little fat. And you can see by the one in the back here that there&apos;s some fat and some cartilage that we&apos;re going to want to remove before we cook with this. The one in the front is a good example of that. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&apos;re going to be using a dry rub today, and it&apos;s a combination of a number of different ingredients. We&apos;ve got some ginger, some allspice, some powdered garlic, powdered onion, a little cayenne pepper, cinnamon, cloves; bring it all together with some brown sugar, a little bit of salt, and then some black pepper. Now we&apos;re going to have to work this in, rub all those good seasonings into the outside of our pork &amp;mdash; using our hands is really the best way to do it. And you just want to work that in, kind of massage it in if you will. And then we&apos;re going to want to let this rest and absorb those good spices for about 15 minutes. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Well, now our tenderloin&apos;s been marinating for about 15 minutes and has had a chance to absorb a lot of those wonderful flavors that we&apos;re looking for, so it&apos;s time to put them on the grill. So, we set up our grill with a hot side and a cool side, and we want to use the hot side to sear it really quickly. We&apos;re just going to put it directly on that hot heat, and we need to hear that sizzle. That sounds wonderful. Now pork tenderloin like that really has three sides; when you start to sear it, you&apos;ll see that. So we&apos;re going to sear it on each of three sides, about three minutes for each side. And while that&apos;s happening, let&apos;s mix up a little bit of glaze to put on top. Now we&apos;ve got some dark honey, which is really great for us and (has) some wonderful flavors. That&apos;s going to add some sweetness. A little bit of tomato paste just for a little bit of acidity and to kind of bring those flavors together. A little vinegar and a little bit more salt, and we&apos;ll stir that all up together. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All right, we&apos;re going to take a peek at our meat now and see how we are. Let&apos;s just kind of take a little quick look there. Oh, that&apos;s looking really good. So we&apos;ve got some nice color on there, and we want to turn it and set it up on the second side. So let&apos;s let that go on the second side for about another three minutes and on the third side three more minutes, and we&apos;ll be ready to move it and start basting. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All right, so let&apos;s see where we are. Looks like we&apos;ve got a nice sear on all three sides. Now we&apos;re ready to move it to the cool side of the grill. Now it&apos;s time to put a little glaze on there. Brush that on nice &amp;mdash; nice, thin, even coat. And we&apos;re going to finish it on this cold side. All right, now we&apos;ve been basting this for a few times while it&apos;s cooking more slowly, and it&apos;s time to take the temperature and see where we are. The best way to know that it&apos;s done is by using a thermometer, and what we&apos;re looking for is 160 degrees internal temperature in the thickest part of the tenderloin. It&apos;ll take about 14 to 16 minutes to get there normally. That&apos;s going to depend on your grill and how thick the tenderloin is, and this one&apos;s not quite there. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After it is done, what you&apos;re going to want to do is let it rest for at least five minutes before you slice it. It&apos;s very important because if you don&apos;t, you&apos;re going to lose a lot of your moisture. But what you end up with is a flavorful &amp;mdash; because of all those wonderful spices &amp;mdash; tender, full-flavored pork tenderloin that your family&apos;s really going to love. 
&lt;/p&gt;
	</Transcript>
	<Thumbnail alt="" height="60" uri="/images/video/thumbnail/mm00766.jpg" width="60" />
</Video>
