<Video xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Video.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Video
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			MM00765
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/grilled-pineapple/MM00765
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2013-06-26
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2008-09-12
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1006" Title="Lifestyle">
				<Keyword MCVID="1094" Title="Nutrition and healthy eating">
					<Keyword MCVID="1248" Title="Healthy cooking" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			A1F16260-E7FF-0DBD-1B503B5945D07944
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword />
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash />
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="" />
	</Meta>
	<Title>
		Grilled pineapple
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Grilled pineapple &amp;mdash; See how to prepare this healthy recipe.
	</Abstract>
	<Stream>
		<VideoFile>
			/video/streams/mm00765_mbr.wmv
		</VideoFile>
		<Format>
			WMV
		</Format>
	</Stream>
	<Transcript>
		&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Richard Johnson:&lt;/strong&gt; Everybody loves to grill out. What do you do about dessert? Well, how about some grilled pineapple? Yeah, you can grill fruit on the grill as well. We have a real quick, simple recipe for you. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We start off with a little bit of olive oil, some ground cloves, some cinnamon, some dark honey. Let&apos;s help that out a little bit. Dark honey is a really good ingredient for us &amp;mdash; wonderful flavor. And I&apos;m also going to add juice from half of a lime, about a tablespoon, and squeeze that in real good. Now that&apos;s ready for some pineapple. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, let&apos;s set that to the side for a minute. We&apos;ve got a nice, fresh pineapple. This looks really good. We want to just trim the top and the bottom. Stand that up. And then we just want to trim the outside, just following kind of an arch motion. You can get about 20 percent of your recommended daily allowance of vitamin C from just a half a cup of pineapple. That&apos;s pretty good. Now, we&apos;re going to want to cut right through the center. Lay that down flat, center again, center one more time. Let&apos;s do that to the other half. And let&apos;s trim a little bit of this core. Now you can keep the core in if you want to, some people really enjoy it. Now you also have the option of using skewers for your pineapple. Today we&apos;re not going to do that because I don&apos;t think we&apos;re going to need to. We&apos;re going to keep our pieces fairly large so they&apos;re not going to fall through the grill (grates). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So let&apos;s just toss that around in our marinade just a little bit. Now the juice from the pineapple is going to also work down into that marinade and work really well for us. Now let&apos;s just let the pineapple and the marinade get to know each other for just a minute, and let&apos;s check our grill. We want to make sure that we have a hot side and a cool side when we&apos;re grilling just because we get a little bit more control from that way. If it starts to cook a little too fast, we can move it to the cold side or vice versa. Now fruit will cook very fast because it does have a lot of sugar in it. This fruit, even though it&apos;s thick like this, is not going to take very long to cook because our grill is nice and hot. You can hear that sizzle. That&apos;s what we&apos;re looking for. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now after you have all your pieces on the grill, just close that lid down, but don&apos;t throw away the rest of that marinade. We&apos;re going to use that to glaze our pineapple as it cooks. Alright, so let&apos;s check our pineapple. Now we&apos;ve been cooking this and turning it and basting it for the last few minutes and also moving it around the grill as we&apos;re noticing where those hot spots are. And this is really looking terrific, and it&apos;s smelling just wonderful. Let&apos;s look at our pineapple a little bit. That&apos;s a nice golden brown color, and it smells good, and it&apos;s really looking nice and shiny, too. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now we&apos;ve prepared a plate to go to the table. Just using some of the pineapple top, now let&apos;s just arrange that on our plate. Now, how are we going to finish this off? One option is a little bit of dark rum; just pour that over the top while it&apos;s still nice and warm. Beautiful, beautiful. And we&apos;ll finish it off with a little bit of fresh lime zest. And we&apos;re going to get a lot of flavor out of our lime, and grating our lime zest at the very last minute. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now we have a nice low-fat, low-sodium dessert, and we cooked it on the grill. How about that? 
&lt;/p&gt;
	</Transcript>
	<Thumbnail alt="" height="60" uri="/images/video/thumbnail/mm00765.jpg" width="60" />
</Video>
