<Video xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Video.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Video
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			MM00108
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/ovulation/MM00108
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2012-06-14
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2000-11-17
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1129" Title="Gender">
				<Keyword MCVID="1131" Title="Women" />
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1463" Title="Life stage">
				<Keyword MCVID="3524" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="3625" Title="Women&apos;s health">
						<Keyword MCVID="3900" Title="Women&apos;s life stages" />
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			A0F8DEFB-36F1-4F79-B4FA68DFC12AAE0A
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword />
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash />
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="" />
	</Meta>
	<Title>
		Ovulation
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Ovulation &amp;mdash; the release of an egg from a woman&apos;s ovary &amp;mdash; occurs about midway through the menstrual cycle. See how it happens.
	</Abstract>
	<Stream>
		<VideoFile>
			/video/streams/mm00108_ovulation_mbr.wmv
		</VideoFile>
		<Format>
			WMV
		</Format>
	</Stream>
	<Transcript>
		&lt;p&gt;
Ovulation is the release of an egg from one of the ovaries. It often happens about midway through the menstrual cycle, although the exact timing may vary. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In preparation for ovulation, the lining of the uterus, or endometrium, thickens. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The pituitary gland in the brain stimulates one of the ovaries to release an egg. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The wall of the ovarian follicle ruptures at the surface of the ovary. The egg is released. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finger-like structures called fimbriae sweep the egg into the neighboring fallopian tube. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The egg travels through the fallopian tube, propelled in part by contractions in the fallopian tube walls. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here in the fallopian tube, the egg may be fertilized by a sperm. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If the egg is fertilized, the egg and sperm unite to form a one-celled entity called a zygote. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As the zygote travels down the fallopian tube toward the uterus, it begins dividing rapidly to form a cluster of cells resembling a tiny raspberry. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When the zygote reaches the uterus, it implants in the lining of the uterus and pregnancy begins. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If the egg isn&apos;t fertilized, it&apos;s simply reabsorbed by the body &amp;mdash; perhaps before it even reaches the uterus. About two weeks later, the lining of the uterus sheds through the vagina. This is known as menstruation. 
&lt;/p&gt;
	</Transcript>
	<Thumbnail alt="" height="60" uri="/images/video/thumbnail/mm00108_ovulation.jpg" width="60" />
</Video>
