<Video xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Video.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Video
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			MM00763
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/honey-crusted-chicken/MM00763
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2013-06-26
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2008-06-27
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1006" Title="Lifestyle">
				<Keyword MCVID="1094" Title="Nutrition and healthy eating">
					<Keyword MCVID="1248" Title="Healthy cooking" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			2BC16E72-E7FF-0DBD-19A2BBFFAB258214
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword />
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash />
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="" />
	</Meta>
	<Title>
		Honey crusted chicken
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Honey crusted chicken &amp;mdash; See how to prepare this healthy recipe.
	</Abstract>
	<Stream>
		<VideoFile>
			/video/streams/mm00763_mbr.wmv
		</VideoFile>
		<Format>
			WMV
		</Format>
	</Stream>
	<Transcript>
		&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Richard Johnson:&lt;/strong&gt; Our recipe today is honey crusted chicken. Children, especially under the age of 1, shouldn&apos;t be served raw honey because there is a concern about botulism. So please be careful when you&apos;re using raw honey. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, we&apos;re using some simple ingredients &amp;mdash; some saltine crackers and paprika. And to make a nice crispy chicken breast, the crackers are going to be a good addition. We&apos;re just going to crush them up with the back of our knife on our cutting board, get them so they&apos;re going to coat the chicken really well, and then just scoop them up. The thing I like about this recipe is it&apos;s low in fat and uses some common ingredients. It&apos;s simple, and I can get it in the oven in just two to three minutes of prep time. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So I&apos;m just going to mix up our cracker with our paprika for a little bit of color. The next thing I&apos;m going to do is I&apos;ve prepared a couple of chicken breasts. I&apos;ve got two 4-ounce portions. I&apos;ve removed as much fat as I possibly can from them. And then my raw honey &amp;mdash; it&apos;s just going to go into the bowl with those. I&apos;m going to quickly toss that around, kind of rub the honey in to coat them really nice. So at this point I&apos;m ready just to add my crumbs. Kind of toss them a little bit, and press them in so I&apos;ve got a nice, even coating. And I&apos;ve prepared a baking sheet with a little bit of pan spray. So I&apos;m just going to put them on that, and they&apos;re pretty much ready to go into the oven. But I do want to make sure that I clean up and wash my hands. What I&apos;m going to end up with is a nice, crispy chicken breast that&apos;s simple, low in fat, uses common ingredients, and only took me two or three minutes to get it ready to go in the oven. 
&lt;/p&gt;
	</Transcript>
	<Thumbnail alt="" height="60" uri="/images/video/thumbnail/mm00763_honeychicken02.jpg" width="60" />
</Video>
