<TestProcedure xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="TestProcedure.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			TestProcedure
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			MY00776
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/testicular-exam/MY00776
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2011-12-02
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2009-10-24
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1127" Title="65 to 80 older" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1129" Title="Gender">
				<Keyword MCVID="1130" Title="Men" />
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1295" Title="Test or procedure">
				<Keyword MCVID="3645" Title="Test">
					<Keyword MCVID="3646" Title="Cancer">
						<Keyword MCVID="4425" Title="Testicular exam" />
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			55D65447-F6C3-138B-3A6219B085521B70
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				testicular exam
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				testicular examination
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				testicle exam
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				testicle examination
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				testicular cancer
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				testicle cancer
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				testicular self-exam
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Definition
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
A testicular exam is an inspection of the appearance and feel of your testicles. You can do a testicular exam yourself, typically standing in front of a mirror. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Routine testicular exams may give you a greater awareness of the condition of your testicles and help you detect when changes occur. Testicular exams may also help you identify potential testicular problems. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you detect lumps or other changes during a testicular exam, make an appointment with your doctor. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
			<PopupMedia>
				<Thumbnail Alt="Illustration of testicular self-examination 
" Caption="To perform a testicular self-examination, grasp and roll the testicle between your thumbs and forefingers, feeling for lumps, swelling, hardness or other changes.
" Height="60" Title="Testicular self-examination" URI="/images/image_popup/thumbs/testicular.gif" Width="60" />
				<Image Alt="Illustration of testicular self-examination 
" Caption="To perform a testicular self-examination, grasp and roll the testicle between your thumbs and forefingers, feeling for lumps, swelling, hardness or other changes.
" Height="298" Title="Testicular self-examination" URI="/images/image_popup/testicular.jpg" Width="400" />
				<HTML>
					To perform a testicular self-examination, grasp and roll the testicle between your thumbs and forefingers, feeling for lumps, swelling, hardness or other changes.
...
				</HTML>
			</PopupMedia>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Why it&apos;s done
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Testicular self-exams help you learn the normal feel and appearance of your testicles. That may make it more likely that you&apos;ll notice subtle changes, should they occur. Changes in your testicles could be a sign of a common benign condition, such as an infection or a cyst, or a less common condition, such as testicular cancer.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Who should consider regular testicular exams?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;It&apos;s not clear which men should consider regular testicular exams. Though often promoted as a way to detect testicular cancer, testicular exams aren&apos;t proven to reduce the risk of dying of the disease. Testicular cancer is a relatively uncommon type of cancer. It&apos;s also highly treatable at all stages, so finding testicular cancer early doesn&apos;t make a cure more likely.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Doctors and medical organizations differ on their recommendations for testicular exams. The U.S. Preventive Services Task Force doesn&apos;t recommend testicular exams because a benefit has never been proven. The American Cancer Society recommends discussing cancer-related health issues, such as testicular self-exams, with your doctor during routine checkups. If you&apos;re concerned about your risk of testicular cancer, discuss the issue with your doctor. Together you can decide whether regular testicular self-exams are right for you.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Risks
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Performing a testicular exam doesn&apos;t pose any direct risks. However, if you notice something unusual that concerns you, the follow-up exams might lead to unnecessary worry and medical tests. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For example, if you discover a suspicious lump, you may undergo tests to determine its cause. This could involve blood tests, ultrasound exams or a procedure to remove testicle tissue for examination (biopsy). If the lump turns out to be noncancerous (benign), you might feel that you&apos;ve undergone an invasive procedure unnecessarily. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				How you prepare
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
No special preparation is necessary to do a testicular exam. You may find a testicular exam is easier during or after a warm bath or shower. Heat relaxes the scrotum, making it easier for you to check for anything unusual.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				What you can expect
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
To do a testicular exam, stand unclothed in front of a mirror. Then:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Look for swelling.&lt;/strong&gt; Hold your penis out of the way and examine the skin of the scrotum.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Examine each testicle.&lt;/strong&gt; Using both hands, place your index and middle fingers under the testicle and your thumbs on top.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gently roll the testicle between your thumbs and fingers.&lt;/strong&gt; Look and feel for any changes to your testicle. These could include hard lumps, smooth rounded bumps, or new changes in the size, shape or consistency of the testicle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While you&apos;re doing the testicular exam, you may notice a few things about your testicles that seem unusual &amp;mdash; but aren&apos;t signs of cancer. For example, bumps on the skin of your scrotum can be caused by ingrown hairs, a rash or other skin problems. You may also feel a soft, ropy cord, which is a normal part of the scrotum called the epididymis. It leads upward from the top of the back part of each testicle.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
			<PopupMedia>
				<Thumbnail Alt="Illustration of testicular self-examination 
" Caption="To perform a testicular self-examination, grasp and roll the testicle between your thumbs and forefingers, feeling for lumps, swelling, hardness or other changes.
" Height="60" Title="Testicular self-examination" URI="/images/image_popup/thumbs/testicular.gif" Width="60" />
				<Image Alt="Illustration of testicular self-examination 
" Caption="To perform a testicular self-examination, grasp and roll the testicle between your thumbs and forefingers, feeling for lumps, swelling, hardness or other changes.
" Height="298" Title="Testicular self-examination" URI="/images/image_popup/testicular.jpg" Width="400" />
				<HTML>
					To perform a testicular self-examination, grasp and roll the testicle between your thumbs and forefingers, feeling for lumps, swelling, hardness or other changes.
...
				</HTML>
			</PopupMedia>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Results
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Make an appointment with your doctor if you find a lump or other change during a testicular self-exam. Depending on the circumstances, your doctor may do a testicular exam followed by a blood test, ultrasound or biopsy. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most changes in your testicles aren&apos;t caused by testicular cancer. A number of noncancerous conditions can cause changes in your testicles, such as a cyst, injury, infection, hernia and collection of fluid around the testicles (hydrocele).
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Testicular exam
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Testicular exam &amp;mdash; Overview covers definition, benefits and step-by-step instructions for examining the testicles.
	</Abstract>
	<BenefitSummary />
	<RelatedLinksBox>
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00410" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="B864A0C5-C048-44A0-A061B69E34C63E5D" Title="Scrotal masses" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/scrotal-masses/DS00410" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00046" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="91B1CB36-2B25-4B93-8FB60CFCAC19B62D" Title="Testicular cancer" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/testicular-cancer/DS00046" />
	</RelatedLinksBox>
</TestProcedure>
