<Article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Article.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Article
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			MY00936
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-texting/MY00936
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2012-09-18
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2009-12-01
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1118" Title="Child">
					<Keyword MCVID="1123" Title="13 to 18 years teen" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1463" Title="Life stage">
				<Keyword MCVID="1533" Title="Children">
					<Keyword MCVID="3756" Title="Tweens and teens">
						<Keyword MCVID="3759" Title="Teen health" />
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			9F0EF2C9-C812-3FBA-F9D6DA9A58EE74DB
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				teen texting
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				teens texting
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				texting and teens
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
For many teens, text messaging has become an essential way to communicate. A lack of maturity can get your teen into trouble when texting, though. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Help your teen understand &amp;mdash; and avoid &amp;mdash; the risks associated with texting. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Don&apos;t allow texting while driving
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Texting while driving is unsafe under any circumstances. In fact, some research suggests that texting while driving is more than 20 times as dangerous as driving alone. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Scarier yet, texting might be an even greater threat for teen drivers than for older drivers, since younger drivers are less likely to stop texting when faced with a difficult driving situation. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Start by talking to your teen about the consequences of texting while driving, such as potentially serious &amp;mdash; or even deadly &amp;mdash; accidents. Talking isn&apos;t enough, though. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Set clear rules and consequences about texting and driving. Explain that texting while driving isn&apos;t allowed under any circumstances &amp;mdash; and that driving and phone privileges will be revoked if your teen texts while driving. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Remind your teen that texting while driving is illegal in many states. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To help your teen resist temptation while driving, you might suggest storing the phone out of easy reach in the car &amp;mdash; such as in the glove compartment or tucked away in a purse or bag. Also consider apps or other safety features that disable texting while driving. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Keep texting from interfering with sleep
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Texting after turning out the lights or going to bed can interfere with a good night&apos;s sleep &amp;mdash; especially if the messages are stressful or emotional. This can lead to issues such as lost sleep, difficulty falling asleep, poor sleep quality and daytime sleepiness. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Work with your teen to establish reasonable hours for texting &amp;mdash; such as no texting after 10 p.m. on school nights. To enforce the rule, you might keep your teen&apos;s phone out of his or her room at night. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Be honest about sexting
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Sexting refers to sending a text message with sexually explicit content or a sexually explicit picture, including naked pictures or pictures of people kissing or engaging in other sexual acts. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even if sexting seems to be the norm among your teen&apos;s peer group, explain the emotional consequences of sexting to your teen. Sexting can be uncomfortable for the sender &amp;mdash; especially if he or she is pressured into it &amp;mdash; as well as the receiver. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The possible long-term impact of sexting matters, too. A picture or message meant for one person can be forwarded to an entire contact list at any time &amp;mdash; and once it&apos;s in circulation, there&apos;s no way to control it. A photo or message could resurface years later under other circumstances, possibly causing great embarrassment or even problems with work or school. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Although laws and degree of enforcement might vary from state to state, make sure your teen understands that the possession of sexually explicit images of a minor is considered a crime. The consequences could be serious, including a police record, suspension from school or legal action. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bottom line: If you wouldn&apos;t be comfortable sharing the photo or message with the entire world, don&apos;t send it. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Be aware of cyberbullying
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Cyberbullying refers to sending harassing texts, emails or instant messages, as well as posting intimidating or threatening content on websites or blogs. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Naturally, cyberbullying can make a teen feel unsafe and might lead to school absences or other problems. It might even be a contributing factor to teen suicide. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Encourage your teen to talk to you or another trusted adult if he or she receives harassing text messages. You might also suggest rejecting texts from unknown numbers. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the flip side, make sure your teen understands that it isn&apos;t acceptable to spread rumors or bully someone through texting. Remind your teen that any text message he or she sends can be forwarded to anyone else, so it&apos;s important to use good judgment with every message. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Actively monitor your teen&apos;s messages
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Sit down with your teen and look through his or her text messages occasionally &amp;mdash; or let your teen know that you&apos;ll periodically check the phone for content. You might also review phone records to see when and how often your teen is sending and receiving texts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As your teen gets older and engages with a wider variety of people &amp;mdash; some of whom might be interested in inappropriate messages or contact &amp;mdash; it becomes even more important to monitor his or her messages. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Enforce consequences
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
If your teen isn&apos;t willing to follow the rules and expectations you&apos;ve set &amp;mdash; or you&apos;re concerned that texting is interfering with your teen&apos;s schoolwork or other responsibilities &amp;mdash; take action.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The options? 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Remove your teen&apos;s ability to text or send pictures through his or her phone &amp;mdash; or simply take the phone away. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Remind your teen that having a phone is a privilege, not a right. Preventing potentially serious consequences outweighs any anger your teen is likely to express. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Teen texting: Help your teen avoid the risks
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Teen texting &amp;mdash; How to talk to your teen about texting and curb phone overuse.
	</Abstract>
	<BenefitSummary>
		Concerned about teen texting? To prevent problems, monitor your teen&apos;s texting habits. Also set &amp;mdash; and enforce &amp;mdash; appropriate limits.
	</BenefitSummary>
	<RelatedLinksBox>
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY01100" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="70696FC7-B486-EC46-F924AA85D4BED373" Title="Teens and sex: Protecting your teen&apos;s sexual health" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teens-and-sex/MY01100" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CC00032" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="0B255027-E129-44F8-A6F18AC6CFD85DEA" Title="Sex education: Talking to your teen about sex" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/sex-education/CC00032" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS01188" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="263A2D69-E5FC-FE67-B31A8D6B7603E150" Title="Teen depression" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-depression/DS01188" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY01384" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="F55B57EB-060D-039E-A672C96756D9783B" Title="College depression: What parents need to know" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/college-depression/MY01384" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY00820" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="E6FA0432-E77E-4D2A-A4C1C7EDD509DE8B" Title="Teenage pregnancy: Consider the options" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-pregnancy/MY00820" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY00521" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="DB3CB780-DDBD-1D4B-56C2D44F36EA662A" Title="Underage drinking: Talking to your teen about alcohol" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-drinking/MY00521" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HQ00139" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="AABBC87E-1A86-46E7-9AE1F0518136CFF0" Title="Teen smoking: 10 ways to keep teens smoke-free" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-smoking/HQ00139" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY00937" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="9F1238D2-DA8F-5FED-ED0278258B98B314" Title="Teenage depression: Prevention begins with parental support" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-depression/MY00937" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="SM00045" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="9217B9F8-1C78-406D-82F6C3F96AD270BA" Title="Performance-enhancing drugs and teen athletes" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/performance-enhancing-drugs/SM00045" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="TN00016" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="8BA0D635-E7FF-0DBD-129F8CF169493637" Title="Teen smoking: How to help your teen quit" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-smoking/TN00016" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CC00019" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="7CDC4D1D-5AEC-475D-8C787638442DB8D6" Title="Teen sleep: Why is your teen so tired?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teens-health/CC00019" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY01099" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="7066CBB9-C726-8F8E-20295CA88DFA1E5D" Title="Teen drug abuse: Help your teen avoid drugs" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-drug-abuse/MY01099" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="WT00012" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="469A09F4-09D3-4A28-82112C1A70B826EE" Title="Teen weight loss: Healthy habits count" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-weight-loss/WT00012" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY01348" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="40B0C31A-FE4B-5280-6D1E0127705E8228" Title="Teen bullying: What parents need to know" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-bullying/MY01348" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY00481" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="26984A1E-E304-2141-E65804D879D445D9" Title="Parenting skills: Tips for raising teens" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/parenting-tips-for-teens/MY00481" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY01156" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="24532FA1-C14E-1FCB-925673F9574DFB86" Title="Teen eating disorders: Tips to protect your teen" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-eating-disorders/MY01156" />
	</RelatedLinksBox>
</Article>
