<Article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Article.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Article
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			MY01264
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/caregiver-depression/MY01264
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2010-07-09
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2010-07-09
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1463" Title="Life stage">
				<Keyword MCVID="3524" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1574" Title="Caregivers">
						<Keyword MCVID="1577" Title="Aging parents" />
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			AA9670CE-C399-DF07-B92D0414AA03597D
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				caregiver depression
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Caregiving is often physically and emotionally stressful. In an effort to provide the best care possible, you might put your loved one&apos;s needs before your own. In turn, you may develop feelings of sadness, anger and guilt. Sometimes, these emotions can trigger caregiver depression. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				What are the symptoms of caregiver depression?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Signs and symptoms of caregiver depression include: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Feelings of hopelessness&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Loss of interest in activities&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Irritability or frustration, even over small matters&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Insomnia or excessive sleeping&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Changes in appetite &amp;mdash; depression often causes decreased appetite and weight loss, but in some people it causes increased cravings for food and weight gain&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Agitation or restlessness &amp;mdash; for example, pacing, hand-wringing or an inability to sit still&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Fatigue, tiredness and loss of energy &amp;mdash; even small tasks may seem to require a lot of effort&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Feelings of worthlessness or guilt, fixating on past failures or blaming yourself when things aren&apos;t going right&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Frequent thoughts of death, dying or suicide&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Unexplained physical problems, such as back pain or headaches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				What can I do if I develop caregiver depression?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
If you&apos;re experiencing signs or symptoms of caregiver depression, consult your doctor or a mental health provider. Depression isn&apos;t something you can simply &quot;snap out&quot; of &amp;mdash; and left untreated, depression can lead to various emotional and physical problems. It can also affect the quality of care you&apos;re able to provide for your loved one. However, most people who have depression feel better with the help of medication, psychological counseling or other treatment. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				What can I do to prevent caregiver depression?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
You can take active steps to prevent caregiver depression. For example: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reach out for help.&lt;/strong&gt; Don&apos;t wait until you feel overwhelmed to ask for help caring for a loved one. If possible, get your whole family involved in planning and providing care. Seek out respite services and a caregiver support group. A support network can keep you from feeling isolated, depleted and depressed.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Determine your commitments.&lt;/strong&gt; Figure out what you can do to help care for your loved one and fulfill your personal obligations &amp;mdash; and what you can&apos;t. Thinking about and planning for what you can control may make you feel less helpless.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remember other relationships.&lt;/strong&gt; Caregiving can take time away from replenishing personal relationships &amp;mdash; but showing loved ones and friends you care about them can give you strength and hope.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take time for yourself.&lt;/strong&gt; Participate in activities that allow you to relax and have fun. Go to a movie, watch a ballgame or attend a birthday party or religious gathering. Physical activity and meditation also can help reduce stress.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stay positive.&lt;/strong&gt; Caregiving allows you to give something back and make a difference in your loved one&apos;s life. It may also have spiritual meaning. Focus on these positive aspects of caregiving to help prevent depression.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Remember, if you think you&apos;re depressed, seek help. Proper treatment can help you feel your best. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Caregiver depression: Prevention counts
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Caregiver depression &amp;mdash; Find out how to prevent and cope with caregiver depression.
	</Abstract>
	<BenefitSummary>
		Caregiver depression can take a toll on you and your ability to care for your loved one. Understand the signs of caregiver depression &amp;mdash; and know how to prevent it.
	</BenefitSummary>
	<RelatedLinksBox>
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HA00014" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="83E7580F-6506-4D06-B9424AC6ED1CA79A" Title="Living wills and advance directives for medical decisions" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/living-wills/HA00014" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY01231" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="2F3ED231-0C00-8975-4818600153B102AE" Title="Caregiver stress: Tips for taking care of yourself" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/caregiver-stress/MY01231" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY01266" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="AA98CBAB-9E7C-71EE-1C043F7B5C927F02" Title="Caregiving: Tips for long-distance caregivers" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/caregiving/MY01266" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HA00066" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="2742ADC3-EA48-4B6A-9D4FBC717A45FB90" Title="Senior health: How to prevent and detect malnutrition" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/senior-health/HA00066" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HA00082" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="10D115DE-2A5D-9994-E42FE0602D531AEB" Title="Aging parents: 7 warning signs of health problems" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/aging-parents/HA00082" />
	</RelatedLinksBox>
</Article>
