<Article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Article.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Article
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			MY02337
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/grief/MY02337
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2012-01-07
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2000-11-15
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1463" Title="Life stage">
				<Keyword MCVID="3524" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1579" Title="End of life">
						<Keyword MCVID="1581" Title="Grief" />
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			B3B298AB-D50E-91B3-61078FD26905C7DC
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				grief
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				death
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				bereavement
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				grieving
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				mourning
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				dying
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				grieve
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				grief process
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				coping with grief
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				dealing with grief
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				grief support
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				grief recovery
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				physical and emotional effects of grief
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				grief and loss
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Sooner or later, each of us will experience that dagger in the heart called grief &amp;mdash; and dealing with grief is a challenge like no other. How can you pick up the pieces, heal the wounds and move on with the rest of your life without feeling like you&apos;re betraying the memory of your loved one?
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Facing the unexpected emotions of grief
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;!-- mcimagecaption --&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;inlineimage right&quot; style=&quot;width: 140px&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/inline/creagane_lg.jpg&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Edward T. Creagan, M.D.&quot; width=&quot;138&quot; height=&quot;168&quot; /&gt;Edward T. Creagan, M.D. 
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- /mcimagecaption --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As an oncologist, every day I see people who have cancer struggle with death and dying. Every day, I also see families struggle with the inevitable end of life &amp;mdash; families who aren&apos;t really prepared for the avalanche of emotions that sweep over them when the final moment comes, even if they knew death was imminent.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I know how challenging and devastating the raw, intense emotions of grief can be, because it&apos;s happened to me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I went for a run one frigid winter morning nearly 30 years ago. When I got home, my son, Ed, then 18, compassionately broke the news &amp;mdash; my mother had died. Even though my mother had struggled with breast cancer and alcoholism, the news struck me like a two-by-four whipsawed across my abdomen. I felt drained of every ounce of vitality. It took all the energy I had to keep from slumping to the floor. As the hours evolved into days, it became exhausting &amp;mdash; even physically painful &amp;mdash; to make any decisions. Our family was completely unprepared for the feelings of confusion and disorganization following the news.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Easing the healing process of grief
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Painful as my own grief was, my mother&apos;s death gave me new insight on dealing with grief. Although there are no quick fixes for the anguish after a loved one&apos;s death, I learned that you can take steps to make the coping easier. Here are my suggestions:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Actively grieve and mourn.&lt;/strong&gt; Grief is an inner sense of loss, sadness and emptiness. Mourning is how you express those feelings. You might plan a funeral or memorial service, wear black, and carry a somber demeanor. Both grief and mourning are natural and necessary parts of the healing process after a loss.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledge your pain.&lt;/strong&gt; If you don&apos;t face your grief, your wounds might never quite go away. Accept that the pain you&apos;re feeling is part of dealing with grief and moving toward a state of healing and acceptance.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Look to loved ones and others for support.&lt;/strong&gt; Spending some time alone is fine, but isolation isn&apos;t a healthy way to deal with grief. A friend, a confidant, a spiritual leader &amp;mdash; all can help you along the journey of healing. Allow loved ones and other close contacts to share in your sorrow or simply be there when you cry.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don&apos;t make major decisions while grieving.&lt;/strong&gt; Grief clouds the ability to make sound decisions. If possible, postpone big decisions &amp;mdash; such as moving, taking a new job or making major financial changes. If you must make decisions right away, seek the input or guidance of trusted loved ones or other close contacts.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take care of yourself.&lt;/strong&gt; Grief consumes a significant amount of energy. Your will to live and ability to follow normal routines might quickly erode. To combat these problems, try to get adequate sleep, eat a healthy diet and include physical activity in your daily routine. Consider a medical checkup to make sure your grief isn&apos;t adversely affecting your health &amp;mdash; especially if you have any existing health conditions.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remember that time helps, but it might not cure.&lt;/strong&gt; Time has the ability to make that acute, searing pain of loss less intense and to make your red-hot emotions less painful &amp;mdash; but your feelings of loss and emptiness might never completely go away. Accepting and embracing your new &quot;normal&quot; might help you reconcile your losses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Losing a loved one is devastating. Someday, however, the sun will shine again. The day will seem brighter and your life will go on &amp;mdash; even if it&apos;ll never be quite the same.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Edward T. Creagan, M.D.&lt;br /&gt;
Division of Medical Oncology&lt;br /&gt;
Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minn.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Dealing with grief: Confronting painful emotions
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Dealing with grief &amp;mdash; A Mayo Clinic oncologist shares personal insights on the healing process.
	</Abstract>
	<BenefitSummary />
	<RelatedLinksBox>
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY00194" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="6A932FE2-E7FF-0DBD-15A1B22BF9201628" Title="Cognitive behavioral therapy" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/cognitive-behavioral-therapy/MY00194" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="TestProcedure" DocID="MY00186" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="470A84D0-E7FF-0DBD-14CBD2F07ED3D45E" Title="Psychotherapy" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/psychotherapy/MY00186" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="PR00098" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="DE7A40B9-5056-4DB3-A41F7BA528851BBF" Title="Pregnancy loss: How to cope" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/pregnancy-loss/PR00098" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01649" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="540BF73C-E7FF-0DBD-1646790B2AD42B83" Title="Grieving process: Is crying required?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/grieving-process/AN01649" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS01023" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="3BA7BEF0-E7FF-0DBD-1D9EBEBA8524182D" Title="Complicated grief" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/complicated-grief/DS01023" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MH00107" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="A142418F-2A5D-9994-E9456F59CF180F6B" Title="Infant death: Grief and the path to remembrance" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/infant-death/MH00107" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MH00036" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="4DBCF89B-EE72-487B-AB396FAC59E1847F" Title="Grief: Coping with reminders after a loss" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/grief/MH00036" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MH00048" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="35568B71-C153-4323-93968861D7F9F657" Title="Suicide grief: Healing after a loved one&apos;s suicide" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/suicide/MH00048" />
	</RelatedLinksBox>
</Article>
