<Article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Article.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Article
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			SM00045
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/performance-enhancing-drugs/SM00045
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2010-12-22
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2003-11-18
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1118" Title="Child">
					<Keyword MCVID="1123" Title="13 to 18 years teen" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1463" Title="Life stage">
				<Keyword MCVID="1533" Title="Children">
					<Keyword MCVID="3756" Title="Tweens and teens">
						<Keyword MCVID="3759" Title="Teen health" />
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			9217B9F8-1C78-406D-82F6C3F96AD270BA
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				performance-enhancing drugs
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				ephedra
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				androstendione
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				anabolic steroids
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				supplements
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				performance enhancing drugs
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				creatine
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				andro
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Carpools. Practices. Games. If you&apos;re the parent of a teen athlete, your life is probably as hectic as your child&apos;s. It&apos;s important, however, to make time to talk to your teen about the dangers of performance-enhancing drugs. By setting rules and consequences and explaining the possible health effects of drug use, you can help your teen steer clear of performance-enhancing drugs. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				What are the most common performance-enhancing drugs?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
For teens, the most common performance-enhancing drugs and supplements include: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creatine.&lt;/strong&gt; Creatine is a naturally occurring compound in the body that&apos;s also sold as an over-the-counter supplement. It&apos;s primarily used to enhance recovery after a workout and increase muscle mass and strength. Creatine is popular with athletes who participate in football, gymnastics, hockey and wrestling. Side effects include weight gain, nausea, muscle cramps and kidney damage. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anabolic steroids.&lt;/strong&gt; Anabolic steroids are synthetic versions of the hormone testosterone, used to build muscle and increase strength. They&apos;re popular with football players and weightlifters. Use of anabolic steroids can cause heart and liver damage, halt bone growth, and result in a permanently short stature. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steroid precursors.&lt;/strong&gt; Steroid precursors, such as androstenedione (&quot;andro&quot;) and dehydroepiandrosterone (DHEA), are substances that the body converts into anabolic steroids. They&apos;re used to increase muscle mass. Most steroid precursors are illegal without a prescription. DHEA, however, is still available in over-the-counter preparations. Side effects of steroid precursors are similar to those for steroids. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Why do teens take performance-enhancing drugs?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Some teens experiment with performance-enhancing drugs as a way to cope with insecurities, the difficulties of fitting in with a group of peers or a desire for independence. Others may be influenced by societal pressure to win at all costs. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Common risk factors for teen use of performance-enhancing drugs include: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A desire to gain muscle mass or strength&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A negative body image or a tendency to compare one&apos;s appearance with others&apos;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Pressure from parents or peers regarding weight or muscles&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Being male &amp;mdash; boys are more likely to use performance-enhancing drugs than are girls&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				What can parents do to stop use of performance-enhancing drugs?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
You can take various steps to prevent your teen from using performance-enhancing drugs or supplements. For example: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discuss ethics and proper training.&lt;/strong&gt; Remind your teen that using a performance-enhancing drug is similar to cheating and, more importantly, could lead to serious health problems. Explain that a healthy diet and rigorous training are the true keys to athletic performance.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be clear about your expectations.&lt;/strong&gt; Tell your teen that you expect him or her to avoid performance-enhancing drugs. Set rules and explain the consequences of breaking them. For example, if your teen uses performance-enhancing drugs, he or she has to quit the team.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get involved.&lt;/strong&gt; Attend games and practices. Encourage your teen&apos;s coaches, school and sports organizations to discourage the use of performance-enhancing drugs. Reassure your teen of your love and support, regardless of his or her competitive performance.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitor your teen&apos;s purchases.&lt;/strong&gt; Check the ingredients of any over-the-counter products your teen uses. Watch for performance-enhancing drug paraphernalia, such as vials, resealable plastic bags and hypodermic needles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				What are the warning signs of performance-enhancing drug use?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Possible red flags include: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Behavioral, emotional or psychological changes &amp;mdash; particularly increased aggressiveness (&quot;roid rage&quot;)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Changes in body build, including muscle growth, rapid weight gain and development of the upper body&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Increased acne and facial bloating&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Needle marks in the buttocks or thighs&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Enlarged breasts in boys or smaller breasts in girls&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				What help is available for teens who take performance-enhancing drugs?
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
If you suspect that your teen is using performance-enhancing drugs, talk to him or her. Encourage your teen to be honest with you. If your teen admits to using performance-enhancing drugs, encourage him or her to stop immediately and offer a reminder of the health risks. Make an appointment for your teen to see his or her doctor for a medical evaluation and counseling. Consider informing your teen&apos;s coach, so he or she is aware of the problem. In addition, be sure to tell your teen that you&apos;re disappointed and enforce the consequences that you&apos;ve established &amp;mdash; such as quitting the team. Most importantly, emphasize the healthy alternatives to achieving his or her goals. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Don&apos;t put off talking with your teen about performance-enhancing drugs. Help your teen understand the risks, as well as healthier ways to support athletic performance and a good body image. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Performance-enhancing drugs and teen athletes
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Performance-enhancing drugs &amp;mdash; Help your teen steer clear of steroids and other performance-enhancing substances.
	</Abstract>
	<BenefitSummary>
		Performance-enhancing drugs can be tempting for teen athletes. Understand the warning signs and what you can do to keep your teen from using shortcuts to improve athletic performance.
	</BenefitSummary>
	<RelatedLinksBox>
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY01100" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="70696FC7-B486-EC46-F924AA85D4BED373" Title="Teens and sex: Protecting your teen&apos;s sexual health" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teens-and-sex/MY01100" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CC00032" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="0B255027-E129-44F8-A6F18AC6CFD85DEA" Title="Sex education: Talking to your teen about sex" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/sex-education/CC00032" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS01188" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="263A2D69-E5FC-FE67-B31A8D6B7603E150" Title="Teen depression" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-depression/DS01188" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY01384" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="F55B57EB-060D-039E-A672C96756D9783B" Title="College depression: What parents need to know" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/college-depression/MY01384" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY00820" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="E6FA0432-E77E-4D2A-A4C1C7EDD509DE8B" Title="Teenage pregnancy: Consider the options" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-pregnancy/MY00820" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY00521" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="DB3CB780-DDBD-1D4B-56C2D44F36EA662A" Title="Underage drinking: Talking to your teen about alcohol" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-drinking/MY00521" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HQ00139" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="AABBC87E-1A86-46E7-9AE1F0518136CFF0" Title="Teen smoking: 10 ways to keep teens smoke-free" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-smoking/HQ00139" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY00937" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="9F1238D2-DA8F-5FED-ED0278258B98B314" Title="Teenage depression: Prevention begins with parental support" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-depression/MY00937" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY00936" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="9F0EF2C9-C812-3FBA-F9D6DA9A58EE74DB" Title="Teen texting: Help your teen avoid the risks" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-texting/MY00936" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="TN00016" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="8BA0D635-E7FF-0DBD-129F8CF169493637" Title="Teen smoking: How to help your teen quit" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-smoking/TN00016" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="CC00019" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="7CDC4D1D-5AEC-475D-8C787638442DB8D6" Title="Teen sleep: Why is your teen so tired?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teens-health/CC00019" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY01099" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="7066CBB9-C726-8F8E-20295CA88DFA1E5D" Title="Teen drug abuse: Help your teen avoid drugs" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-drug-abuse/MY01099" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="WT00012" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="469A09F4-09D3-4A28-82112C1A70B826EE" Title="Teen weight loss: Healthy habits count" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-weight-loss/WT00012" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY01348" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="40B0C31A-FE4B-5280-6D1E0127705E8228" Title="Teen bullying: What parents need to know" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-bullying/MY01348" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY00481" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="26984A1E-E304-2141-E65804D879D445D9" Title="Parenting skills: Tips for raising teens" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/parenting-tips-for-teens/MY00481" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY01156" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="24532FA1-C14E-1FCB-925673F9574DFB86" Title="Teen eating disorders: Tips to protect your teen" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/teen-eating-disorders/MY01156" />
	</RelatedLinksBox>
</Article>
