<Article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Article.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Article
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			SR00031
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/stress-management/SR00031
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2010-07-23
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2006-07-20
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1006" Title="Lifestyle">
				<Keyword MCVID="1231" Title="Stress management">
					<Keyword MCVID="3290" Title="Stress basics" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			11188EF9-E7FF-0DBD-1F000BF4D482945B
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				stress management
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				stress reduction
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				stress relief
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				acute stress
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				chronic stress
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				sources of stress
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				stressors
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				causes of stress
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				stress triggers
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
The kids are screaming, the bills are due and the pile of papers on your desk is growing at an alarming pace. It&apos;s undeniable &amp;mdash; life is full of stress. Understanding the types and sources of stress &amp;mdash; big and small, short-term and long-term, internal and external &amp;mdash; is an important part of stress management. So what stresses you out? 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Two main types of stress
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Stress is your body&apos;s reaction to the demands of the world. Stressors are events or conditions in your surroundings that may trigger stress. Your body responds to stressors differently depending on whether the stressor is new &amp;mdash; acute stress &amp;mdash; or whether the stressor has been around for a longer time &amp;mdash; chronic stress.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Acute stress
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Also known as the fight-or-flight response, acute stress is your body&apos;s immediate reaction to a significant threat, challenge or scare. The acute-stress response is immediate and intense, and in certain circumstances it can be thrilling. Examples of acute stressors include a job interview, a fender bender or an exhilarating ski run. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A single episode of acute stress generally doesn&apos;t cause problems for healthy people. However, severe acute stress can cause mental health problems, such as post-traumatic stress disorder, and even physical difficulties such as a heart attack. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Chronic stress
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Mild acute stress can actually be beneficial &amp;mdash; it can spur you into action, motivate and energize you. The problem occurs when acute stressors pile up and stick around. This persistent stress can lead to health problems, such as headaches and insomnia. The chronic-stress response is much more subtle than is the acute-stress response, but the effects may be longer lasting and more problematic. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Effective stress management involves identifying and managing both acute and chronic stress.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Know your stressors
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Effective stress management starts with identifying your sources of stress and developing strategies to manage them. One way to do this is to make a list of the situations, concerns or challenges that trigger your stress response. Take a moment to write down the top 10 issues you&apos;re facing right now. You&apos;ll notice that some of your stressors are events that happen to you while others seem to originate from within.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				External exasperations
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
External stressors are events and situations that happen to you. Some examples of external stressors include: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Major life changes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; These changes can be positive &amp;mdash; a new marriage, a planned pregnancy, a promotion or a new house. Or they can be negative &amp;mdash; the death of a loved one or a divorce.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Environment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; The input from the world around us can be a source of stress. Consider how you react to noises, such as a barking dog, or to too much or too little light in a room.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unpredictable events&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; Out of the blue, uninvited houseguests arrive. Or you discover your rent has gone up or that your pay has been cut.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Family&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; The occasional spousal spat, a teenager who refuses to cooperate or a nagging mother-in-law can all contribute to stress.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Workplace&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; Common stressors at work include an impossible workload, urgent deadlines and a demanding boss.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; Just think about going on a blind date and you probably start to sweat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Strategies to manage external stressors include lifestyle factors such as eating a healthy diet, being physically active and getting enough sleep &amp;mdash; which help boost your resiliency. Other helpful steps include asking for help from others, using humor, learning to be assertive, and practicing problem solving and time management.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Internal irritations
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Not all stress stems from things that happen to&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;you. Much of our stress response is self-induced. Those feelings and thoughts that pop into your head and cause you unrest are known as internal stressors. Examples of internal stressors include:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fears.&lt;/strong&gt; Common ones include fear of flying, fear of heights and fear of public speaking.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Uncertainty&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; Few people enjoy not knowing what might happen. Think about how you might react when waiting for the results of a medical test.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beliefs.&lt;/strong&gt; These might be attitudes, opinions or expectations. You may not even think about how your beliefs shape your experience, but these preset thoughts often set us up for stress. Consider the expectations you put on yourself to create a perfect holiday celebration or advance up the career ladder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The good news is that we have the ability to control our thoughts. The bad news is that our fears, attitudes and expectations have been our companions for a long time and it often takes some effort to change them. Strategies to manage internal stressors include reframing your thoughts, challenging negative thoughts, using relaxation techniques, and talking with a trusted friend or counselor.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Take the first step
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Recognizing a problem is the first step toward solving it. By beginning to identify and understand the sources of your stress, you&apos;ve taken the first step in learning to better manage it. Manage it, not eliminate it. Stress is a fact of life. And that&apos;s OK. You can handle it.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Stress management: Identify your sources of stress
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Stress management &amp;mdash; Understanding your stress triggers is essential to stress relief.
	</Abstract>
	<BenefitSummary>
		Your response to the demands of the world determines your stress level. Take time to consider common stressors and how they affect you.
	</BenefitSummary>
	<RelatedLinksBox>
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN02168" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="42BFA803-BAEE-25AB-8E0670108F7BF416" Title="Stop multitasking and learn how to focus" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/how-to-focus/AN02168" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY01976" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="AFDA76C9-F998-E928-3C4546E31A6A9DBD" Title="Empty nest syndrome: Tips for coping" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/empty-nest-syndrome/MY01976" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HE00002" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="99AA7BEE-2A5D-9994-E3CB19C93755C16D" Title="Headaches: Reduce stress to prevent the pain" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/headaches/HE00002" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01128" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="D647C373-9E9F-43D1-BFB5BE1408F55891" Title="Stress and weight gain" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/stress/AN01128" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01442" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="D602A979-E7FF-0DBD-1437879F210D33EB" Title="Stress and hair loss: Are they related?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/stress-and-hair-loss/AN01442" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Table" DocID="SR00008_D" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="ADA11820-E961-4379-965BB77B679CB1CA" Title="Stress symptoms: Effects on your body, feelings and behavior" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/stress-symptoms/SR00008_D" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01286" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="ACA4A132-2A5D-9994-E6C4E01A48F09A7D" Title="Chronic stress: Can it cause depression?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/stress/AN01286" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01768" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="ABD85560-E7FF-0DBD-10C087AC4FA6D796" Title="Normal stress or adjustment disorder?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/adjustment-disorder/AN01768" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="SelfAssessment" DocID="SR00029" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="47D87EFD-2A5D-9994-E3522C6D5B4F1A58" Title="Stress assessment: Rate your stress level" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/stress-assessment/SR00029" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00584" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="2D2E338B-DCF4-45FD-ADD551D9C8804E96" Title="Adjustment disorders" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/adjustment-disorders/DS00584" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00246" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="181CCBB4-A467-4D76-A3488529DC3DBEE9" Title="Post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD)" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/post-traumatic-stress-disorder/DS00246" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="SR00001" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="76F75B48-39C9-42CE-AC10563A6FFB68E8" Title="Stress: Constant stress puts your health at risk" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/stress/SR00001" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY01357" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="649C0F2F-E1B2-CA0A-604800B622E13A00" Title="How to be happy: Tips for cultivating contentment" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/how-to-be-happy/MY01357" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="SR00032" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="15AC47CB-E7FF-0DBD-1E403F470F686D23" Title="Stress management: Re-examine your stress reactions" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/stress-management/SR00032" />
	</RelatedLinksBox>
</Article>
