<FirstAid xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="FirstAid.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			FirstAid
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			WL00008
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/first-aid-blisters/WL00008
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2012-02-17
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2000-07-01
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1125" Title="19 to 44 younger" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1004" Title="Content Packages">
				<Keyword MCVID="3155" Title="First aid">
					<Keyword MCVID="3162" Title="Skin problems" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="3327" Title="First aid">
				<Keyword MCVID="3944" Title="Skin hair and nails">
					<Keyword MCVID="3946" Title="Blisters" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			E0D0ED0A-9EDA-412C-B19A74F605F72CFE
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				blister
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				blisters
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				foot blisters
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				skin blisters
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
If a blister isn&apos;t too painful, try to keep it intact. Unbroken skin over a blister provides a natural barrier to bacteria and decreases the risk of infection. Cover a small blister with an adhesive bandage, and cover a large one with a porous, plastic-coated gauze pad that absorbs moisture and allows the wound to breathe. If you&apos;re allergic to the adhesive used in some tape, use paper tape.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Don&apos;t puncture a blister unless it&apos;s painful or prevents you from walking or using one of your hands. If you have diabetes or poor circulation, call your doctor before considering the self-care measures below.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;How to drain a blister&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;To relieve blister-related pain, drain the fluid while leaving the overlying skin intact. Here&apos;s how:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wash your hands and the blister&lt;/strong&gt; with soap and warm water.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Swab the blister&lt;/strong&gt; with iodine or rubbing alcohol.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sterilize a clean, sharp needle&lt;/strong&gt; by wiping it with rubbing alcohol.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use the needle to puncture the blister.&lt;/strong&gt; Aim for several spots near the blister&apos;s edge. Let the fluid drain, but leave the overlying skin in place.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apply an antibiotic ointment&lt;/strong&gt; to the blister and cover with a bandage or gauze pad.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cut away all the dead skin&lt;/strong&gt; after several days, using tweezers and scissors sterilized with rubbing alcohol. Apply more ointment and a bandage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Call your doctor if you see signs of infection around a blister &amp;mdash; pus, redness, increasing pain or warm skin.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Blister prevention&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;To prevent a blister, use gloves, socks, a bandage or similar protective covering over the area being rubbed. Special athletic socks are available that have extra padding in critical areas. You might also try attaching moleskin to the inside of your shoe where it might rub, such as at the heel.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Blisters
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		How to administer first aid for blisters.
	</Abstract>
	<MobileBody>
		&lt;p&gt;
If a blister isn&apos;t too painful, leave it unbroken and protect it with an adhesive bandage.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If the blister is painful:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wash your hands and the blister&lt;/strong&gt; with soap and warm water.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Swab the blister&lt;/strong&gt; with rubbing alcohol.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sterilize a clean, sharp needle&lt;/strong&gt; by wiping it with rubbing alcohol.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use the needle to puncture the blister.&lt;/strong&gt; Aim for several spots near the blister&apos;s edge. Let the fluid drain, but leave the overlying skin in place. Apply an antibiotic ointment and cover with a bandage.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cut away all the dead skin&lt;/strong&gt; after several days, using tweezers and scissors sterilized with rubbing alcohol. Apply more ointment and a bandage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you have diabetes or poor circulation, call your doctor before considering these self-care measures. Also call your doctor if you see signs of infection around a blister.
&lt;/p&gt;
	</MobileBody>
	<BenefitSummary />
</FirstAid>
