<Article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="Article.xsd">
	<Meta>
		<Attribution Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com">
			Content provided by MayoClinic.com
		</Attribution>
		<ContentType>
			Article
		</ContentType>
		<CopyrightOwner DocID="MayoCopyright">
			33DF435C-58F5-47FE-B83E25C1B9EA9A15
		</CopyrightOwner>
		<DocID>
			WO00128
		</DocID>
		<OriginalURL>
			http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/belly-fat/WO00128
		</OriginalURL>
		<UpdateDate>
			2011-04-16
		</UpdateDate>
		<PublicationDate>
			2007-04-16
		</PublicationDate>
		<ControlWords>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1126" Title="45 to 64 middle" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1000" Title="Age">
				<Keyword MCVID="1124" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="1127" Title="65 to 80 older" />
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1129" Title="Gender">
				<Keyword MCVID="1131" Title="Women" />
			</Category>
			<Category MCVID="1463" Title="Life stage">
				<Keyword MCVID="3524" Title="Adult">
					<Keyword MCVID="3625" Title="Women&apos;s health">
						<Keyword MCVID="3900" Title="Women&apos;s life stages" />
					</Keyword>
				</Keyword>
			</Category>
		</ControlWords>
		<ObjectID>
			6B90797A-E7FF-0DBD-14568428CBB7C25D
		</ObjectID>
		<MayoVersion>
			4
		</MayoVersion>
		<MetaKeywords>
			<MetaKeyword>
				belly fat
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				abdominal fat
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				tummy fat
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				women
			</MetaKeyword>
			<MetaKeyword>
				menopause
			</MetaKeyword>
		</MetaKeywords>
		<HasFlash>
			0
		</HasFlash>
		<Source />
		<TermsOfUse DocID="AM00021" />
	</Meta>
	<Body>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead />
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
An expanding waistline is sometimes considered the price of getting older. For women, this might be especially true after menopause, when body fat tends to shift from the arms, legs and hips to the abdomen. Yet an increase in belly fat can do more than make it hard to zip up your jeans. Research indicates that belly fat also increases the risk of cardiovascular disease, diabetes, certain cancers &amp;mdash; even premature death. The good news? The threats posed by belly fat can be cut down to size.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				What&apos;s behind belly fat
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
Your weight is largely determined by how you balance the calories you eat with the energy you burn. If you eat too much and exercise too little, you&apos;re likely to pack on excess pounds &amp;mdash; including belly fat. However, aging also plays a role. Muscle mass gradually diminishes with age, and fat accounts for a greater percentage of your weight. Less muscle mass also decreases the rate at which your body uses calories, which can make it more challenging to maintain a healthy weight or lose excess pounds.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In addition, many women notice an increase in belly fat as they get older &amp;mdash; even if they aren&apos;t gaining weight. This is likely due to a decreasing level of estrogen, which appears to influence where fat is distributed in the body. The tendency to gain or carry weight around the waist &amp;mdash; have an &quot;apple&quot; rather than a &quot;pear&quot; shape &amp;mdash; can have a genetic component as well.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Why belly fat is more than skin deep
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
The trouble with belly fat is that it&apos;s not limited to the extra layer of padding located just below the skin (subcutaneous fat). It also includes visceral fat &amp;mdash; which lies deep inside your abdomen, surrounding your internal organs. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Although subcutaneous fat poses cosmetic concerns, visceral fat is associated with far more dangerous health consequences. That&apos;s because an excessive amount of visceral fat produces hormones and other substances that can raise blood pressure, negatively alter good and bad cholesterol levels and impair the body&apos;s ability to use insulin (insulin resistance). An excessive amount of any fat, including visceral fat, also boosts estrogen levels. All of this can increase the risk of serious health problems, including: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Cardiovascular disease&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Stroke&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Type 2 diabetes&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Breast cancer&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Colorectal cancer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Recent research also has associated belly fat with an increased risk of premature death &amp;mdash; regardless of overall weight. In fact, some studies have found that even when women were considered a normal weight based on standard body mass index (BMI) measurements, a large waistline increased the risk of dying of cardiovascular disease, cancer and other causes. 
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
			<PopupMedia>
				<Thumbnail Alt="Illustration showing where belly fat accumulates
" Caption="Subcutaneous fat is the belly fat you can feel if you pinch excess skin and tissue around your middle. Visceral fat, which is more dangerous, is belly fat that accumulates in your abdomen in the spaces between your organs. Too much visceral fat increases the risk of serious health problems, including cardiovascular disease, stroke, type 2 diabetes, breast cancer and colorectal cancer.
" Height="60" Title="Belly fat" URI="/images/image_popup/thumbs/mcdc7_belly_fatthu.jpg" Width="60" />
				<Image Alt="Illustration showing where belly fat accumulates
" Caption="Subcutaneous fat is the belly fat you can feel if you pinch excess skin and tissue around your middle. Visceral fat, which is more dangerous, is belly fat that accumulates in your abdomen in the spaces between your organs. Too much visceral fat increases the risk of serious health problems, including cardiovascular disease, stroke, type 2 diabetes, breast cancer and colorectal cancer.
" Height="418" Title="Belly fat" URI="/images/image_popup/mcdc7_belly_fat.jpg" Width="400" />
				<HTML>
					Subcutaneous fat is the belly fat you can feel if you pinch excess skin and tissue around your middle. Visceral fat, which is more dangerous, is belly fat that accumulates in your abdomen in the ...
				</HTML>
			</PopupMedia>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Measuring your middle
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
So how do you know if you have too much belly fat? Simply measure your waist:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Place a tape measure around your bare stomach, just above your hipbone.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Pull the tape measure until it fits snugly around you, but doesn&apos;t push into your skin.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Make sure the tape measure is level all the way around.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Relax, exhale and measure your waist, resisting the urge to suck in your stomach.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For women, a waist measurement of 35 inches (89 centimeters) or more indicates an unhealthy concentration of belly fat and a greater risk of problems such as heart disease, high blood pressure and type 2 diabetes. For men, a waist measurement of 40 inches (102 centimeters) or more is considered cause for concern.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<SectionHead>
				Trimming the fat
			</SectionHead>
			<HTML>
				&lt;p&gt;
You can tone abdominal muscles with crunches or other targeted abdominal exercises, but these exercises won&apos;t get rid of belly fat. Fortunately, however, visceral fat responds to the same diet and exercise strategies that can help you shed excess pounds and lower your total body fat. To fight back the bulge, stick to the basics:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eat a healthy diet.&lt;/strong&gt; Emphasize plant-based foods, such as fruits, vegetables and whole grains, and choose lean sources of protein and low-fat dairy products. Limit saturated fat, found in meat and high-fat dairy products, such as cheese and butter. Choose moderate amounts of monounsaturated and polyunsaturated fats &amp;mdash; found in fish, nuts and certain vegetable oils &amp;mdash; instead.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep portion sizes in check.&lt;/strong&gt; Even when you&apos;re making healthy choices, calories add up. At home, slim down your portion sizes. In restaurants, share meals &amp;mdash; or eat half your meal and take the rest home for another day.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Include physical activity in your daily routine.&lt;/strong&gt; For most healthy adults, the Department of Health and Human Services recommends moderate aerobic activity, such as brisk walking, for at least 150 minutes a week or vigorous aerobic activity, such as jogging, for at least 75 minutes a week. In addition, strength training exercises are recommended at least twice a week. If you want to lose weight or meet specific fitness goals, you may need to exercise more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To lose excess fat and keep it from coming back, aim for slow and steady weight loss &amp;mdash; up to 2 pounds (1 kilogram) a week. Consult your doctor for help getting started and staying on track. Your patience and effort will pay off in a lifetime of better health.
&lt;/p&gt;
			</HTML>
		</Section>
	</Body>
	<Title>
		Belly fat in women: Taking &amp;mdash; and keeping &amp;mdash; it off
	</Title>
	<Abstract>
		Belly fat is more common after menopause. Here&apos;s why &amp;mdash; and how to keep it off.
	</Abstract>
	<BenefitSummary>
		What does your waistline say about your health? Find out why belly fat is more common after menopause, what dangers it poses &amp;mdash; and what to do about it.
	</BenefitSummary>
	<RelatedLinksBox>
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01999" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="D9F05B8D-B7B0-DB95-1BAEBCBDC59E7DC9" Title="Asthma: Why are symptoms worse during my period?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/asthma/AN01999" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY02015" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="A161A133-A9B2-924A-9CE86A23249FD9B2" Title="Breast-feeding nutrition: Tips for moms" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/breastfeeding-nutrition/MY02015" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HE00003" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="99F213B1-2A5D-9994-E6CE49D8A51AD634" Title="Headaches and hormones: What&apos;s the connection?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/headaches/HE00003" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="DA00038" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="167CE011-22E6-46C5-BC2634387D8E47AC" Title="Diabetes and menopause: A twin challenge" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/diabetes/DA00038" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Answer" DocID="AN01770" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="ABD995B4-E7FF-0DBD-11327A43DC65FF7B" Title="Menstrual cup: Good alternative to tampons?" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/menstrual-cup/AN01770" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Video" DocID="MM00108" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="A0F8DEFB-36F1-4F79-B4FA68DFC12AAE0A" Title="Video: Ovulation" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/ovulation/MM00108" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00119" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="FDA7CB3A-4F3C-4FDB-9FDD926923BCDCB9" Title="Menopause" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/menopause/DS00119" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00394" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="B7ACC24F-E124-4B69-A0231E7FEB5ECEC8" Title="Menorrhagia (heavy menstrual bleeding)" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/menorrhagia/DS00394" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00554" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="AD5A5A12-B388-40F4-B8073113B0A8BF4E" Title="Perimenopause" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/perimenopause/DS00554" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00134" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="95C74A46-AC0A-405D-AEC831A8F66C8CF4" Title="Premenstrual syndrome (PMS)" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/premenstrual-syndrome/DS00134" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Disease" DocID="DS00506" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="79750BA2-8034-4A38-BA3288C1B2EA8FE8" Title="Menstrual cramps" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/menstrual-cramps/DS00506" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="HQ01076" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="7878C26C-47F2-4F1F-BF04FCEB2D9C6589" Title="Menopause weight gain: Stop the middle age spread" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/menopause-weight-gain/HQ01076" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="WO00130" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="38B56C01-E7FF-0DBD-12D1C37EBADFED16" Title="Water retention: Relieve this premenstrual symptom" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/water-retention/WO00130" />
		<LinkItem ContentType="Article" DocID="MY00478" LinkType="Internal" ObjectID="227487BD-A497-31CD-C81E1398182F51BA" Title="Fitness tips for menopause: Why fitness counts" Url="http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/fitness-tips-for-menopause/MY00478" />
	</RelatedLinksBox>
</Article>
